<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-alaska-gold-rush</id>
    <results>
    <!-- 1 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn99021999/1890-05-04/ed-1/seq-5/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE GOLD FIELDS OF ALASKA
          Since the acquisition of Alaska in 1867 public attention in regard to it has been mainly directed to the salmon fisheries in its waters and to the seal rookeries in Behring sea. The value of the country as a dependency has been wholly determined by the public from the rental which the Priboloff islands yield to the national treasury. Few references in the intervening period have been made by public journals and in the periodical literature of the country to the gold-yielding capabilities of Alaska, or to the degree of development already reached.
  The truth is that hundreds of thousands of intelligent Americans are profoundly ignorant of the fact that some of the largest and most profitable gold mining enterprises within the limits of the United States are conducted in Alaska.
  Gold in variable quantities and under different conditions has been found in three principal districts of Alaska-the
  Juneau and Douglass Island district, 180 miles northeast of Sitka and bordering Gasteneaux channel, a narrow inlet which separates Douglass island from the mainland; the Sitka district, the quartz deposits of which are found at Silver bay, a narrow, tortuous arm of the Pacific, indenting Baranoft island, and in the valley of the Yukon river in western Alaska. Gold bearing quartz has also been found at Unga island, one of the smaller of the Aleutian group, and some egort has been made there at development, but more of that hereafter.
  As concerns the Yukon valley, little attention has been paid by explorers and prospectors to discover gold bearing
  quartz, and the only results, so far, relate to placer mining. At the head of Lynn canal, one of the inner passages adapted to steamer navigation, about 300 miles northeast of Sitka, is the mouth of the Chilcatl river, navigable for canoes for a score of miles. At the head of this canoe navigation are three large Chilcatl villages, and it is at this point where commences what is known as the Chilcatl Portage, across the range to the head waters of the Yukon river in
  British territory. The distance from the Indian villages on the American side of the divide to the first lake, the source of the Yukon, is about thirty miles, but the source is one of the most difficult in the territory, yet the only practicable one to reach the Yukon valley from the south. During the past three years the reports that the bars of the Yukon and its tributaries, Stewart and Pelly rivers, and Forty-Mile creek were rich in placer gold, have induced several Alaska miners to venture across the range, at the Chilcatl crossing and descend these streams. Several parties are all known to have perished in this perilous search for the new gold fields. 
  In the history of gold mining in the states and territories, no obstacle was so stubborn that it was not finally over-come. This, too, will be the history of the gold fields of western Alaska. Army officers who have served in the territory at various times, are now endeavoring to induce congress to authorize an exploration of the Yukon Valley from its source to its mouth, and express a willingness to undergo the evident hardships and privations of such an undertaking. The reports of the fertility of certain large portions of that great valley, and respecting its agricultural possibilities are so conflicting and uncertain, that it can hardly be regarded as an absolute waste of money to authorize an intelligent official examination of those valleys to that end.
  The permanent development of gold mining in Alaska has been made in the southeastern part of the territory, which embraces all that strip of mainland, thirty miles wide from Portland channel at the southern boundary to the vicinity of Mt. St. Elias and including the islands of the Alexandrian Archipelago, which hug the mainland closely from south to north and west. The topography of this section is characteristic and remarkable. The thirty-mile strip of mainland belonging to the United States is no more than an unbroken range of very, steep and lofty mountains, the summits of many of which are never free from snow. No valleys separate or break the continuity of these ranges. At intervals short, swift streams, fed by the interior glaciers, have worn down waterways to the bays and inlets, but these streams, in most instances, are only wild cascades. Rarely one finds the gorge, the streambed, wider than a space sufficient for the passage of the water; and in attempting to ascend to their sources, one is confronted by tierce torrents impossible to stem, and with no margin by their sides, along which to pass around the cataracts. Frequently the last leap is made only a few rods from the point where the river enters the sea, and this is even the rule. All the islands off the coast southern Alaska, Baranoft, Admiralty, Douglass and Prince of Wales are simply mountains rising out of the Pacific, whose interiors are vast glacial formations, while their fronts to the sea are clothed with timber. No white men has ever been heard of having crossed either of these islands, and the Indians disclaim ever having attempted it, preferring the easier mode of passing around them in their canoes.
  The faces of the mountains toward the water, on the mainland and on the islands of southeastern Alaska, are very steep, almost perpendicular, and covered with a deep, spongy bog or tundra, which is always wet or moist. They are also covered with forests of fir, spruce, hemlock, yellow cedar and & scrub birch and alder, up to the snow-line, and this undergrowth of birch, salmon berry, alder and devil's club makes everywhere almost impassible thickets and jungles. These topographical conditions must be borne in mind constantly, in considering the mining development and possibilities of Alaska, for they figure largely in estimating the present progress of the industry.
  Gold quartz was first discovered in the territory in 1877, near Silver Bay, in the vicinity of Sitka. The discoverer, Mr.
  Haley, was a soldier discharged from the regular army, and previous to his enlistment, had mined in Colorado and California. Numerous quartz lodes are located in the vicinity of his discovery, which is about three miles back from the beach, and far up the side of the mountain. Haley opened several tunnels and exposed valuable quartz, and succeeded in selling two of his discoveries for fifteen thousand dollars. 
  The proprietors of another lode some distance from the original discovery put up a five-stamp mill; but for the want of adequate capital to place the enterprise on a square footing, conjoined with feeble and incompetent management, the project went to pieces, the mill was sold by the marshal and is now corroding to ruin in the rain and snow. Another company, organized under the laws of Wisconsin, have become the owners of the "Lucky Chance," and with a five-stamp mill are making satisfactory milling tests, preparatory to a liberal and adequate investment in a plant coming year. Water for power in that group is abundant all the year round, and owing to the mildness of the winters at Sitka, through the trend of the Japan current, milling operations will seldom if ever be interrupted by freezing weather. Ore has been taken out of ledges in the Sitka group, yielding $40 a ton; but numerous tests made demonstrate that the fair average is about $10 a ton. All the work and exploration done up to this time, in this basin, has been of the crudest, most careless and unsatisfactory character. No definite policy of prospecting and exploration in any part of the territory has ever been adopted, and where discoveries have been made they were merely accidental.
  Those owning and controlling these valuable interests have hitherto been unable to inspire that confidence in the future of their properties which is necessary to induce capital to even closely investigate their value and possibilities.
  The manner of developing this and other similar mining localities in Nebraska will be referred to again, when considering the larger and more thoroughly worked mining district of Juneau and Douglass Island. It is to the latter that we must look for the most satisfactory results, and by noting what has already been accomplished in that field, possibly predict whether the gold yield of Alaska will be permanent and profitable, or only fitful and spasmodic.

  Juneau and Douglass Island are 180 miles northeast of Sitka, and reached from the latter place by the inner passages of Peril and Catham straits, und Gasteneaux channel, which separates Douglass island from the mainland. In 1880, that section of southern Alaska was without a single white inhabitant, and was one of the most forbidding portions of the earth. In October of that year Mr. N. A. Tuller, in charge of the affairs of the Northwest trading company at Sitka, became aware of the fact that Auk and Tarku Indians, whose villages were on the mainland at Gasteneaux  channel, possessed a tradition of the existence of gold in some of the deep basin of the mountains in that vicinity. One particular basin was designated as containing abundance of this treasure. Having faith in the story, Fuller fitted out a canoe expedition for the purpose of testing his belief. It was intrusted to a Canadian French miner, Joseph Juneau, the nephew of the founder of Milwaukee, and who had visited all the gold mines from Arizona and Old Mexico in the south, to Cassiar, in British Columbia, in the north. Juneau was accompanied by two Sitkan Indians as guides, and after ten days of a tempestuous canoe voyage up Chatham Straits, landed near the site of the present town now bearing his name, and proceeded to follow the difficult course of Gold creek, the outlet to Silver Bow basin, until he reached the head of a gulch filled with glacier ice. Passing down the gulch, Juneau discovered some quartz laid bare and protruding into the ravine, and an examination showed at once that it was rich in gold, so rich that the free gold was apparent in many places where the rock was fractured. Claims were staked off, the party returned to Sitka, and reported their success to Mr. Fuller. The secret could not be long kept. Before spring had fairly opened several hundred miners were on the ground, and the nucleus of a prosperous mining camp created. 
  When the snow disappeared from the basin , with its area of a thousand acres or more , with mountain walls for its steep sides , it was found that centuries of erosion had created in that contracted area one of the richest placer mines
  over worked. Though of limited area it equaled in richness many of the old California placers.
  No civil government was formed in Alaska until more than three years afterward , but in the spring of 1881 the 250 hardy old minors who had explored nearly every region where gold had hitherto been found, met and adopted a code of mining laws which became obligatory upon every miner in the district.
  Half a dozen beautiful glacial streams poured from the sides of the mountains, hemming in Silver Bow basin and feeding the rapid torrent of Gold crook , furnished abundance of water for gold washing, and before that summer ended fully $1,000 in gold dust had been taken out, and still only a meagre impression made, Quite $1,000,000 in dust have been washed out of the sand and dirt of that one basin in the intervening years, and the surface is now practically worked out. Pay gravel exists, however to a considerable depth on the floor of the basin, and a now company has run a tunnel through one of the environing ridges, for the purpose of mining by the hydraulic process. Two stamp mills are also in operation upon quartz the mine ground, and a roadway, two and a half miles long, and costing $13,000 has been completed, so as to connect the mines with the channel beach. A flourishing town of 1,500 white inhabitants has grown up about this mining location, with schools , churches and many of the comforts of civilization.
  The development of mining on that portion of the mainland of south-eastern Alaska has just fairly commenced. Every indication points to the inexhaustible character of the gold quartz deposits, and though there is nothing of a high grade, or of fabulous richness, yet it is manifest that mining carried on bore with adequate capital, ample plants and conservative methods insures that this section of Alaska will have indefinite period of prosperity as a mining district. Farther on I shall speak of what is requisite in order to make the handling of these low grade ores of Alaska remunerative.
  About three miles to the eastward of the town , and up the gulch of Snoop's Creek, recent discoveries of quartz have
  also been made , equaling those in Siver Bow Basin. No mills have been yet erected to work these deposits of gold-
  bearing rock , but considerable quantities have been shipped to Seattle and Portland, and refilled with fair profits to
  the owners of the mines. Though explorations have been frequently made to discover silver in the territory, none was
  found until the winter of 1888 , when a fine rich voin of galena was discovered in the Sheep's Creole gulch already
  alluded to. It is reported by credible persons as having yielded $130 per ton In the smelter at Portland.
  Soon after the gold discoveries on the mainland at Juneau , prospectors crossed over to Douglas Island, only two miles distant. Here was found abundance of placer gold, on the face of the mountain which rises directly out of the water at nearly all points along the shore, but at this particular place recedes from the beach, leaving a stretch of low land more than a mile long and a few hundred foot wide. While some were engaged in washing the dirt, others began to search for quartz lodes In the same vicinity, and on the face of the same mountain. The indications wore fair, but putting in the necessary tunnels for exploration was expensive and those engaged soon became discouraged. John
  Treadwell , who had been a successful contractor and builder in San Francisco, was attracted to Alaska by exaggerated tales of fabulous bonanzas, and touching at Douglas Island, found the owners to several quartz claims ready to abandon their rights, fully disheartened. Treadwell purchased their interests and improvements for a small
  amount, and with faith, energy and resources pushed the explorations already begun to a conclusion.
  For many months ho was the butt of every old miner's ridicule in all that region. At last he pierced a ledge of gold bearing rock 400 feet wide, over 800 feet deep from the surface and more than 9,000 feet in length from east to west. This, in fact, became the great Treadwell gold mine, now operated by the Alaska Mining and Milling company. He was soon able to convince capitalists that he had something in which it would pay to invest, and the company was organized in 1881, with Senator Jones of Nevada and D.C. Mills of Now York, he principal shareholders. 
  A mill with 120 stamps was erected in a few months, and the mill and chlorination works on a grand scale put in operation. Two largo ditches, one ten miles long to the westward, along the face of the mountain, and the other to the cast, five miles in length, wore constructed with great difficulty and expense, owing to the tundra character of the surface, to convoy water to the mill as a motive power. A pressure of 700 feet , through iron pipes twenty inches in diameter, was communicated to a wheel of eight feet in diameter, by which all those ponderous stamps, 2,000 pounds each, and the other machinery, were set in motion and did their work. For two years the mill and works wore kept in constant operation, no cessation night or day, during the week. Early in 1888 the capacity of the stamp mill was expanded, and the number of stamps increased to two hundred and forty, making the largest mill of the kind under one roof In the world. The policy of keeping the establishment in constant operation remains unchanged, and since its increase incapacity, there has been a stoppage of only one day. During the summer of 1889 , fifteen miles were added to the ditch for water supply, and to intercept additional streams as they came down the mountain side to the sea. During the winters of 1887 and 1888, there was no interruption of the supply of water by cold weather, for motive power, but to guard against any contingency of that that kind , a powerful Corliss engine has been provided to drive the great mass of machinery at such times. The winters at Douglass island are seldom so severe that the rapid, fresh-water torrents freeze over and deprive the mill of its full supply. In December , 1889, there was some difficulty in that respect, and the Corliss engine was doing the work of the waterwheel. The Treadwell is not a mine in the strict sense. The rock is taken out of an open quarry and convoyed to the mill less than five hundred feet distant on a tramway. Its capacity Is 650 tons every twenty-four hours. The profits of the establishment are, of course, the company's own secret, but exports acquainted with this quartz and other conditions, put the average yield per ton at $10 and the cost of extracting the metal, at from $4 to $4.50 per ton. By the amalgam process, all the free gold which passes from the stamps to the concentrators is recovered, while the residue, in the form of sulphurets; is manipulated by roasting and chlorination in the vast wooden building which stands several hundred yards nearer the beach than the stamp mill.
  This company owns 9,000 lineal feet or six quartz claims in length, from east to west , and while in four years of constant movement, an enormous cavity in the side of the mountain has been created, the indications are that the supply of rock, at the present rate of production, will hold out for a quarter of a century yet. A line electric light
  plant enables the operatives to work by night in the mill , and in the chlorination works and the mine. Four
  hundred men arc employed in various duties about the mine, stamp mill, chlorination work, stores, and saw and planning mills , which the company operates as part of its mining and mining plant. About one-third of the operatives are Indians or natives of Alaska. The latter are an industrious, frugal and reliable class of mining employes, and receive the same wages as white men engaged in the same class of work. Indians are largely employed not
  only at the salmon canneries in southeastern Alaska as fishermen, but in nearly all the mining operations of that section of the territory. No antagonism exists between them and white labor, and their relations are of the most cordial character. The white minors in southeastern Alaska do not permit Chinamen to engage in that class of work , and coolies are only found on the inside, all the salmon canneries, always going below at the end of the season.
  Early last year work was begun on the "Bear's Nest", a mining claim which was sold to an English syndicate in the fall of 1888 for $2,000,000. It is located about half a mile west of the Treadwell, and was sold on the strength of its good neighborhood, and upon the results of diamond drill tests. After a tunnel had penetrated the hillside for 1,000 feet, and about $70,000 had been expended toward erecting a stamp mill , and other parts of the requisite plant, they failed to strike the ledge which was doomed to be a westward prolongation of the rich and extensive lode constituting the Treadwell. Operations have been suspended, and litigation to determine whether the sale was a fraudulent transaction, the salting of a mine , or whether the failure to roach a paying ledge was the result of operative blundering has been begun. The mere fact that an enterprise starting out with so much of promise failed in the very midst of the brightest anticipations, will , most certainly, produce a chilling effect upon all present attempts to inaugurate new mining enterprises in Alaska. The Mexican company, a corporation with abundant resources, however, is vigorously prohibiting Its explorations at an equal distance to the eastward of the Treadwell , in the hope and confidence , and with every prospect of intercepting the prolongation of the Treadwell ledge. Rich deposits of gold-bearing quartz have also been discovered on Admiralty island, in the same group as Douglass island, and the stamp mills are in course of erection there also.
  The discovery of coal near the beach, and easy of access by water transportation at Cook's inlet, Unga island and at
  other available points on the coast of western Alaska , will have an important bearing not only on the general commercial importance of the territory, but upon its gold and silver mining enterprises, coal, when used In the latter industry, is now only attainable at Departure bay, British Columbia , and with the enormous cost, of coal freights under the present arrangement of transportation the work of development is more or less retarded. 
  One word more with respect to the future of gold mining In Alaska, as far as discoveries extend, the ores are of a
  low grade. This will requite that they be handled In large plants with capital in large mass, owing to the policy pursued
  by the company operating the Treadwell mine. In addition to that, the management must be of an intelligent character and not mere inexpert experiments by unskillful adventurers. Under such conditions Alaska , through its gold mines , will be n source of great wealth to the entire country.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 2 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030272/1896-03-01/ed-1/seq-28/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>THE RUSH TO YUKON
          The rush Into the Yukon has already begun. The fest party of miners to take the trail left Juneau about the middle of January. There were nine men In the party. This is an unusually early start for miners. A good many others in town are wetting ready for the trip, intending to tackle the range about the middle of March. Every steamer that comes in from below now brings party of old-timers and crowds of now men all anxious to get in and get to work. The Yukon country in almost certain to be overcrowded this summer, surely as regards winter supplies, unless large outfits are taken in from here by the miners.
From all accounts received here from sections along the Pacific coast and In the East Alaska is destined to receive a rush of people this summer which will not be consistent with the present progress and the amount of work now going on. Alaska at present can support so many people and no more, and if the rush pans out according to present prospects there Is likely to be considerable hardship. Alaska has no industries except mining at which the wage earner can make a decent livelihood, and unless a man has sufficient means to carry him through, either in some business or for a season's prospecting, he had better steer clear of this country. It requires some capital to prospect for a mining claim, and when the claim is found it requires more capital to open It up. Gold nuggets do not grow on bushes, and It takes both a man's hands and his pockets to get the yellow metal in this country. There's an almighty lot of at here, but it isn't to be had for the asking. It is perhaps timely now to tell something explicit about the way of getting into the Yukon and the difficulties of the trip. No one should think of coming to Alaska who has not perfect health and has not, moreover, a more than ordinarily strong constitution, to enable him to withstand the atmospheric and climatic changes. In the Yukon district the thermometer has an annual range of 180°. There Is a time in the short summer when it ranges about 110° above zero, and in the winter it frequently goes to 70°  below, and sometimes more. No one should come to Alaska who has not some practical knowledge of quartz and placer mining. Theories are all right in their way, and the theorist may stumble upon something good, but it is the practical prospector who gets the Alaskan nugget every time. Every unfavorable report of Alaska mines can be traced directly to some disappointed tenderfoot who thought he could come up here and pick the gold off the bushes. Most of them didn't like it because they found they couldn't get nuggets as easily as they could salmon berries. Anybody can tell gold after the smelter gets through with it, but it isn't so easy to know where to look for and how to find it.
If you are contemplating making the trip into the Yukon you want to give careful consideration to these things: The length of time you will have to stay in the country, the amount of money it will take, and the results which may be attained. Briefly, these things are: Time, three years; money, $500; results, unlimited. Little can be accomplished in less than three years' stay in the Yukon unless the prospector has marvelously good luck. A good part of the first season will be consumed in reaching the mines. Then if claim is discovered and located only preliminary work can be done. The second year the mine can be opened up well, and probably some money can be made. The third year is when the prospector may reasonably expect to get his profits.
No man ought to make the start into the Yukon basin with less than $500 above what he expects to spend for the outfit which shall carry him through to the diggings. That is, if he goes in by way of Juneau and over the pass, he wants to have $500 when he gets to Forty Mile or Circle City, or wherever it is he is going. It he goes by the way of St. Michael's and up the Yukon he wants to have just the same money.

The road Is a long one whichever way he goes. Supplies are expensive. The season is short, and fortune Is fickle. Failure to find gold the first season is likely to entail great hardship upon those whose funds are insufficient at the start. Not one in a hundred makes a paying strike the first season. The trading companies in the interior find a quick market for all their goods at spot cash prices, and they refuse absolutely give credit. Their supply is almost invariably behind the demand. These are the cold-blooded facts and if you haven't got the money to meet them you had better not try to go into the Yukon basin looking for a fortune. You won't get it. But if you've got the money, and if you are strong and healthy and ambitious and are a practical prospector, and if you've got good grit, why, come along. Here's the 1 place where you can make a pile. There's lots of it up here, and such men are digging it. It is estimated that they dug out In the Yukon district, in the last season upward of $800,000, and that isn't a patch on what's there. 
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 3 -->
       <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85058130/1898-04-09/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>KILLED ON THE TRAIL
Thirtyone Miners Crushed Under a i
Chilkoot Avalanche
Cbikoot I
FIFTY BURIED IN SNOW
LIST OF THE LOW AN
INJURED
Softening of the Snow On the Moun
tain Side By Recent Rains and
Chinook Winds Believed to Be the
Cause of the Accident Klondike
News
Skaguay Alaska April 3 via Seattle
April 8At about noon today on the
Chilkoot trail between the Scales and
Stone House at least 31 men met death
and a large number of others were In
jured more or less seriously In a snow
slide
The dead were crushed under an av
alanche of snow and ice which came
down from the mountain side upon the
lefthand side of the trial about mid
way between the Scales and Stone
House
At this writing the known dead are
Gus Zebarth Seattle Frank Sprague
Seattle Steve Stevenson Seattle Tom
Collins Portland Ore C P Harrison I
Colns
Seattle W L Riley Seattle one wom
an name unknown Ed Atwood New 1
York C Beck Sanford Fla L Weid
lein Kansas City Mrs Ryan Balti
more John Morgan Emporia Kan
Grimes of Sacramento who has a
brother In business at Dyea
Two of the seriously Injured are al
ter Chappey of New York and John C
Murphy of Don Dakota I
BURIED IN THE SNOW i
Fully 50 people were overtaken by I
the slide and are either burled in the
bor
snow or are scattered along the
ders of the avalanche In a more or less
Injured condition
The point at which the accident oc
curred is some five miles above Sheep
I Camp The nearest telephone station
is four miles distant The Scales are
some five miles above Sheep Camp
The telephone wires at this point were
carried away by the slide This fact
makes it difficult to obtain further iRr I
ticulars at this time
I
BLINDING SNOWSTORM
A blinding snowstorm was raging all
day upon the summit and as a conse I
quence many of those in the vicinity
were making no attempt to travel I
Zebarth Sprague and Stevenson of I
Seattle were traveling together as part
ners and were found side by side in
bedThousands I
Thousands of people were encamped
in the vicinity of the accident at the I
time and were soon upon the scene
rendering such assistance as was pos
sible Upon recejpt of the news points
below Dyea telephoned up to knowlf
assistance was required and received
answer to the effect that 5000 people
were at work upon the debris and were
only In each others way
CAUSE OF THE SLIDE
All day Saturday and Sunday a
southerly storm with chinook wind
rain and snow prevailed in this vicin
ity and it is believed the softening of
the snow on the mountain side by
those agencies was the cause of the
avalanche The quantity of snow and i
ice that came down in the slide is es i
timated at thousands of tons I swept i
directly across the trail which not I
withstanding the fact that the weather I
was unsuitable for travel was
thronged with wayfarers The last
vestige of the trail in the vicinity was
wiped out of existence and where it
led Is now a mountain of snow and ice
under which are many dead bodies
that cannot be recovered for days to
come
MORE UNFORTUNATES
Later reports bring the information
that the bodies of three more unfor
tunates have been taken from the snow
One is that of Garrison initials and
residence unknown Ritchie initials
and residence unknown Durber Ini
tials unknown residence Seattle
There was a preliminary slide at 2
oclock in the morning People were
digging out their goods when the sec
ond slide occurred about noon
The latest reports are that 31 bodies
have been recovered
A LATER ACCOUNT
Skaguay Alaska April 4 via Vic
toria B C April 18The horror on
the Dyea trail Is growing in magni
tude hourly As the work of rescue
proceeds it becomes more apparent that
many more lives were lost than at first
thought possible I is now beliexed
that between 50 and 100 men and wo
men were killed by the avalanche
Many bodies will never be recovered
until the summer sun melts the tons
of snow and ice that now bur them
from sight
Two or three thousand men are work
Ing in relays of as many as can stand
side by side shoveling away the debris
In search of the dead and dying Twen
tytwo dead bodies have been recov
ered and identified and 25 have been
taken out alive
CORRECTED LIST
A corrected list of killed and wound
ed as complete as possible at the hour
of writing Is as follows
i Gus E Sebarth Frank Sprague
Steve Stevenson C II Harrison W
L Riley Seattle E D Atwood New
York C Beck Sanford Fla L W
Weidelein Kansas City Mrs Ryan
Baltimore John Morgan Emporia
Kan F M Grimes Sacramento Mrs
Anna Moxon Jefferson county Penn
sylvania Ras Hepgard Baker City
Ore Atkins Idaho Tom Geffert
Seattle E F Miller Vancouver
Wash Tom Collins Portland Ore T
Lamer
The seriously injured so far recov
ered are
AValter Chappey New York John C
M rphys Dlxon N D F B Hol
brooke Portland Oret Dahlstrom
resldente unknown
Seventeen employees of the Chilkoot
Ralway8 Tram company who went
up to the summit orj the moraine of
the slide to work are missing and It is
feared that they are among the lost
I Is estimated that 10000 tons of out
fits are buried under the snow and ice
S SLIDES
There were several smaller slides be
fore the deathdealing avalanche was
started About 2 oclock In the morn
In a small slide occurred which
burled several cabins The alarm was
spread and many people were endeav
oring to work back to Sheep Camp
when the big disaster occurred The
snowstorm was blinding and the
crowds were coming down by the aid
of a rope when overtaken The exact
location of the slide is given at two
and onehalf miles above Sheep Camp
and 100 yards above the Oregon Im
I provement companys power house
Here an immense gorge rises at a very
I steep incline Into the hills and It was I
down this the avalanche came
I ANXIOUS FRIENDS
i The telephone office here has been I
thronged all day and night with friends i
anxious to get some word of friends
believed to have been in the disaster i
The wires are working well and In I
formation Is gotten here direct from
the scene as rapidly as it is gathered
Many people have gone from this city
and Dyea to Sheep Camp to aid in the
I work of rescue I Is believed that
I when the full returns are in the dead
v111 number nearer 150 than 50 II
I The slide covered the trail for sev
eral hundred yards at a depth of 50 I
feet in many places I has effectually i
blocked travel for the present and It
will be some time before it ca be resumed
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 4 -->
       <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85066387/1897-12-19/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Alaska, A Chance for the Poor Man and the Capitalist
HERE is probably no section
of the United States where la-
THERE more in demand than in j
of the United States where la- !
bor is more in demand than in j
j Alaska. Along the southwest- j
s erly shore line the mines and j
fisheries would afford perma- j
nent occupation to a large pop
ulation. We want men who will come
with their families and make our land
their permanent abode. When homes
are established then will our future be
assured. At present I scarce believe
that the entire white resident popula
tion of Alaska exceeds 10,000.
But before there can be much immi
gration to Alaska there must be an
extension of the land laws. At present
a purchaser can secure no title to
property. The only deed is a quit
claim. He'll get off and you set on.
We have been living in this way for
thirty years.
The mining laws of the United States
have been extended to Alaska, but not
the land laws. Why, every man who
cuts a stick of timber is a trespasser.
The people realize that they are there
on suffrage, and there is no attempt to
cut timber for export out of the coun
try.
The poor man has an equal chance
with the capitalist so far as mining in
the southern s -tion is concerned. Of
course, when it comes to outfitting,
paying for transportation into the Yu
kon district, the man of limited means
is practically barred.
But I believe that the rush into the
Klondike will soon be diverted. As
Governor I receive hundreds of letters
seeking information regarding the
country. I have noted that many of*
these letters inquire about chances in
the Copper River and Cooks Inlet dis
tricts, showing that an increasing
number of people are now turning their
eyes in those directions, because they
believe in their mineral wealth and
because they are on American soil. We
anticipate -I great rush there, and
while it might be for a time a tran
sient addition to the population of the
country it will mean somewhat of a
permanent settlement later on.
At no distant day I believe there will
be what may be termed "the Alaska
farmer." As a result of my twenty
years' experience in this northern
country I have no hesitancy in saying
that it possesses superior agricultural
advantages to my old Indian stamping
ground. I now raise fine garden truck,
beef cattle, and am able to raise pigs
with little difficulty. It is some trouble
to get feed, but there is plenty of grass.
The western islands and Cooks Inlet
are covered with grass four feet high.
Some day there will be a farming pop
ulation in Cooks Inlet.
The transition in Alaska will be from
gold to coal and from coal to agricul
ture. I have heard it said that the Yu
kon Valley offers a field for barley un
surpassed anywhere in the world, even
though the soil one foot or eighteen
inches below the surface is eternally
frozen.
The fish Industry is one of the great
est interests in Alaska. The business
last year amounted to $3,000,000, but it
needs to be regulated by a commission.
The cannery men should be called to
gether in conference to decide the many
questions which should be settled where
a fierce rivalry exists. All sides could
be heard, and more intelligent laws
than those now governing would re
sult. There are a number of instances
I could give of the necessity of a com
mission. '-*;%
There is now an absence of Govern
ment machinery, which makes lt Im
possible for even constituted officials
to enforce their authority.
Think of the future of the fish Indus
try! The grounds on the Atlantic
coast are giving out,' while ours are un
touched. Some day a majority of the
fish consumed in the world will come
from Alaska. ■ . ,% **?
The fur industry has seen its best
days. On the western islands foxes,
blue and silver, are being cultivated,
and I understand those interested in
the venture are having good success. *
I do not believe that Alaska has a
large enough permanent population to
warrant the creating of a Territory.
I do, however, favor the appointment
of a commission to visit Alaska and
frame new laws for its government.
The business men and officials of
Alaska are concerned in effecting some
change or amplification of the laws
at present in force. They ought to
confer and submit to Congress a prop
osition to authorize the appointment
of a commission which can consider on
the ground the needs of Alaska My
idea is that the commission should
consist of a Senator, a Representative
and three bona-fide Alaskans. If we
are ever able to get such a commission
something would be accomplished for
the practical good of Alaska. Other
wise the time devoted by Congress to
Alaska will be frittered away in the
consideration of numerous individual
bills of.no benefit to the country as a
whole. This man will want a right of
way; that one certain privileges.
Each bill will be lobbied and pushed,
to the exclusion of more general mea
sures, with the result that Alaska will
stand where she
, stood for the last \
thirty years. The !
work of Congress j
will be fruitless I
and the simple
laws we need will
remain unenacted.
"I SHOULD VERY MUCH LIKE TO
JOIN THESE EXCITED 'GOLD RUSHERS'."
But even as she
is to-day, nothing
can stop the great
development and
growth of Alaska.
JOHN G. BRADY,
Governor of Alaska
r- VERY now and then something happens which makes one
L perately to be younger. Just now it is the rush to Klondike. Next sum-
EVERY now and witnessed the most wonderful rush cf men desire des
perately to be younger. Just now it is the rush to Klondike. Next sum
mer there will be witnessed the most wonderful rush of men
I and the most wonderful improvised city of frame house
' i-s. i-u- _,„«•■ *n*/-,*-,/*A-ft*i oa loons, e-nrnhline nlaces.
Mini ilie uiu*>*. •-> *j».*j*-»-.»»» - > «= =* -
dancing places, singing places, newspapers, churches,
perhaps, that the world has ever seen. There was
a rush to California in the old days. There was a /
rush to Melbourne. I remember from time to •
time running across men who had been to /
the gold fields. None of them had broughf
away any gold at all. What they did bring
away was rheumatism, bent bodies, creak
ing joints, torture and early death. And
that, I think, in some form or other, will be
the portion of most of the Klondike dig
gers. The word has apparently been pass
ed to "boom" Klondike in the interest of
the American outfitters, who will reap all
the harvest for themselves. If I were
younger I would go to look at the place
and the people. Alas! I cannot. It is
no use recommending young novelists
to go, because, no doubt, they are pre
paring for a a start in March. There
were three young novelists. They all I
resolved— each thinking himself "the i
first— go to Klondike, and there lay
the scene of a novel certain to have a
most enormous boom. They all thought
they would start in March— this all hap
pened next year. They went out by dif
ferent boats; one by the Allan line, so as
to get local color in Canada; one by the
Cunard line, because they have never lost
a passenger; and one by the White Star,
because it was handy. They all got out
West— far West, to British Columbia, where
the start is made; on the morning of the
start they met; face to face they met. Thej
had come by different routes and they ' me
on the same morning, face to face; every man T>
had thought himself the first in the field. And
grasped the situation in a moment; they broke
Into hollow laughter; they shook hands with wooden
smiles. "Going to Klondike?" said one. "So am I. V**!
All on the same business, of course." They started, *-,
anon they came to a tight place; two held aloof, hoping
that the third would tumble over and break his neck. Noth-
-()
--: As a rule, when
one goes to hear a
celebrated lecturer
one is so eager and
expectant to hear
and see the great
man himself that
little notice is tak
en of the manner
in which he is in
troduced to theau
dience by the
chairman, though
the method is oft
en very amusing or
curious, especially
where the chair
man Is a "self
made" man or a
local "big-wig,"
whose knowledge
of literary, scienti
fic, or theological
subjectsisno
greater than it
should be.
At a well-known
mechanics* insti
tute in the north
of England the
chair, at a recent
lecture by a dis
tinguished clergy
man, was taken
by an Alderman
who had made
most of his money
and reputation in
the grocery busi
ness, and whose
atta inments in
theology had not
soared above the
Bible and church
hymnal. Hence,
when he announc
ed that the Rev.
would now de
liver his lecture on
"The Canon; Its
Composition and Place In History,"
and went on to say that it was most
important , nowadays, with our com
mercial interests, that we should be
quite up to date with all military and
naval knowledge, etc., the audience
was immensely tickled.
Ing happened. On the third day one of , them, who had been
quite silent and meditative all day, lay down at night beside the other two
In the morning he had vanished. The other two looked at each other. There
It Is not long ago that, when a great
"gathering had assembled to hear the
inimitable Mark Twain lecture, they
found an empty platform before them
almost up to the very moment of start
ing. Then, just before the appointed
hour, there came on the boards a
rather simple-looking man who wan
dered aimlessly about, surveying first
the audience, then the empty stage,
then the roof, then the people again,
till they thought him demented. His
remarks were not less amusing.
"Very nice hall; very nice! Nice peo
ple; very nice people!" And so on.
Finally the _■ audience lost patience
and some called to him to "vanish"!
Then he came forward to the foot
lights and said in a most seriou3 voice:
THE SAN FRANCISCO CAUL, SUNDAY, DECEMBER 19, 1897.
"Ladies and gentlemen, as I have to
lecture to you to-night, I think we will
now begin !"'
It was Mark himself, who had chosen
this amusing way for his introduction
to them. \_;j,^x ''*
Probably few introductions in Eng
land are of the style a famous traveler
experienced when lecturing in a back
woods town on his travels. The chair
man was a local desperado, who began
the proceedings in this style, evidently
thinking that his dignity in the chair
demanded supporting: *
"Gentlemen, this is Mr. , who is
going to tell us what he's seen; and If
any darned man contradicts or inter
feres he's got me to reckon with arter
it's all over."
And, in acknowledgment, he placed
a revolver on the table. The lecturer
was not contradicted or interfered
with.
The famous composer of "The
Mikado" tells a laughable story of how
he had once to apologize at a meeting
in the far West, where a great crowd
of people appeared on learning that
"Sullivan" would lecture on a certain
day. It was only when he had to con
front the audience that he discovered
they had come expecting to hear J. L.
Sullivan, the pugilist! The chairman
and his supporters, in introducing the
noted musician, had no small task in
calming the disappointed "far-west
ers.
ALASKA HAS BIG PRIZES
FOR THE WINNERS.
THE eyes of the gold hunters
of the world are on Alaska.
With the coming year will
begin one of the greatest
gold rushes in the history of
the world. It is safe to say
that fully 100,000 adventurers
will strain and struggle to
be first in the mad race for the new El
Dorado. Is there a chance for all?
Will not hundreds perish in the race?
Readers of those fascinating stories
of glittering finds made on the Klon
dike must not think for a moment that
any one can go there and pick up gold.
Far from it. The poor man who
reaches there with a dollar in his
pocket may, in the wild juggle of
things, strike on everlasting fortune,
but his chances are Infinitely smaller
than those of the capitalist who goes
there with sufficient means to permit
him to carefully comb over the pros
pects and select the offers of those com
pelled by necessity to sacrifice their
claims. The men who have made the
big strikes to date went into the' coun-
I try well supplied to battle with adverse
I fortiine and bad weather. Had they
j struck nothing they could have tided
I were only themselves. The other man, therefore, had rolled over something
I and broken his neck. They smiled, and went on. Then they came to the
place of all; the most terrible road in the whole world, and in
the night one of the two remaining novelists vanished.
Assuredly he had gone over the precipice, too; he
rhyming to the woods and fields outside, the seasons faithfully
remembered, the little exiles of the flowerpot bear mute witness that the house
! wherein they live is a "building of God, a house not made by hands."
over their bad luck and traveled safe
ly out of the country. Don't go to
Alaska unless you see your way clear
to getting out, and bear in mind that
in that rough, hard country you will
win no prizes in gold or trade without
a hard, stubborn struggle.
Alaska is no place for a weakling in
body or spirit. She has big prizes for
the winners, but to gain them one
must fight stoutly and steadfastly.
Read the story of Alaska and you
will find that only the stoutest hearted
and most persistent have ever won for
tunes from her. I wonder If the Impa
tient adventurers have any notion of
the extent of her vast domains. Her
mountains, moss plains, ice fields, for
ests and patches of flint, bushes, grass
and waterways cover about 600,000
square miles, an area about as large
as that part of the United States lying
east of the Mississippi River. She has
nearly three times as much coast line
as the rest of the United States. Sev
eral millions of men could lose them-
A CHANCE FOR THE POOR MAN
AND THE CAPITALIST.
I selves within her lines. Robinson Cru
soe cut more of a figure on his lonely
island than do the 400 miners now
scratching the frozen ground along a
few iceclad streams. Of all this vast
expanse practically nothing is known.
For instance, take Baranoff Island,
where Sitka, the capital, is situated.
It is eighty miles long by forty broad,
and has been settled for over 100 years.
Yet no one has ever penetrated the
mountains of the interior.
Since Vitus Bering discovered the
country in 1741, while cruising for the
Russian Government, it has lain al
most as quiet, unnoticed and undis
turbed by hustling white men as the
j interior of China. As usual in the de
velopment of new lands commerce
hunters first opened it up. But out
side of furs and fish they discovered
nothing for 150 years. But plain furs
proved a giant bonanza for that big
■'•monopoly, the Russian-American Fur
Company. On one cargo of 80,000 sea
otter skins alone they received $40 per
pelt. Those were the days when the
nobles of the Orient paid fancy prices
for rare and fine furs. Governor Bar
anoff was the brains of the business.
was no more. The third novelist went on -.vim us
* light a heart as the perils and sufferings of that
pass would allow. But the first who van
ished was not killed; he simply thought he
A would go home. On the way back he
bought all the Klondike literature that
he could find; he drew rough sketches; he
drew pictures of houses, of mountains,
\of gold waching; he took the train to
New York; wrote all day 1 ong all
the way across the Atlantic; he went
up to London. * • * Six weeks later the
. great Klondike novel came out. It had
\ an enormous boom. A quarter of a
\ million copies went off in the first
\ month. All previous boomers lay
\ down and died with envy. Then the
second traveler arrived. He, too,
had not perished, but he had made
vp N his mind to go no further.
Imagine his joy when he reached
Liverpool to be offered the last edi
tion — they came out six a week— of
the great Klondike novel! No; his
own was refused everywhere. There
could not be two booms about the
J washing; he took the train to
Fork; wrote all day 1 ong all
ay across the Atlantic; he went
London. * • * Six weeks later the
Klondike novel came out. It had
mormous boom. A quarter of a
on copies went off in the first
ith. All previous boomers lay
n and died with envy. Then the
md traveler arrived. He, too,
not perished, but he had made
his mind to go no further,
tgine his joy when he reached
erpool to be offered the last cdi
—they came out six a week — of
great Klondike novel! No; his
i was refused everywhere. There
d not be two booms about the
same place. Lastly, there came, two
/ months later, the man who had done it.
/ I believe they allowed him to produce a
/ "Journey to Klondike," which nobody
/cared about, because by this time the
papers were full of journeys to Klondike,
life at Klondike, want at Klondike, and
he rest of it. The moral of this is, of
tat If you are a novelist you don't want to
go to Klondike. At the same time I wish I
r was younger because I should very much like
to join these excited "gold rushers."
p** r Flowers have no speech nor language, but
they are living creatures, \ and, when transplanted,
'^ '. from their own me haunts to ours, they claim the
captive's due of tenderness, and they will reward love,
like a child, with answering loveliness. In their religious
After his death the company gradually
went to pieces and the fur trade lan
guished. In 1868 the Russian Govern
ment was glad to sell the country to
the United States for $7,000,000.'
Under the Americans the fish trade
was developed till it rivaled what was
left of the fur seal trade. More than
$6,000,000 is invested there now in sal
mon fisheries alone.
The golden period began in a modest
way about twenty years ago by the dis
covery of some placer mines near where
the city of Juneau now stands. Quartz
ledges were found later. The great
Tread well mine was developed and put
into successful operation. It produces
about $1,000,000 per annum, and has
a plant valued at $2,000,000. This suc
cess led to the discovery and develop-j
ment of other mining property
throughout the territory, until South
eastern Alaska produced about $3,000,
--000 per annum.
In 1886 came the discoveries fore
shadowing the rich finds on the Klon
BY GOVERNOR JOHN G. BRADY,
BY EX-GOVERNOR JAMES SHEAKLEY
THE KLONDIKE; A CHANCE FOR NOVELISTS,
By Walter Besant.
dike. First, gold was found on Stew
art river, a tributary of the Yukon,
and prospectors began to drift into that
region. New mines were discovered
slowly. What was then considered rich
diggings came to light, and Alaska
quietly and unostentatiously drifted
toward competency and civilization.
Last spring came the news of gold
discoveries that set the world agog.
And now expeditions are being form
ed in all parts of the world to venture
into this almost unknown region. So
much for the past development of the
country.
Alaska Is entering upon an era of
tremendous development and prosper
ity in comparison with the past. These
new conditions demand new regula
tions and new laws for her government.
Many new propositions will be present
ed to the coming Congress and many
of them will be wild and impracticable.
The best and safest proposition fox
the people of Alaska is to have Con
gress pass an act allowing the President
to appoint a commission of persons
who have resided in Alaska and who
are well acquainted with its needs and
conditions, to draft a code of laws,
both civil and criminal, and also to
make such changes in the organic act
and to establish such courts as may
be necessary.
From among the hardy, resourceful
men who sprinkle gold rushes there
will spring to the front brainy ones
plenty capable of handling all local
questions till the Government steps
in. Alaska is in need of such people.
They hustle around and force things
into line. Alaska has hibernated so
long that next spring's awakening
will be something tremendous for her.
The Indians have a saying: "White
man heap fool; take gun and go out
hunt bear. Indian take gun and go
out and wait for bear." In a rough
fashion that has been the character
of the country to date. Those Indians
are a queer lot to enterprising white
men. I remember a mine on Kotzebue
Sound; it is a very rich silver mine
and the farthest north in this country,
where the manager went to San
Francisco for the long winter, leaving
several natives to watch the plant and
the six tunnel mules till spring. When
Green got back In July he asked the
boss native what kind of a winter
they had had. "Oh, fine; heap fine,"
was the reply. "Heap plenty to eat.
Everything heap plenty and fat."
They had eaten the six mules. •
Alaska is probably the most Inacces
sible country on
the globe. To pros
pect the gold fields
requires not only
moral courage, but
a great deal of
physical strength
and endurance. All
its approaches are
by water. Even
the big part of the
.summer traveling
must be done by
water, for there is
not ten miles of
Ie country on
globe. To pros
: the gold fields
aires not only
al courage, but
rreat deal of
sical strength
endurance. All
approaches are
water. Even
big part of the
imer traveling
»t be done by
er, for there is
ten miles of
tlway in all of
the 600,000 square
miles of territory,
Even the trails
are wretched apol
ogies for footwear.
More cattle paths
and rough roads
were constructed
last spring by the
pioneer gold rush
ers than were built
by the pelt-hunt
ers and fishers dur
ing the preceding
150 years.
The coast waters
that the gold hunt
ers will be -obliged
to voyage are fre
quently visited by
sudden storms.
The vessels select
ed for the trips
should be of the
most stanch and
seaworthy kind
and should be com
manded by experi
enced and compe
tent navigators.
I would sound a
Word of warning
in regard to those
old hulks and river
boats that are be
ing fitted up for
the Alaska trade.
I am satisfied that
many of them will
not reach their
destination. If you
go by Dyea and
the Chilcoot Pass
you will have 25
miles of land trav
el over an eleva
tion of 4000 feet
high. If the trip is
made in the early
PRESIDENT McKINLEY ON ALASKA'S NEEDS
__ HE Territory of Alaska requires
SHE Territory of Alaska requires
the prompt and early attention of
•Ij Congress. The conditions now
T-T- existing demand material changes
in the laws relating to the Terri
tory. The great influx of population
during the past summer and fall, and
the prospect of a still larger immigra
tion in the spring will not permit us to
longer neglect the extension of civil
A general system of public surveys
has not yet been extended to Alaska,
and all entries thus far made in that
district are upon special surveys. The
act of Congress extending to Alaska
the mining laws of the United States
contained the reservation that it
should not be construed to put In
force the general land laws of the
country. By. an act approved March 3,
authority within the Territory
1891, authority was given for the entry
of land for townsite purposes and also
spring you must pass over on snow
shoes and take the risk of being
caught in the blizzards which dur
ing that season visit the summits.
To me it is a matter of regret that so
many people are determined to try to
get into this inhospitable country
during the coming spring and summer.
Thousands of them are going without
proper preparation and a sufficient
amount of means. There is no ques
tion but that many of them will meet
disappointment, suffering and death.
It will take years to properly (de
velop the broad Alaskan gold fields.l
I earnestly advise those who J<ft^e
planned to go and who have not ade- .
quate means for a year's camp there
to patiently wait until better and
cheaper facilities for reaching the
Yukon basin are supplied. Companies
have been formed to build railroad^
into the interior from different points
on the coast. Several of these com
panies will no doubt have a railway
constructed within the coming year.
There is no danger of the crop of
mines becoming exhausted within the
next twenty-five years. I came to the
California mines in 1852. I left in 1854
thinking the mines were worked out.
I returned here forty-two years after
ward and found that gold-mining in
California was only in its infancy;
more gold was produced this year than
will be produced in all Alaska and
British Columbia within the next two
years.
Once in the gold fields, what are the
chances for the poor man and the rich
man?
Briefly, then, without a proper outfit
and supplies, it is absolutely hopeless
for any one to tempt fortune by pros
pecting. The seasons are so shot"t. liv
ing so dear and traveling so difficult
that to work for wages practically cuts
a man ! off from aiming at anything
higher. With from $500 to $1000 ,in his
pocket,' however, a man may reason
ably try his chances with the best of
the prospectors. Consider some of the
difficulties of mining there and you will
see why this is so. As far as any one
has dug down the ground is solidly
frozen. One miner told me he had sunk
a shaft forty-five feet and the ground
was icebound ahead of him. Wood
cannot be got for less than $20 a cord.
The ground must be thawed with fire
before It can be picked out. WJ*uere
wages are $10 a day it costs about §_ J 0 __\
a foot to sink a hole. The poor 1 W*\\\m\\
can calculate how long he can hold P*-
to sink a shaft on his prospect a* (ditch
figures. But capital is going into the
country No doubt it . will give em
ployment to a large number of poor
men, both in working the older mines
I and in prospecting for new ones.
The gold field is very extensive. I be
lieve that good mires will be discov
ered north of the Yukon, and that b*-^*
fore many years ships will be trans- 1
porting miners and supplies through:,
Bering Strait into the Arctic Ocean
and landing them at the mouth of the
Coquille River for the purpose of work
ing the mines en that and other
streams which flow into the northern
ocean.
Outside of .finding employment in the
mines the poor man has practically no
chance of earning a living. There is
no country on earth where he can
starve to death quicker. The cold
temperature of almost eight months of
the year makes it imperative that he
'shall have a proper amount of food
and good clothing. True, the rush of
adventurers will develop lines of busi
ness that must furnish supplies to the
mines, but a limited number of men
will fill all such billets. The fish and
fur trades already have all the men
they can handle. The lumber business,
cuts but a small figure on acccount of
the scarcity of good timber. Agricul
ture and grazing will always be very
limited. Supplies will always have to
come from abroad, and only wealthy/
companies will be able to handle thejw j
in the present rough and expensive |
conditions of transportation. '*
One point these gold-rushers should I
bear In mind: In prospecting the prac
tical miner has very little or no advan
tage over the novice. In that country"
no person can figure on surface indi
cations while prospecting. Many of ;
the big finds of this last year were in
what you might call marshes. No
practical miner would have dreamed 1
of looking in such places for gold indi
cations. There is an old saying: "Silver,
lies in veins and gold is where you <>>*^
it." Six thousand years of experience-'
has proved the truth of this saying.
The chief \ advantage the practical
miner will have over the novice will be
in working and developing claims. : . J
.'No man should set foot in the Yukon!
gold fields without at least $500 in his
pocket. That will keep him till he gets]
work, and in case of a mishap or ill
fortune he will have enough to carry,'
him out of the country, for he might as
well be shipwrecked on an iceberg in!
the northern ocean as stranded in the.
interior of Alaska without supplies. £
JAMES SHEAKLEY. 1
for the purchase of not exceeding 160 i*
acres, then or thereafter occupied for
purposes of trade and manufacture. ]
I concur with the Secretary of War
in his suggestions as to' the necessity-*
for a military force in the Territory !
of Alaska for the protection of persons
and property. Already a small force, X
consisting of twenty-five men, vjfth 1
two officers, under command of,L;'/u- I
tenant-Colonel Randall of the Eis-ftnh j
Infantry, has been sent -to St. Michael
to establish a military post.
As it is to the interest of the Govern- ■
ment to encourage the development
and settlement of the country and its -J 2
duty to follow up the citizens there T^
with the benefits of legal machinery, |
I earnestly urge upon the Congress the 1
establishment of a system of govern- i
ment of such flexibility as will enable I
it to adjust itself in the future areas of I
greatest population.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 5 -->
       <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85066387/1897-07-25/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>The Call's' Map of the Alaskan Gold Region
          THIS map of those portions of Alaska and the Dominion of Canada
in which public interest is centered has been prepared for THE
CALL by Professor George Davidson, \vho has been for a
generation the most competent geographer on the Pacific Coast.
Alaska is in the field which for so many years he superintended as the
head of the Coast and Geodetic Survey on this coast, and he has been
able to supplement the best of the charts yet issued from his personal
familiarity with the field and from special sources.
This map is a long advance from the best maps hitherto obtain
able, and it will not be much improved upon until a long period of
exploration and survey has elapsed.
The San Francisco Call
SAN FRANCISCO, SUNDAY MORNING, JULY 25, 1897-THIKTY PAGES.
Ooxx* jailed and Draxvn for "The Call" "toy PROFESSOR GEORGE DAVIDSOX.
This map will be invaluable to those who invade the Yukon region
this year and next, and it will long be a valuable reference for all in
terested in Alaska.
The geographical features not charted it is impossible to chart.
The latest geographical information about the interior is here given,
but years of exploration and survey must elapse before this region is
mapped for any distance from the main watercourses. It includes in
its showing the magnetic variation of the compass, which it is neces
sary to know in finding directions by that instrument, as many travel
ers will have occasion to do. Lines of variation five degrees apart are
shown, and arrows indicate mere simply the direction in which the
needle actually points — to the magnetic pole and not the North Pole.
The overland route can be readily traced from Juneau to Dyea
by water, thence over Chilkoot Pass to Lake Lindeman and Lake
Bennett, where boats and rafts are built for the long journey of 600
miles down the watercourse to Dawson. The ride is on through Lake
Marsh, through or around White Horse Rapids and to the Lewis River,
thence to the Yukon, which is formed by the junction of the Lewis
and Pelly at Fort Selkirk. Chilkat Pass and White Pass may be
found on either side of Chilkoot Pass, and both may become important
routes. The proposed railroad is shown connecting the navigable
extremes of Stahkeen River and Feslin Lake in British territory.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 6 -->
       <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85038615/1905-04-02/ed-1/seq-31/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Tanana, Alaska's New El Dorado: $100 in Gold to the Pan
M now being trumpeted'byTatiana, the
? ? Eldorado in Alaska.' Already thou?
sands of frenzied seekers after gold are there.
"For fortunes beyond the dreams of.ava
, rice are being garnered by placer mines along
the streams in that locality.
As much as $ioo a pan has.been washed
out in this new district. How startling these
figures are to miners may be judged from'the
fact that, ground averaging 40 cents to the
pan is considered a bonanza, and ip cents a
pan is regarded as big pay.
During the last winter, in spite of the
fact that the ground was frozen, one claim
averaged $1000 in pay dirt a day, and a num?
ber of claims changed hands at $60,000 each.
Within the last twelve months 4000
miners from the Klondike have rushed to the
new fields.* They were the first to hear the
news. All durW.g the winter hundreds strug?
gled thither over snow and ice. Indications
point to a remarkable rush northward from
Seattle this string.
Fairbanks, the centre of the Tatiana
region, consisted a year ago of a few log
cabins. To-day it is a prosperous city of over
three thousand people, with all the conven?
iences of modern city life.
AS SOON as boats are able to navigato the
inland streams of Alaska, a great summer
rush to Tanana is expected to begin. Re?
ports from Seattle state that gold-seekers
aro crowding therj from all parts of the country.
A surprisingly large number are outfitting as
though they had been in mining regions beforo nnd
knew how to arrange for the long and tiresomo trip
by steamer, dog team and afoot. , 1
' Freight charges from Seattle to Dawson in
eummer average over $7d a tori, and as much moro
from .Dawson to Fairbanks, so that the cost of tak?
ing along an extensive equipment is considerable.
It is estimated that the Tanana region pro?
duced $1,500,000 in gold last year, when tho num?
ber of miners was insignificant, compared with the
great army that will camp alonar its streams this
season.
Before news of tho rich'finds penetrated beyond
,the silent forests, pioneer prospeotorj had quietly
taken out a quarter of a million in yellow metal
flakes.
Until the new trails were broken aud in use,
Tanana was not an easy section of Alaska to reach
or leave, and travelers along that way wero scarce?
consisting principally of Indians hunting game or
stray prospectors nosing about for gold.
Situated on tho Tanana river, tho town of
Fairbanks is 150 miles southeast of tho point of
juncture pf that river with'the mighty Yukon; Daw
eon, in the Klondike, is 500 miles away to the oast
ward by sledgo trail, and to the south Valdez, on
the coast, is 5?i miles distant.
Discoverers of gold along tho Tanana wore not
inclined to shout tho glad tidings to the world.
Among those patiently .washing dift there dur?
ing the fall of 1002 wa*'a secretivo individual, a
Mexican, known as Pedro,
Pedro, like the others, lived in a little hut. His
bed was a blanket; chairs and table Avere simply
blocks of -wood. He had little use for the cabin, ex?
cept as a placo to sleep and store his provisions.
All the long arctic days ?ho searched soil along
the streams for gold, usually alone in the vast wil?
derness. At other places w? re other men'similarly
engaged, but they, too, were'there for business and
had little time for sociability. '
Ono day Pedro made" a big strike. Ho found
gold that turned out $100 to, the. pan. Pedro was
a rich man. Then he went away to the couth. But
he didn't spread the news-?he was faithful to tho
miners left behind. >
Others, too, were lucky. Stray prospectors
came that Avay andimmediately'located claims.- It
seemed as if somo had smelled the good news from
distant camps.,
For months this handful of men struggled
fiercely to wash all the gold they could before tho
mad rush they knew was coming, sooner or later.
First to arrivo Avere some steamboat men Avho
had ascended the river with supplies for tho trading,
post just opened at Fairbanks. These men heard
of the marvelous new field and promptly staked
claims there.
Among them was an energetic Japanese named
Wada, Avho, like others of his race, had been in
many mining camps of the far North.
For some reason, as soon as ho had ctaked his
claim and learned of the richness of the region,
Wada started out on a long, lono tramp over the
snow, with a dog team drawing his ? ipplies, for
Dawson) BOO mi lea away.
No trail liad been broken -or at least half the
distanco, butWada. plunged along, helping the dogs
and Making from fifteen to twenty-five inilos a day.
He wns tho first to bear the news of Tanana'a
wealth to Bawsou, and minors of the older Klondike
region immediately Avent wild.
This was in the Avintor of.lOO'i?an exception?
ally cold season, even in Alaska.
Without waiting for spring, -.rimers hurried off
in hundreds for a 6U0-mile journey over snow and
ice, and through a.roadless -yilderness, in a tem?
perature from 50 to CO degreed below ?ero.
Hastily authoring what supplies thoy could,
some left Bawson in small sleighs drawn by horses,
others with ?log teams; but the greater number
hurried along on foot, drawing their sleda them-,
? 'selves. '. ? ?
'?, It was a mad rush for g?ld^:3ir?ny.reached tha
?new field before spring, ?but hundreds of others
came'toiling in all during tho sunom?f. '.,.'
, "When the majority arrived thoy, found the best
claims'already taken, a shortago of, supplies facing
them, and discouragement in tho air.
Wada had returned with the rush. When some
of the men realized their position, they brga?niged'
a miners' meeting and decided to hang the' Jap.
A rope Avas found, and Wada was about to be
strung tip, when ho produced a copy ?f a Seattle
newspaper, showing that he had onco saved the
lives of many whalers, ico-impriaoned in the Arctic
Ocean by tramping overland from Point Barrow to,
St. Michael in dead of winter.
This saved his life, but "Wada Avas driven from
the region to which he had invited tho rush.
In spite of their first disappointment, tho new?
comers spread out and set to work. At this time
gold was only known to exist along one creek. Soon
it" was found along a dozen creek's.
In the spring tho rush from Bawson continued
by steamboat. Olairas were located in overy direc?
tion. Now hundreds who arrived late, or Avho found
that thoir claims did not pay, ar.o working as labor?
ers for tho moro fortunate.
In a little Avhilo, too, all thb surface gold had
been panned, so that it became noces?ary to work
the underground strata by machinery.
; When'tha Klondike Avaa struck, the only method .
known of thawing the frozen ground for sinking
ehafta and running tunnela was to build Avood fires
on the surface, scrapo away the earth as far as it
had thawed, build other fires and keep this tedious
process up indefinitely.
Already at Tnnana steam thawers aro being
used, and steam"ia also employed to movo the wind?
lass buckets that lift the earth.
Theeo steam engines and boilers aro brought
from the etistern United States at great expense.
It is estimated that there ore now about one hun?
dred and fifty at work in the Tnnana region, and
many more are expocted this1 spring.
Iron pipes with hojes in ono end inject the
steam into tho frozen ground. An enormouaamount
of-fuel is required to feed theso boilora, and it.is
estimated that fully one-fifth tho laborers in tha
Tannini country are engaged in cutting and hauling
wood.
This wood costs from $7 to .$10 a cord, and as
each camp burns thousands .of cords a winter, it ia
fast becoming scarce.
Hydraulic methods of mining will bo employed
this Bummer, when the soft surf ace way bo swept
away very offec'ually. Machinery for this work is
also expensive, and freight rates to the interior aro
enormous.
The best-paying claims so far located nro on
Fairbanks, Cleary, Gold Stream and Pudro creel?.
Scattered all along theso etreama and their
numerous tributaries are tho hottics of tho miners.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 7 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86063615/1897-07-20/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Gold Fever Raging
ALASICAV TfnWvS DESERTED IN THE
IILS1I l'Oll KLONDIKE.
MANY GOING WITHOUT MEANS.
MORE STOniES OF THE WEUTII
THAT II S BEEN DISCOVERED.
Captain HlKSiun, of the Excelsior,
Sa Thut Klondjke la n. Great
Place for a Man IVItU a
Icnr's Provision to
Make a StuL.e.
Port Townsend, Wash., July 19 The ex
cursion steamer Queen has arrived from
Alaska with 170 passengers, principally
tourists. Tho officers of the Queen state
that the merchants and tradesmen in both
Juneau and Sitka are closing their shops
and hastening to the new Eldorado Fifty
business men left Juneau for Daw ton City
on Julv 12, and 130 were to leave on the
16th, two das after the Queen sailed The
officers sa that by tho time tho Queen re
turns to Juneau on her return trip, nine
davs hence, there will not ba an able-bodied
man left in the town. Many men are leav
ing Juneau for tho gold fields without pro
visions or means to buy them
Tho steamer Al Kl balled for Alaska at
midnight. She carries forty horses and 1,000
sheep for Dyca, where they will be land
ed and driven across tho summit to the
Yukon vallei. Stockmen say the sheep
are the finest band ever collected off East
ern Washington ranges. They will be taken
to Circle City and Klondike and slaughter
ed. Any kind of fresh meat there sells at
50 cents per pound.
San Diego, Cal., July 19. An Interesting
letter telling of the recent trip of the
steamer Excelsior to Alaska has been writ
ten by Captain J. F. Hlggins, of the steam
er, to a friend In this city Hesajs.
"The word Klondike means Deer river,
which Is called Reindeer river on the
charts. It empties into tho Yukon fifty
miles abovo tho big river. The geographic
al position of the Junction is 76 degrees 10
minutes north latitude. 139 degrees 50 min
utes west longitude. Ronanza creek dumps
Into Klondike about two miles above the
Yukon. Eldorado is a tributary of the
Bonanza. Ther are numerous other creeks
and tributaries, the main river being 300
miles long The gold so far has been taken
from the Ronanza and Eldorado, both well
named, for the richness of the placers lz
truly marvelous. Eldorado, thirty miles
long. Is staked the whole length and as far
as worked has paid.
"As each claim Is 509 feet along the creek
bed, there is half a million to the claim.
So uniform has the output been that one
miner who has an Interest In three claims
told me that If offered his choice he would
toss up to decide. One of our passengers
who Is taking J1.000 with him has worked
100 feet of his ground and refused J200,0u0
for the remainder and confidently expects
to clean up J100.0O) nnd more. He has In a
bottle J212 from one pan of dirt. His pay
dirt while btlng washed averaged J250 an
hour to each man shoveling In Two others
of the miners who worked their own claims
cleaned up J6O0O from tho day's washing.
"There Is about fifteen feet of dirt above
DedrccK, the pay streak averaging from
four to six feet, which Is tunneled out while
the ground Is frozen Of course the ground
tal.cn out is thawed by building fires, and
when the thaw comes and water rushes In
they set their sluices and wash the dirt.
Two of our fellows thought a small bird
in the hand worth a large one In the bush
and sold their claims for Jlj.OuO, getting
JI.500 down, tho remainder to be paid In
monthly installments of J10000 each The
purchasers had no more than J3.000 paid.
They were twenty days thawing and get
ting out dirt. Then there was no water to
sluice with, but one fellow made a rocker
and in ten dais took out the J10.000 for the
first Installment. So tunneling and rotklng.
they took out J49.000 before there was water
to sluice with.
"Ot courts thebo things read like tho
story of Aladdin but fiuion is not In It
with facts and KIbndyke Tho ground lo
cated and prospected can be worked out
In a few ears. but there Ik still an Immense
territory untouched, and the laboring man
who can get there with one 1 car's pro
visions will have a better chance to make
a stake than In any other part of the
world "
Seattle, Wash, July 19 The amount of
ueasure orougni aown irora me iamcu
Klondike on steamer Portland is now placed
at Jl.BOOOOO. and there is good reason to
believo that the sum was nearer to J2.00O.
000. In this connection, something In tho
nature of a confidence game appears to
have been worked on the North American
Trading and Transportation Company, or
its officials In charge of the Portland, by
the miners. Each man was required to
place his gold dust in the ship's safe, but
this was not done, by any meant Many
of tho miners secreted their dust In
blankots and luggage, which were taken
either to their state rooms or thrown care
lefsly about the ship
Clarence J. Herri, one of tho Klondike
kings, brought down at least JS4 000 In
nuggets of not a cent of which the Port
land had any record. The statement is
made on tho authority of Captain William
Kldson. the master ot the vessel When
piessed for nn estimate ns to the grand
lUlill OI IIJU iUlklttltUS i.feis. w,. ....-
son said It was no doubt nearer JIjOOOOO
than the amount accounted for on tho
ships records ... , ...
At present only miners' laws rule the
camp, but next lear Dawson City will be
incorporated and municipal officers elected.
The miners are determined on one thing,
however, namely, that order will be pre
served at nil hazards No "sure thing'
gambleri. will be permitted In either Daw
son City or the diggings
Information comes from Juneau to tho
effect that several rich strikes have recent
ly been made In the neighborhood of Forty
Mile. It has been christened Minute Cretk
and is now panning out J22 a day to the
men Another discovery on American
creek, fiftv miles below Forty-Mile camp,
is said to be paiing well, and a great num
ber of men have flocked there during the
last few weeks The pans run from J10 to
118. It Is thought likely that many of the
prospectors will strike for these camps,
thus relieving the strain on Dawson City.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 8 -->
       <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85066387/1897-07-20/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Inexhaustible Riches of the Northern El Dorado
        The business equilibrium of Seattle was never so
disturbed as it has been by the news of the
richness of the recent Klondyke strikes.
'For forty-eight hours the telegraph offices
of this city have been thronged by people
sending messages to Eastern friends
making a request for sufficient money to
get into the new camp. The list of those
who have arranged to go includes not only
'clerks and such as work for salary, but
business and professional men of recog
nized standing and ability.
"Send me $500. Stake me enough
money to go to Klondyke. News not in
the least exaggerated," is the tenor of the
appeal flashed over the wires. Men are
t being grubstaked in tnis city to an extent
never before thought of and never before
possible. Some local bouses who are
likely to lose trustworthy and well-known
. employes will be behind them in many
cases, while individual men with money
at their disposal who by reason of circum
stances cannot go are not slow to outfit
men in whom they can place unbounded
; confidence.
-*" Many amusing instances connected with
grubstakes are transpiring.- One which
will actually describe the situation had
its finale this morning early. A well
known man, honest but poor, was one of
the first stricken with the desire to go.
• The information reached a friend Satur
. day afternoon and shortly • after the two
met. "How much do you want?" in
> quired No. 2 of the Klondyke fever pa
tient. "I think about $400," was the re
[ spon-e. "bee me in the morning; I think
I can stake you." Sunday the two did
not meet, but early this morning they
did,, when No. 2 gave the first man a chill
that extended down the vertebra^ to the
end of his toes. "I guess that matter is j
all off," No. 2 said. "I have about decided
to go myself, and my man who is inter- 1
ested with me is also going."
It must be said that meanwhile noth- !
ing is occurring which in the least de- :
j tracts or discredits tho Monte Cristo-like
tales first sent out from the district. Sub- j
sequent reports not only verify but tend to
enlarge upon the first accounts. Hon.
C. H. Macintosh, Governor of the North
west Territory, comprising the districts of
j Alberta, Saskatchewan, Assinniboia and
the unorganized districts of the Yukon, i
Athabasca and all the territory east to ;
Labrador and Hudson Bay, arrived in j
Seattle' to-day, being en route to Regina,
the capital of tha Territory. He was seen
at the Rainier CluD.of which he is a guest,
this afternoon. When asked for an ex
pression of his views regarding the great
Klondyke district Governor Macintosh
, replied:
"We are only on the threshold of the
greatest discovery 'ever made. Gold has
been piling up in all -these innumerable
streams for hundreds of years. Much of ]
the territory the, foot of man has .never ,
trod. It would hardly be possible for one '
jySS exaggerate tee richness, hot only of the ,
Klondyke, but other districts in the Cana- ;
dian«"Yukon. At the same time the folly |
of thousands rushing in there without I
proper means of subsistence and in utter !
ignorance of the geographical conditions j
1 of the country should be kept ever in '
• mind. There are fully 9000 miles of these
i golden waterways in this section of the ;
', Yukon. Rivers, creeks and streams of i
l every size and description are all pos- I
"sessed of more or less gold. I derived this j
knowledge from many old Hudson Bay
\ explorers, who assured me that they con
sidered the gold-bearing district next to
_ inexhaustible.
"In 1894 I made a report to Sir John
Thompson, then Premier of Canada, and
• who died the same year at Windsor
Castle, strongly urging that the name
Yukon should be given to that country
by order in council and that a body of !
;. Canadian police be established on the ;
river to maintain order. This was done j
j in 1&05 and the British outpost of Fort '<
; Cudahy was founded. I have known gold |
>. to exist there since 1889 consequent upon !
a report made me by W. Ogilvie, the j
Government explorer.
Many of "-/hat will no doubt prove to be
as rich or richer streams than the Klon- i
dyke have not been explored or pros- I
pected. Among these I might mention
Dominion Creek, Hootalinqua River, ',
: Stewart River, Liard River and a score of j
~ other streams comparatively unknown. j
It is my judgment and opinion that the
1897 yield of the Canadian Yukon will ex- i
ceed $10,000,000 in gold. Of course as is |
the case of the Cariboo and Cassiar dis- I
tricts years ago, it will be impossible to
accurately estimate the full amount taken
. out. There is now far in excess of $1,000,
--000 remaining already mined on the Klon
dyke. It is in valises and tin cans and
some of it is lying loose in saloons and
just as sacredly guarded there and appa
. rently as safe as though it was in vaults.
"Already this spring we have official
knowledge of, over $2,000,000 in gold ;
having been taken out of the Klondyke j
THE YUKON ORDER OF PIONEERS— McQuestin, . the Father of the Camp, Sits in the
Middle, With Frank Bowker, Who Has $90,003 in Gold Dost, on the Righ^ ;
The San Francisco Call
Official Verification of the Wonderful Gold Discoveries in the Klondyke j
District Ten Million Dollars a Conservative Estimate of What
Will Be Taken Out This Year.
camps. It was shipped out, as you know, j
on the steamers Excelsior ana Portland. .
Let me cite a little incident or an instance t
shewing the gold yield of some of the j
Klondyke claims. A friend of mine went j
to a dump and was looking it over, and lie j
told me that it bore the appearance of |
some ones having taken and poured j
bucketfuls of gold nuggets down over the
dump. In truth, he said there appeared ;
to be more gold than dust. Incidentally*
I may say to you that we have data of an j
official nature which leads us to believe i
ttiat the gold output for the Rossland and !
Kootenay districts for 1397 will be in excess j
of $7,000,000, including the silver yield I j
should have said, and I have no hesitancy j
in asserting that within the course of five I
years the gold yield of the three districts j
named will exceed that of either Colorado, |
California or South Africa."
Governor Macintosh announced that I
the Government is seriously considering i
the construction of a railroad into the I
Yukon district. In fact, he said, it has \
several corns of engineers now making ;
surveys.
"One route," the Governor said, "con- i
templates the operation of a line of steam
ers from Fort Wrangel up the Stickeem
R ver, which Is open to both countries,
under the Washington treaty of some
twenty-five years ago, to Telegraph Creek.
From Telegraph Creek surveyors are now
endeavoring to ascertain the feasibility of :
the construction of a railway line from j
125 to 130 miles to Teslin Lake. The route
extends through scrubby timber, and has }
only one or two serious obstacles. Begin- '
ning with Teslin Lake, boats will be oper- j
ated along a series of lakes and rivers that j
connect with the Stewart and Pelly rivers :
emptying into the Yukon. It is claimed ;
that no serious difficulties, that is diffi- !
culties such as cannot be reasonably over- j
come, are encountered anywhere along
this route.
"1 may say in this connection that tbe
route I have just described to you would
be more than 3000 miles shorter than the
present route by way of Sl Michaels and
the YuKon and every foot of it would be
in British territory. There is another
route through Canada which has been
found possible. A railway extends from j
Calgary, Northwest Territory, over 200 |
miles. Then there is a trail, and a good j
one, from Edmonton to Athabasca, land
ing in the unorganized district of Atha- j
basca.* Hudson Bay ' boats how run over
.Athabasca La k.* down slit river of Atha- j
basca to the vicinity of McKenzie River,
where it has' been found possible with
very easy portages to reach the Porcupine
River, and thence down that stream into
the' Yukon. The Government explorer, j
Mr. Ogilvie, made an inspection of this
route several times, once in 1887. once in
1888 and in 1890 and 1891 with Mr. j
Dawson, the director-general of geological j
surveys. The White horse River route is J
also considered feasible."
The Governor leaves in the morning for I
Victoria, going thence to his capital. Re- j
gina. He comes here in reality to see one j
of his sons, who has the fever, safely off
to the Klondyke.
Discussing the Stikeem River route the j
Alaska Mining Record of Juneau in the | i
issue of July 14 says:
"G. W. Garside returned from Wrangel I J
on the Queen and reports the Canada sur- j
veyors are and have been at work survey- i '
ing out the Stikeem route for the proposed !
narrow-gauge railroad for the Yukon | I
country. Were the United . States Gov- ! I
eminent possessed with half the interest i
for its northern subjects and the enter- ! >
prise shown by the Canadians, the way to j i
the greatest gold fields ever known would i i
be mi easy one. But it can hardly be ex- i
pected that the Government will ever I i
spend a dollar toward opening a trail ■ 1
when a disposition to even carry the mail | i
is not shown. Where else on this earth j <
are the citizens treated»by their mother j 1
country as those of Alaska? Mr. O'Brien. ' i
who claims to know the movements of j I
the Canadian Government anent the Yu- i i
kon country, says that immediate steps i
will be taken to establish telegraphic com
munication between Forty-mile ami the j
head of Lynn canal via the Daiton trail.
This by boat to Victoria will give them a '
weekly communication which is so much
desired by the. people of that far-away f i
away." * :
The Mining Record also annonnces]that ! -
"Three distinguished persons in the sport- j i
ing world were passengers on the last trip
of the Queen for Juneau. They were
SAN FRANCISCO, TUESDAY MORNING, JULY 20, 1897.
Prank P. Slavin, the champion heavy
weight boxer of England, who once held
the championship of the wori I ; Joe Boyle
of Ontario, now champion heavy-weight
of , Canada, and Frank Raphael of San
Francisco, liuht-weight champion of the
Pacific Coast. 'They are on tlieir wav to
the gold fields of the Yukon, where th«>y,
like many others, are sanguine of making
their little fortunes quietly and then re
turning to other lands to enjoy it."
On the hurricane deck of the A!-Ki yes
terday stood a young man with straw hat
and bright beardless full face, his elbows
planted on the edge of a life raft, his chin
resting in his palms, and at his de was a
very pretty young woman. Everybody
noticed them, but nobody knew that that
young man is the grandson of old John
Brown who died at Harpers Ferry. '
Young John Brown is a dentist. He came
to Seattle some six years ago. Dr. Brown
practiced dentistry in Seattle, Everett,
Salem and several other places and went
last year to Cooks Inlet, coming out with
the same amount of gout as the others.
Like his grandfather he has not given up,
but goes marching on to the gold fields.
When living in Everett Dr. Brown once
made application to J. W. Gunn, then a
life insurance agent, for a policy. In the
midst of the questioning Agent Gunn
read from the blank form:
"Is your father living?"
"Yes, sir."
"Is your grandfather living T"
"No, sir."
"From what cause did he die?" ■ ,'-'
"Executed," was the answer, without
the slightest chance of tone or look.
"Executed, how's that?" said the ques
tioner, becoming interested, but not read
ing from tie insurance blank. _ - ';' ViVuM
"1 happen to be a grandson of John
Brown, who was hanged at Harpers
Ferry," was the quiet- answer.
"Great Scott exclaimed Gunn, "you a
grandson of old John Brown?" : utVVL
The little insurance agent was speech
less.
O. J. Anderson, writing from Dawson
City to his brother, G. A. Anderson, says:
•'1 left Circle City .in March and came
up here. It is a mistake that you are not
here as the times are good and there is
plenty of gold. There is going to be lots of
work this summer and next winter. lam
making lots of money and will have a good
sack when I come out. Albert has cleaned
un $20,000 in the last two years and has an
interest in a mine that he would not sell
for $50,000. He will be cut soon and will
take a trip to the old country. When- I
came up here 1 left a six months' outfit at
the Circle City mines. lam now making
$20 to $30 a day so cannot afford to go back
lor a little thing like that. This is the
richest country I ever saw. They are
packing the gold dust around, not in their
pockets, but on their backs. . There are a
good many that have made $50,000 apiece
since last fall."
' Joseph A. Costello, a well-known news
paper man, has resigned his position with
the Seattle Times and will leave Sunday
for. the Klondyke, accompanied by Mr.
Branson and Samuel Archer, also of the
same paper.
The late Alaska papers announce that
Robert Insley, proprietor of the Juneau
Opera-house, recently married Miss
Blanche Lamont, a San Francisco vaude
ville performer, and that the people pro
ceeded at once on a wed iing tour involv
ing a trip to the Klondyke.
While the Alaskan placers are all the
talk, Captain Mem of the London Ex
ploration Company would have it under
stood that there is also a little quartz
around Juneau, and he is quoted by a
paper of that town as saying: "There are
7,000.000 tons of ore in sight at; the Paris
or Treadwell mine on Douglass Island."
This would run a 500-stamp mill for
eleven years." ' V ■■
PORTLAND'S OPPORTUNITY.
Oregon's Metropolis May Supply
the 50.000 Who Will Rush to
the North.
PORTLAND, Or., July 19.— Hon. J. B.
Montgomery, the millionaire land-owner,
to-day handed The Call correspondent
the appended excerpt from a letter. from
his son Russeil on the Klondyke district:
"Here is the golden opportunity for
Portland. Our city is staid, steady and a
little slow, but we. get there all the same.
I have no doubt at all that 50,000 men will
rush into Alaska in the next twelve
months. It will not be alone from Ore
gon, California and Washington, but from
every State 1 in the Union. Remember the
rush to California in 1850. Why, this will
beat it out of sight. The argonauts bad
to sail around the horn and across the
plains. It took six months. Now they
can cross the continent, in, less v than a
week and for a quarter of the sum. The
gold placers of the Yukon appear to be
tenfold richer than those on the American
River. r --"V*!>V '
"I have been examining a United States
Circle Giy at Midn'ght on June 20.
Government map. It shows a range of
mountains from 4000 to 19,000 feet high.
Out of these run the Pelly, Klondyke and
other rivers. All of them will no doubt
furnish rich placer diggings. And then
think of the illimitable auriferous rock in
these mountains. California has fur
nished $1,000,000,000 of gold— more than
half from her quartz and to-day, after
fifty years of delving and mining, she
produces mote gold than any other region
in the world. Where will these 50,000
Alaska argonauts be supplied from? Un
doubtedly Portland ought to do it, and
she will. We are very deliberate, as I
said, but we get there. What will they
require? Well, at least 100,000 barrels of
flour and an equal weight ot meats and
groceries. We have the transportation here
to do it with. The Oregon Railway and
Navigation Company has lour steamers in
the San Francisco trade. They have been
running with a -beggarly array of empty
berths until the recent reduction to carry-'
ing people for next to nothing. They
could put two of them on and put on tbe
Yukon their river steamers, which I am
told have been doing charity work for ten
years."
GOING FROM BERKELEY.
Party of Ton Men Being Organized
at the Co less Town for
Klondyke.
BERKELEY, Cal.. July 19.— party of
ten men is being organized in the uni
versity town to go into the Klondyke
gold fields..
Hansford .Griffith, a graduate of the
University of Virginia and at present a
student at Berkeley, is at the head of the
scheme. xMuuu -VVuV"----. ."■-.■
He proposes that each of the party of
ten put up $500 to defray the expense of
reaching the gold fields and purchasing a
year's provisions and outfitting. They
will go by way of Juneau and will leave
as soon as the ■ party is complete and
transportation can be secured. :>
■ It is proposed that the party remain in
Alaska for at least two years. Those who
are strongly considering the ; proposition
made by Griffith are J. C. Berry of 'the
tailoring firm of " Mikkelsen_*' Berry,
Charles Graham and A.B. QuacKenbush ,
all of whom are well known in business.
All of those mentioned are . young men
and are accustomed to ' roughing ' it. Two
of them will leave wives and families.
. H.T. Gilbert, an account' of whose pro
posed trip to the Yukon was published in
a late issue of ; The 1 Call, will leave to
morrow on the Walla Walla for the Tread
well mine. '.'.' .
Football Captain Haskell of the Uni
versity of California eleven and Theodore
Barnes, one of •"" the 'university's*' crack ;
sprinters, are in Alaska at the present
time.V They went up early in the vacation >
for pleasure and to work Vif : they i found
anything suitable. 3 "^ An intimate student
friend of the young men remarked i to-day 1
that he believed * Haskell and Barnes
.would get the Klondyke fever and not rre
turn to Berkeley." ,In that event new
football captain will have to be elected;
Gold 1 In ; Washington.
TACOMA, Wash., July : 19.— Gold has
been found on Section 36, between Gig
Harbor and Henderson Bay. George
Barnaby struck a handful of small nuggets
on Saturday afternoon while working on
the road, and a dozen placer claims have
been staked out. The school section is a
mile from Gig Harbor and two miles from
Purdy on the Gig Harbor and Springfield
road. Several Tacoma and Gig Harbor
men who are investigating believe there is
paying geld on the section, and will com
mence sluicing at once. The find has
diverted some of the excitement over the
Klondyke. Others claim it is an attempt
to secure valuable school lands through
the medium of mineral filings.
Going* From New York.
NEW YORK, N. V., July 19.— H. W.
L'implugh to-day advertised for men to
invest $1000 each in a company to go to
Klondyke. Afterward he explained his
idea was: "To get 'five or six young
fellows to form themselves into an in
corporated company. . Then ,we will go
there by, way of Seattle, Sitka Island and
St. Michaels and lip the Yukon and
straight up to Klonkyke. There each
man would work a claim, and make all
the money he could." He said thirty-two
satisfactory replies had been received to
the advertisement and that the party may
start in a few days. 1 ■■ I :•/*•'•- < -X. uV*?V
RICHEST IN THE WORLD.
Six Miners From the Klondyke Tell
of the Wonderful Finds of
Gold Already Made. .
' A party of six miners direct from the
Klondyke reached here yesterday at noon,
having come down by rail from Seattle.
They are C. E. Myers, B. F. Purcell, J.
O. Clements, Charles Leonard, C. Bran-
nan and J. J. Halterman. The stories
they -tell of the fabulous wealth of the dis
trict they have recently left bear out the
reports which have been coming in for the
past week. They are of the party which
came down on the steamer Portland and
are the advance guard of twenty- or
thirty of their comrades who are expected
to-day.
Myers, who seems to be the leader of the
party, is a practical miner of long experi
ence, and says he left Preseott, Ariz., in
the spring of 1896, and has bepn woreing
claim 30 on El Dorado Creek, owned by
McDonald & Chappie, for half tho profits.
They started in late in the spring, after
nearly every one had quit work, and were
laughed at by the miners for so doing.
The V day after- commencing work they
struck bedrock, and in the next thirty
three days took out $41,000. i.v *,:
• Mr. Myers says he believes ho took from
this claim the biggest pan ever washed in
the district. From i a shovel half full of
dirt he got $800. As illustrating the value
of the claim and the richness of the dirt
he also says that his partner, and himself
in six hours' shoveling "cleaned up" three
times, and in each ."clean up" got $8000.
Myers owns claim 51 above Discovery, on
Bonanza Creek, which be intends to work
next season. ,
Another member of , the . party, J. 0.
Clements, is said to have disposed of a
claim for $50,000, and has in the , safe of
the Golden West Hotel a nugget valued at
$231. The nugget seems to be about half
pure gold, and is a very rich specimen. .-;
Charles Leonard has been three years in
Aiaskn, one of which has been spent in
the Klondyke country. In three and a
half months' actual work he says he took
Yukon Steamer Bella as She Appeared While Gearing in -the Spring From C City.
out $14,000. He is going back in the
spring, and seems to be very well satisfied
with the result of bis work.
B. F. Purcell is a man about sixty years
of age and left his home near St. Louis in
April, 189G, bound for the Yukon. He did
not reach the Kionnyke. however, until
thelst of January, 1897, and while he de
clines to state the amount of gold he has
brought out with him, says that he sold a
half interest in claim No. 28 above Dis-
covery on Bonanza Creek for $21,000, not
including the dirt already on the dump*
and says that he is very well satisfied. As
be expresses it the El Dorado and Bo- |
nanza Creek districts are a golden
wonder, but he is ot the opinion that the
Stewart River country which is about
eighty miles above Dawson and which
was being explored as he came out, will
be found to exceed in richness anything
yet discovered. He says there is room for
200.000 men in the mining districts of I
Alaska without any crowding, but that
the suffering this winter will be terrible
and characterizes any attempt to reach
there this fall as foolhardy.
Myers says, the pay dirt on the claim he
has been working is more than 150 feet
wide and at least a foot in depth and tbat
he has never taken out a pan which gave
less than $1. On claim 27 in the same dis
trict he says there was a streak eight feet
wide and five feet deep which went from
$17 to $82 a pan. That claim sold for
$50,000, and $:00,000 would not buy it to
day. It is owned by "Big" Alex McDon
ald and James Dough try. He tells of a
man named Andrew Nelson who made
$40,000 for a partner who had given him a
grab stake and had never seen the claim.
The largest amount brought down by any
one member of the party is placed at
between $70,000 and $80,000. Myers built
the third house erected at Dawson City,
and says the discovery of gold in '49 is a
mere bagatelle compared to that of the
Alaska placers.
* The men tell harrowing tales of their
sufferings and say that, the hardships
which must be endured in order to exist
cannot be exaggerated. Several of the
party have not yet recovered from the
.scurvy, and ail appear to be physically
demoralized. : Their lust for gold, how
ever, is not dimmed, and they are anxious
to resume the search for hidden treasure. !
While wages are very high, said-one of the '
party, : a man had much better work a ,
claim on shares, for h'.» he's got to make » \
groat (deal jof money to .'repay him for '
going to such a country. " Last winter was !
a mild one. the thermometer only ' reach
ing about 70 degrees below zero. During
a severe season it frequently goes' away
down in the eighties.
Referring to the amount of dust brought
down on the Portland, they say it is im- j
possible to make a correct estimate of the
total, value, as. nearly every man. secreted
all he could- in his personal effects and |
clothing. Said one: "It would not sur
prise me to know that two- million dol- [
lars' worth of dust and nuggets came into
Seattle on thessteamer. ;'.'--.■
With one or two exceptions the men in
tend remaining in San Francisco until
ready to start on their northern journey.
Going to the mines the men say the route i
over the "divide" should always be taken, }
and in coming out the river route is
preferable. One of the men claims to
have lost a satchel in which he had over j
$1000 worth of , walrus ivory, and each of
the men has brought down some of the j
stuff. ; One beautiful specimen of walrus
tusk was shown for which the owner said j
he paid $5, and which must be worth at
least $50 or $60. . , .
A member of the party tells of the ex
perience of a man who located the claim
adjoining his. This man had been in the
Alaska mines for more than five years
and had been unable to make a "strike."
At last, becoming disgusted with his luck,
lie resolved to leave the country. On the
day before he was to leave Circle City
word reached that place of the Klondyke
discovery. He decided to try his luck
once more ana immediately started for
the new diggings. In three months he
had taken out more than $20,0u0 and is
still pegging away, resolved to stay until
be has $500,000. A man should' not, how
ever, ■ say these gold-seekers from the
north, remain in the country 'more than
one season without coming to the world of
civilization. By coming out he acquires a
new lease of life, as it were, and goes back
better qualified' to cope with the hard
ships to which he must submit.
"Oar greatest privation," said Mr. Par
cell, "is the scarcity of fresh meat. A
small band of cattle* was driven in last
fall, and if it had not been for these' I
think a great many of us would have
died. Any kind of beef brings 50 cents a
PRICE FIVE CENTS.
pound, and at times it. is impossible to
get it at any price. At an eating-house
(it could hardly be dignified by the name
of restaurant) two fried' eggs generally
cost $5, and a square meal would cost
more than a day's wages."
Charles Brannan owns claim 38 on
Bonanza Creek, said to be one of the best
paying properties in that particular dis
trict. The patriarch of the party, B. F.
Purcell, who is also one of the most en
thusiastic, says that there is hardly a foot
of ground in either the El Dorado or
Bonanza Creek districts which does not
carry gold in paying quantities, and that
for 300 miles which has been prospected it
is the richest country in the world. "]
do not believe it would be possible to ex
aggerate the wealth to be found there."
said he, "and the future will add to
rather than detract from the marveloui
stories already brought from there."
AN "OFFICIAL" REPORT.
Dominion Surveyor Ogilvie Haa
Sent an Account of the Dis
coveries to Ottawa.
"Official" information about the Yukon
diggings is scare, and valuable.. The off
hand stories of lucky prospectors have
made up most of the tale to date. A Gov
ernment report of the Klondyke digging!
was published but a short time ago, and it
will be read with faith in its reliability.
It is by Surveyor William O.ilvie, located
at Klondyke, for the Canadian Govern
ment, and it was given out by the Gov
ernment at Ottawa. From this report the
following extracts are taken:
The name "Klondyke" is a mispronuncia
tion of the Indian word or words Thron-dak
or Duick, which means pletny of fish, irom
the fact that it is a famous salmon stream, li
is marked Tondack on our map! It joins the
Yukon from the east a few miles above the
site of Fort Reliance, about fifty miles above
Forty Mile. As I hsve already Intimated, thai
rich placer mines of gold were discovered in th«
branches of this stream, 1 believe, was due to
the reports of Indians. A white man named
G. W. Carmach, who worked with me in 1837,
was the first to take advantage of the rumors
and locate a claim oh the first branch, which
was named by the miners Bonanza Creek.
Carmach located here late In August,
but had to cut some logs for the mill
nere to get a tew pounds of provisions to
enable him to begin worK on his claim, the
fishing at Klondyke having totally failed him.
He returned with a few weeks' provisions for
himself, his wife and brother-iD-law (Indians)
and another Indian in the last days of August
and immediately set about working bis claim.
As he was very short of appliances he could
only put together a rather defective appira
tus to wash the gravel with. The gravel itself
he had to carry in a box on his back from 30
to 100 feet.
Nowithstanding this the three men, work
ing very irregularly.^ washed out $1200 in
eight days, and Carmacb asserts with reason
that had he , proper facilities it Could hive
been done in two' days, besides having several
hundred dollars mete gold, which was lost on
the tailings through defective apparatus.
.When it was fairly established that Bonanza
Creek* was rich in gold,' which took a few
days, for Klondyke had been prospected sev
eral times with no encouraging results, there
was a great rush from all over the country
adjacent to Forty Mile. The town was almost
deserted; men who had been in a chronic
stated drunkenness for weeks were pitched
into boats as ballast and taken up to stake
themselves a claim, and claim were stake l by
men for their friends who were not in the
country at the time. All this gave rise to
much confliction ana confusion, there being
no one to take charge of matters. The agent
being unable to go up and attend to the
thing, and myself not knowing what todo, the
miners held a meeting and appointed one o|
themselves to measure off and stake the
claims and record the owners' names, for
which he got a fee of $2, it being of course
understood that each claim-holder would
have to record his claim with the Dominioq
agent and pay his fee of $15.
I am afraid a state of affairs will develop in
the Klondyke district that will worry some
one. Naturally many squabbles will arise out
of those transactions. Many of the claims are
said tb be only 300 and 400 feet long, and ol
course the holders will insist on getting them
the full 500, ana it is now probably impossi
ble that they can without upsetting ail the
claim-holders on the several creeks.
So encouraging were the reports irom the
Klondyse regions that all the creeks around
are practically abandoned, especially those on
the head of Forty-mile, in American territory.
Miller ana Glacier creeks, on the head ol
Forty-mile River, which my survey of the
141 st meridian determined to be in. Canada,
were thought to be very rich, but they are
poor both in quality and quantity compared
with Klondyke. '
The extent of the gold-bearing section here
is such as to warrant the assertion that we
have here a -district which will give 1000
claims of 500 feet in length each. Now 1000
such claims will require at least 3000 men to
work them properly, and as wages for working
in the mines are from $8 to $10 per day, with
out board, we have every reason to assume
that this part of our territory will within a
year or two contain 10,000 souls at least, for
the news has gone out to the coast and an un
precedented influx is expected next spring.
And this is not all. for a large creek called
Indian Creek joins the Yukon about midway
between Klondyke and Stewart River, and all
along this creek'good pay has been found. All
that has stood in the way of j working it here
tofore has been -the scarcity of .provisions and
the difficulty ot getting them up there even
when here. Indian Creek is quite a largo
stream, and it is probable it will yield 500 or
600 claims. 
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 9 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85066387/1898-04-09/ed-1/seq-8/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Buried by a Mighty Avalanche
Lives of Scores of Gold
Seeders Lost in tF)e
Dyea Canyon.
(\ Wall of Snow Crashes Down
Upon a Trail Thronged
by Men Bound for
th>e Klondike-
PARTIAL LIST
OF THE DEAD.
WILLIAM WARNER, San
Francisco.
THOMAS COLLINS, Portland,
Or.
E. D. ATWOOJ\ New York.
C. BECK. Banford, Fla.
MRS. RYAN, Baltimore.
JOHN MORGAN', Emporia,
Kan.
Gl'S SEABOULD, residence
unknown.
L. WEIDELEIN, Kansas City,
Mo.
W. L. RILEY. Seattle.
C. P. HARRISON, Seattle.
GUS ZOBARTH, Seattle.
STEPHEN STEVENSON, Se
attle.
FRANK SPRAGUE. Seattle.
— DUNBAR, Seattle.
F. M. GRIMES, Sacramento.
— RITCHIE, Seattle.
— GARRISON, Seattle.
G. DEARBORN, Seattle.
C. P. HAINES, Seattle.
MRS. ANNA HAXON, Jeffer
son County, Pa.
R. HEPGARD, Baker City. Or.
— ATKINS. Idaho.
THOMAS GEFFERT, Seattle.
E. F. MILLER, Vancouver,
"Wash.
T. LAMER, residence un
known.
— DERBER, San Francisco.
W. E. D. WARD, New York.
W. ENGLAND. Washington.
E. MURPHY, San Francisco.
SERIOUSLY INJURED.
WALTER CHAPPET, New
York.
JOHN C. MURPHY, Dixon,
N. D.
F. B. HOLBROOKE, Portland,
Or.
— DAHLSTROM, residence
unknown.
JUNEAT', Alaska. April 4 (by steam-
Bhip Al-Ki, via Seattle, April B).— A
horrible catastrophe, surpassing in the
number of fatalities the flooding of the
canyon last fall by the mountain lake,
nas occurred in Dyea Canyon, between
Sheep Camp and the Scales. An ava
lanche of snow and ice yesterday after
aoon swooped down the mountain,
burying alive and crushing between
forty and fifty men, and injuring nearly
is many more. There is great excite
ment as Skaguay and Dyea, and many
will leave here for the scene of the dis
ister on the steamship Australia, which
sails late f>-night for Skaguay. The
srst news of the calamity reached here
at 5 o'clock this afternoon on th»
Bteamship Discovery and the Al-Ki
came in at about 8 o'clock to-night and
;onfirmed the report.
The Al-Ki left Skaguay at 9:30 this
morning. As the fatal snow slide oc
curred at about 4 o'clock yesterday
(Sunday) afternoon only meager details
were obtainable here to-night. The
representative of The Cah whom I left
In charge at Skaguay and Dyea during
my absence chartered a tug at Skag
uay last evening to take him around
the point to Dyea and from there he
will go by horse to the place of death.
I will reach the scene to-morrow after
noon.
A telephone message was received at
Skaguay from Dyea late last night,
stating that twenty-seven bodies had
been dug out of the snow. A large force
of volunteers is at work with pick and
shovel throwing aside the snow in the
hope that it may be in time to rescue
Borne of the buried men alive. The res
cuers worked all night.
About 8 o'clock this morning another
message came by telephone from Dyea
stating that eighteen more bodies
had been excavated. If these figures
are accurate they will make a total of
forty-three dead.
The slide occurred in about the same
place where the lake of water broke
loose last fall. It was near Stone
House and over on the other side of the
canyon. John Pellett of Seattle, a pas
senger on the Discovery, left Sheep
Camp yesterday morning, a few hours
before the snow slide. He said:
"The first we heard of the accident
was last evening at Skaguay. The re
port came over from Dyea by tele
phone. I left Sheep Camp early yes
terday morning to catch the first boat
south. It had been snowing steadily
for two days up the canyon. It was a
heavy, wet snow. Great quantities of
It accumulated on the mountain sides,
and I expected some of it to fall down.
There was so much snow that I did not
Bee how it could cling to the sides of the
canyon. Great fields and mountains of
It were piled upon the top of the can
yon on both sides. There are tents and
camps all along the canyon. The men
gx» up loaded early in the morning and
come back to their camp or cache at
Sheep Camp at 11 or 12 o'clock. In the
afternoon they make another trip to
the summit or the Scales, and along
about 4 o'clock and on to 5 o'clock there
j- «». r*Kular crocession of men cominir
bark on the trail. That explains to me
why so many were caught and buried.
"The walls of the canyon opposite
Stone House are almost perpendicular.
A man would have only one chance In
a hundred of petting out of the way
of an avalanche there, even If he
looked up and saw It earning. It would
be a straight fall Instead of a slide. I
heard that thirty-one dead men were
taken out last night."
A little more light Is thrown on the
disaster by the situation of the trails
at Stone House. The horse trail runs
to the right of the canyon, going up
and over close to Stone House. Foot
and handsled trail Is over on th~ op
posite side and follows the course of
the river, which is considerably lower
than the horse trail, and all day Ions?
there are twenty men on the hand
sled trail to one on the horse trail. I
have seen 100 men on this trail within
a distance of fifty yards, going and
coming. Nearly opposite Stone House,
on the brow of the canyon, is a glacier.
Its walls of ice, beautiful as emerald
and sapphire in' the sunshine, an im
aginary cathedral of the skies, stand
exposed in June as well as in January-
It does not melt away the y?ar round.
Mountains of snow crown this glacier
during the winter. This is the point
from which the avalanche came.
A small snow slide which occurred
shortly before the big avalanche buried
two or three men who were encampc-d
along the trail. While those on the trail
were hard at work endeavoring to ex
tricate the unfortunates the monster
avalanche swept down the mountain
side, crushing the tents pitched along
the trail and enveloping scores of men,
the majority of whom were endeavoring
to assist those who had met with mis
fortune in the previous smaller slide.
The injured gold-seekers who have
been rescued are terribly lacerated, and
it is feared that a number of them will
die. As soon as the news of the calam
ity was made known along the trail
men hurried to the scene from Dyea
and other points, and with shovels,
picks and even pans and pails toiled
to extricate the unfortunates. Sheep
Camp was soon left without an inhabi
tant, as every one from there to the
scales was soon on the scene.
The sight was an awful one, for there
in a state of terrible excitement, which
increased as the bodies were uncovered,
were brothers, fathers, sons and friends
anxiously digging, trembling lest the
next body they uncovered should. be
that of a loved one. As in the rush to
the " gold fields, but few men, even
though traveling together, went to the
trouble of inquiring as to the names
of their companions, the greater num
ber of the dead have not been Identi
fied, and those who have been taken
out alive are so benumbed and dazed
that they can hardly tell who had been
in company with them.
The roar of the avalanche could be
distinctly heard at Sheep Camp and as
far as Canyon City, situated about six
miles south of the fatal spot.
Seventeen men. all members of the
Chilkoot Transportation Company,
started over the trail on Sunday morn
ing and had about time to reach the
Scales when the terrible slide occurred.
None of them have since been seen,
and none of their bodies have been re
covered. It Is feared the entire party
was caught in the slide and killed.
There were a good many tents covered
up beyond the reach of rescuers and
numbers of bodies will never be re
covered until the spring sun thaws
away their snow graves.
At the Stone House four big slides
occurred. One hundred men, who were
descending by the aid of a life line 200
yards long, were caught. Of these only
three are known to have been saved.
At the Scales, where the third slide
took place, at least 100 tons of outfits
were covered up. S. A. Townsend of
Fort "Worth, Texas, talking of the cal
amity, says:
"From personal knowledge and in
quiry it is my judgment that at least
150 people were killed by the slides.
When I left Sheep Camp at 10:30 a, m.
on Monday morning thirty-one dead
bodies had been recovered, and the
number of injured that hed been res
cued was reported at twenty-five."
The dead are being laid out in a tent
used as a bunkhouse. Nobody is per
mitted to touch the remains. Many
physicians have gone to the scene from
Dyea, and there are about a half dozen
doctors at Sheep Camp also; so there
is no lack of medical attendance for
the injured. There is a well conducted
tent hospital at Dyea. The law au
thorizes the United States Commission
er at Dyea to act as Governor.
A report that the bodies had been
robbed lacks confirmation. The United
States troops at Dyea would probably
interfere to prevent any desecration of
that kind.
The report that forty-three men had
been killed was corroborated by Purser
Bush of the Al-Ki. One of the men who
brought down the first news of the
avalanche on the steamship Discovery
was Oeorge Bach, who came from
Seward City in February. with the first
information of the loss of the Clara Ne
vada, and who is the only person who
saw her burn. The work of recovering
i the dead from the snow continues.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 10 -->
       <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn90059523/1899-10-15/ed-1/seq-21/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Nome's Golden Sands
MOST WONDERFUL MINING CAMP
ON THE FACE OF THE
EARTH
MARVELOUS FACTS ABOUT IT
Not usual for a Man 'to Pan Out
.$1(1 to $15 an Hour From the
Sitiiit on the Beach—Whether the
Lode Is in the Sou or in the Hills
on Land Has Not Vet Been De
cided.
ST. MICHAELS, Alaska, Sopt. 15.—
The most remarkable gold mining at
present In the world, if not in the entire
history of gold mining, is that now in
progress at and about Cape Nome, on
Norton Sound, Behring Sea, Alaska, sit
uated about 225 miles north and west
of the mouth of the Yukon river, or 135
miles from this point. Gold was first dis
covered on Snake river last fail, and
during the earlier portion of this season.
Cape Nome district had acquired con
siderable repute as a gold producer, and
not a few miners from the Yukon river
f Lx r\* •*•■ rfi^*?--.".^rrT _/^ t 1" "^"^/^^^=k_.^^\!l\ V V / S"^'^
new v ?^p. A^f, .
MAP SHOWING LOCATION OF THE GOLDEN SANDS, AND ILLUSTRATING METHODS OF THE MINERS.
/ country, many of them stranded here,
f went over to Nome and either staked
such claims as they could get, or secured
work as they could find It. Much com
plaint was made that claims had been
taken by persons holding powers of at
torney, their principals not being present
in person, and in June the Cape Nome
district had become so unpopular 'hat
reports were circulating to the effect that
the whole thing was a "fake" foisted on
the public by the transportation compa
nies to Improve their business.
Whatever of truth there may have been
In these stories Is now of small import,
for in June or early July, some one of
the stranded miners tenting on the beach,
as the only unclaimed space, accidentally
discovered gold in the sand at his feet.
He told his story quickly among his
stranded friends, and soon all the unem
ployed were at work on the beach with
any and all kinds of tools that would
dig. Their success was such that within
a few days men who had work on
claims along the creek at $10 a day and
board threw up their jobs and took to
the beach, expecting to earn, and actual
ly earning in many instances, as much in
an hour as they had earned in a day.
Never had such easy mining brnn heard
Df, never had it been found so unex
pectedly and so opportunely, and it was
•lot long before everything else was 2
serted for the seashore, and even wo
olen and boys of 10 or 12 years were to bo
found as busy in the sand as the men
were.
Since the discovery the number of j
"beach combers," as they are called, has I
steadily increased, and today is presented
the strange' sight of hundreds of miners I
rof both sexes and all ages and condl- }
".ions strung out along the beach for a ;
rlozen miles or more.
For miles to the west of Cape Nome the [
oeach runs straight away In a strip of
;lde land, varying from forty to sixty
!eet in width between high and low water
mark, extending up to the "tundra" cr
black alluvial soil, which is from three
to five feet higher than the beach proper.
All of this tundra, ard all the territory
along the creeks and rivers east and west j
for thirty or forty miles and back into j
the mountains for ten or twelve miles had !
been staked, but on the long strip of tide i
lands no man had a better claim than j
another, or could have, under the tide- ;
land laws, and here the grand army of
gold seekers camped, and in very short ;
order had converted the barren strand '■
Into a site of tremendous and enthusiastic
Industry. At the same time business of
all kinds began to respond to the boom
i from the beach, and the usual collection
of gambling hells, saloons and dance
halls went Into operation. At present it
t ls estimated that 1,000 to 1,200 miners are
at work on the beach, extending west for
twenty miles. All these work with rock
_ ers, and they occupy just as much ter
~ ritory to the man or group as can work
It It is not unusual for one small square
bit of beach to pan out $10 to $15 an hour,
but, of course, the space is soon exhaust
ed and the lucky digger must move to
another snot.
. This beach deposit of gold Is as yet
an unsolved problem. By some It Is claim
ed that the gold In the sand, which is
entirely "dust," has been washed out
from the tundra by the waves at high
tide and deposited through hundreds of
years in the sand. It is found here now
from two to five feet below the surface In
the drift, and so plentiful that the miner
who does not find It In paying quantities
is the exception. On the other hand,
there are some who claim that the gold
is washed in from the sea, and that the
real field or "mother lode," so to speak.
Is to be reached and developed by dredg
ing. There may be something in this
theory, but the other seems to be the
more tenable, "-.ark'jpi^eya^fa^
The beach to the east of Cape Nome
makes no such gold showing as does the
beach to the west, owing to the existence
of a long reach of water or "lagoon,"
which lies a short distance back from
the sea and parallel with It. Gold deposits
along the creeks the interior are quite
as rich In one direction as the other.
The headquarters of the Cape Nome
territory is Anvil City—so named from
the shape" of the mountain above It—at
. the mouth of Snake river, although Nome
City is the postofflce. While the city pos
sesses a number of frame houses, tents
are the prevailing shelter, and prices for
commodities are pretty much as they are
In all mining towns. Notwithstanding
this is one of the most' accessible mining
towns on earth, as ships from any part
of the world may come up to its very
doors, making due allowances for no har
bor, and -much delay between ship '- and
shore in bad weather. Meals are from
•$1.50 to $2.50 each; a bed In a tent, $1.50;
plain drinks, 50 cents each; beer, 50 cents
per glass, and other things in proportion,
including a mutton chop at $I.2s—and, by
the way, these are not much in excess of
prices at first-class places ln New York
city. Copper plate for use In rockers is
worth Its weight In silver, and one miner
who had no copper substituted silver dol
lars for It, sixty-four of them being re
quired to properly plate his rocker, which,
added to the first cost of $20, made it
somewhat expensive, even for this local
ity. Labor in the mines Is worth from $8
to $10 a day and board, and even carpen
ters, about the only other class of labor,
are paid $1.50 and hour and board them
selves. As the days In summer are from
eighteen to twenty-four, hours long, a
carpenter can put In a lot of spare time.
Everybody has money, and as many who
have It are not used to It, they are lav
ishing their earnings by day on gambling,
liquor and dance halls at night. Gam
bling takes the bulk of the dust, and
every species of game is represented in
Anvil City.
As to what amount of geld is being
taken out, there Is no means of determin
ing. It is known that not more than $200,
--000 in all have been shipped by steamer,
and $100,000 of that has gone out within
the past week. The beach mining is re
ported to be turning out about $30,000 a
day, but this in the nature of things can
not continue, and when it is exhausted
these men will go to work on the numer
ous claims lying back from the sea and
along the creeks. Here the gold is found
In very rich deposits, the claim of Linde
burg- & Co., on Anvil Creek, turning out
over $1,000 an hour ($25,000 in twenty-four
hours),. one nugget recently found being
worth $312. Another claim, owned by Dr.
Kettlesen, in one day cleared* up $9,000,
and so the stories go. One may hear al
most any kind of a fairy tale, and while
some cf them are exaggerated the fact
remains that just now every man in the
district has a pocket full of dust and ?
heart full of hope, and there are no dead
brokes In- Anvil City. "What the condi
tions will be a year hence will not be
known until then, and cannot be pre
dicted.
Nov. 1 communication with - the outside
world will be completely shut off for sev
en month's at least, and only a few of
(he people now in the Cape Nome district
are fixed with either food or shelter for
the sever!- of the climate, though those
who are prepared with houses to live in
and sufficient food and fuel can not only'
pass the winter comfortably, but can do
more or less work.
There are very few so well eff as this,
however, fuel being scarcer than food,
but among the "beach combers" a novel
plan will be adopted. Parties of four,
six or eight will organize for winter op
erations by securing a large tent, spread
ing ii over the ground they propose to
work In, and there they, will set up house
keeping. The canvas will.be protected on
the outside from the weather in every
way possible, and stoves will be kept go
ing on the inside, so that the tent will not
only be comfortable to live and to work
in, but it will never freeze in there, and
the mining can go on quite as satisfac
torily as if the balmy spring were the
only season known in tho Cape Nome dis
trict A groat rush is expected in the
spring, but, as has been stated, there are
no claims unstaked anywhere . within
thirty or forty miles of Anvil City, and
what lies beyond those limits is pracfical
ly unknown. But, according to the tales
of prospectors, as far beyond as Cape
Prince of "Wales, 2:*5 miles, gold has been
found along the creaks in quantities that
would pay from $10 to $50 per man par
day if panned by an expert.
Claims are offered for sale—a claim be
ing twenty acres—at prices from $50,000
to $150,000, and there are, of course, at
this time not many takers at those, fig
ures, but they are expected In the spring
with the rush.
j -Over 1,000 claims—covering 20,000 acres,
i about thirty square miles of territory
j have been recorded, and It is generally
j believed that each claim represents a
| suit at law, so hasty and haphazard have
j been the methods of procedure in secur
ing claims.
The claims of this entire section are of
the placer variety, and so far no quartz
has been discovered, which means that
what is a busy mining camp with millions
this year may be a deserted village twelve
months later.
Nome gold is much darker in color than
the gold of the Yukon river country, as
saying $19 an ounce, though the current
trading price Is $18 an ounce. Gold dust
and nuggets constitute the bulk of the
currency, and gold scales are as neces
sary in the stores as the ordinary gro
cer's scales.- And gold dust as a circulat
ing medium Is not as popular as it might
be, for coin or paper money coihmandg
a premium of 7 per cent In many local
ities. Such money is known as "che'eha
ko," or "nev/comber." as only the new
arrivals have it, and that. Is the Eskimo
word for new arrivals.
Winter at Anvil City—that is to say, In
the entire Nome ordinarily con
tinues from October to June, and a tem
perature of 50 lo CO degrees below is not
unusual. On Dec. 21 the sun barely rises
above the horizon, and on "June 21 it does
not disappear entirely from sight during
the twenty-four hours.
To the prospective miner in ' the states"
expecting to try his luck in the.:* Cape
Nome rush next spring, or rather next
season, it may ba said.. that he should
keep his attention fixed on weather re
ports from the Northwest and be in San
Francisco, or Seattle. In June., to catch
the first boat out. as Norton bay usually
opens in June. What the faro wi'l be
cannot be told this year, but now It la
$G0 and $75, according to accommodations,
to St. Michaels, and $20 on to Nome by
the small steamers crossing the bay—
miles. The distance direct to Nome from
San Francisco Is about 2.800 miles, and
from Seattle or Tacoma 2,300 miles, and
competition has made the fare to St.*
Michaels the same. What changes the
rush of gold seekers next year will make
remains to be seen. It Is merely an or
dinary agreeable sea trip, and the miner
arriving at Nome Is practically In the
midst of his field of labor as soon as he
goes ashore, and there is little to do ex
cept become a millionaire as soon as con
venient. At the same time It may be re
marked with truth that if hejs comforta
ble at home and is doing fairly well, he
had batter- stay right where he ois and
thank.the Lord for a contented spirit.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 11 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045298/1956-08-25/ed-1/seq-8/</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>-</text>
      </result>
      <!-- 12 -->
       <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1955-02-06/ed-1/seq-172/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Get Real Deed to 1 sq. inch, of Land in Yukon Gold Rusk Country!
■ FACTS ABOUT MFStegt De . dm ~ al , et &’» Fuel sua -», h u,k y^,>^
YOUR YUKON LANS l^ k of land right here M the*® delidou. Quaker breakfast cereal*.
C* — ~ == r? (If P*ck-0-Ten s your favorite, send Quaker Guarantee
3!** *" d V n ** famou * fl 1 Seal instead of boxtop.)
__ «, iwt« wer« aKted'by do* wmm pullin* oo yo«t ridlo. M»ay of th« iptoedfc n.« i " h,lM ‘ tl "~ l *■* y~"^)_
Rni if Actually Own ’,^igg|^"LegET > *l*Fi! No one knows how many brave uk. pUc. n.ar th. propMgy you’ll oam |.wwjfL-3-LL- f^L.ll— ! "_*-""‘-"-V-"-"-T*-‘-‘-V_'JV , J I 'i
1«,. inch of Yukon Land EE£&:‘?ir t “* ,l, ~ £2SsUSL‘fft9ft£' | OJM* BLAMSI SINPNOMOmf
WMjR ev#ry Tuesday and Thursday.) i MAIL TO i DEED. BOX Q, CHICAGO 77, ILLINOIS
SEND TODAY for your authentic deed |I IOT _ AB _.. _ , __ . , _ .. . >v ' * ' Pl**** send ma ■" authentic deed to 1 »q. Inch of Klondike Land. I en- J
that make# you the actual owner of 1 LUST FOR GOLD! They Always Get'Their Man i clot# 1 boxtop from either Muffets Shredded Wheat, Quaker Pulled I
square inch of land near the famous Nothing is stranger ... or stronger ... Canada’s Northwest Mounted Police ‘ ! Qu*»w Psck-O-TW. (Sand J
gald ruth town of Dawson in the fabu- than the lust men have for gold. Ih the * are the moat famous police force in the i
I6us Klondike area of the Yukon. All Gold Rush men fought the wildest coun- world. Mounties are “the Law” in the —ILL J hams _' - • _ , ; (
you do <i fill out the order blank and try on earth and the most savage of di- Yukon. They protect the law abiding X~. r ' , - 1 . i • »«*•«»«'«» ' t
send it along with a boxtop from one of mates to gft to the Klondike where from the desperate breed of men who i in ! address — * , . !
the delicious Quaker Cereals shown at your land is. During the winter the only are often found in the outposts of civi* MzSST |
right. Send no money - just follow di- way to the gold fields was by “mushing" liration. Listen to the thrilling adven- Tg • CITY __ ’ ZONS jtr Arm J J
rectiona on order blank for weak after week. The more fortu- tures of Sot. Preston or THE Yukon 
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 13 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1955-11-20/ed-1/seq-131/</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>-</text>
      </result>
      <!-- 14 -->
       <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045499/1935-12-07/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>JACK LONDON’S
mightiest story gives
Gable his greatest role!
JACK LONDON'S
DOG STORY AT
GAPITOL SUN.
"Call of the Wild,” Famous
Story of Yukon Gold
Rush, Stars Gable
• Call of the Wild-,” screen version
of Jack London's famous dog story,
plays Sunday at the Capitol The
ater. with Clark Gable and Jack
Oakie in the leading roles.
Although the story has ocen re
hashed in the studios to include a
love story and therefore a woman
(in this case. Loretta Young), and
although, in the rehashing, the orig- j
nal plot—that of a civilized dog's
'. eversion to wolf instincts—is so en
tirely lost that the writer of the
pre ent movie publicity forgot 11
mention even that there is a dog In
the picture, the new story is authen
tically London in local color and ad
venturousness, and if you haven't
read the book you will not be disap
nointed. It is one of the really good
■Pictures of the Yukon gold-rush,
vhich Jack London experienced as a j
boy of twenty.
London came to the Gold Rush as
the reaction to a year of hard study
at the University of California. Pre
viously he had. as a boy of fourteen,
left home to join the notorious "oys
ter-pirates” of San Francisco Bay.
He later shipped as a sailor on a
j chooner, as a salmon fisherman ai.d
; even joined a fish patrol. After a seal
! hunting expedition to Japan, he
went back to California and took
; jobs as coal-shoveller, long-shore
man and anything else that turned
up. He tramped a width of the coun
try and even served a term in Jail
■ fer vagrancy. While at the University
| he worked in a laundry to support
\ himself.
; The book, which is in the Juneau
I public library, is well worth any
j body’s reading, and the picture, while
it cannot be considered a faithful
reproduction of the masterpiece, is
i a worthy companion story.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 15 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86090439/1896-05-04/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>HARDSHIPS IN ALASKA.
Gold Hunters Rushing Into Yukon
Country, Perhaps to Starvation.
Provisions High and Work Scarce—Doff
Meat Eaten During Past Winter to
Keep Alive—GrewAomc Reports
from Land of Promise.
News has been received from Forty
Mile, on the Yukon river, in Alaska, that
work there is scarce, provisions high
and that miners who go to the Yukon
country without money are certain to
have trouble and possibly to starve. Six
hundred men wintered at Circle City
and 800 more at Forty Mile. Several
thousand men are rushing in thisspring,
taking, in most instances, only enough
provisions to last them until they reach
the mining camps. As there are but
three steamers plying on the Yukon be
tween its mouth and the mining camps
it is very doubtful if enough supplies
can be taken up the river to feed these
thousands of men over another winter.
The number wintering on the Yukon
this winter will be at least three times
ns great as that last year. Recent let
ters state that provisions became so
scarce in some of the outlying districts
in January that dog meat had to be
resorted to in order to make the regular
provisions hold out until June, when the
first steamer will get up the river. It
is feared that some of the men in these
camps have died of starvation. These
reports have not in the least diminished
the great rush to Alaska. Within a
week 500 men have gone north. Half
of these will go to the Yukon and the
other half to Cook’s inlet.
A letter just received from Forty Mile
says:
"Of the 200 or 300 miners who left the
Yukon last fall nearly everyone was
“broke.” There were a dozen in our party
when we came In last March, some of whom
spent eight or ten years on the river, and
they were all “broke.” Still they had mado
people on the outside believe they were
rich. At present our best prospect is the
hope of getting trusted at the stores, but
if the miners are fortunate next summer
everything will be O. K. But few new pros
pects were opened up here last summer.
The problem I am trying to solve is the
buying of a whole year’s provisions, for
prices have gone up. If a man can make
enough money in the summer time to buy
a year’s grubstake and clothing he runs a
good chance of finding paying dirt by pros
pecting in the winter time. However, a
miner might live here 20 years and not find
a good prospect. At the present time,
January 25, the thermometer stands 70
degrees below zero.”
A. L. Smith, who went to the Yukon
country last year, writes:
"The mines haven’t turned out as well a.
expected. Provisions are very scarce at
some camps. The condition of exiles in
Siberia is preferable to living in this God
forsaken place.”
These letters are more discouraging
than any others received. Others say
that the Yukon is a good country for
men y ho have $5OO and can stand hard
knocks.' r •'
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 16 -->
       <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/2018270505/1915-10-01/ed-1/seq-78/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>UNION CONSTRUCTION COMPANY
AMM0U1CEMEMT
THIS COMPANY announces that it has made arrangements with the Bucyrus Company to t
act as its exclusive agent for Gold Dredges and repair parts in the Western United States, {
Alaska, Yukon Territory and British Columbia. I
This arrangement will result in the co-ordination of the manufacturing facilities of the J
Bucyrus Company with the knowledge and experience of the Union Construction Company, J
gained in the design and construction of gold dredges in all parts of the world in which this type i
of mining is carried on- f
Thus the service rendered to users of gold dredging machinery, both present and prospec- I
tive, will be even more thorough and complete than in the past. |
Those contemplating the installation of this class of machinery, as well as those at present |
engaged in their operation, will find it to their advantage to place their problems before us. |.
EIGHTEEN of our new type of light weight portable gasoline prospecting drills were in use
this season.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 17 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn87062169/1925-04-30/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>YUKON PIONEER DIES
IN SAN DIEGO, CALIF.
SEATTLE, April 30.—Word has
been received from San Diego, Califor
nia, of the death of Michael Moore, a
pioneer Yukon-Alaska gold seeker who
went from! Butte to Nome in 1S98, lat
er going to Fairbanks and the Idita
rod. Moore was never lucky as a gold
seeker but had interests in extensive
coal deposits in the Bering Sea dis
trict before the entries were with
drawn by the government.
. ••
Fake Mining Schemes
Detriment To Alaska
SEATTLE, April 30.—The Seattle
Mining Club, organized to check fake
promoters and help legitimate mining
by publicly condemning shady ven
tures and approving worthy projects,
will greatly help Alaska. Charles G.
Titus,, a Valdez mining engineer said.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 18 -->
       <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045462/1959-08-02/ed-1/seq-166/</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>-</text>
      </result>
      <!-- 19 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82015679/1897-07-18/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>ALASRAS GOLD FEVER
IT HAS STRUCK THE NORTHWEST,
-MAY BECOME EPIDEMIC.
Another Steamer Beturns with Miners
and Has* of Nuggets from the
Klondike District.
♦
TALKS WITH THE LUCKY ONES
POVERTY-STRICKEN MEN WHO
.MADE FORTUNES IN TWO MONTHS.
.
Advice to “Tentlerfeet” Who Are
Thinking of .Making a Rash
for the Rich Fields.
PORT TOWNSEND, Wash., July 17.-
At 3 o’clock this (Saturday) morning the
steamship Portland, from St Michael’s for
Sesattie, passed up the sound with more
than a ton of solid gold on board and many
passengers. In the captain's cabin are
three chests and a large safe filled with
the precious nuggets. The metal is worth
nearly $7u0,000, and the most of it wait
taken out of the ground in i*ss than three
months last winter. In size the nuggets
range from the size of a pea to a guinea
egg. Os the sixty-eight miners aboard hard
ly a man has less than S7,O(H), and one cr
two have more than SIOO,OOO in yellow nug
gets. One peculiar feature noticed is that
the big strikes were made by “tenderfeet,”
while the old and experienced miners of
many years’ experience are suffering in
describable hardships and privations in
Alaska and the Northwest Territory, and
have only a few thousand dollars to show
for their labor. Fortune seemed to smile on
the inexperienced men who went into the
mining districts late last year, as nearly all
of them were unfortunate. The
stories that they tell seem to
be incredible and far beyond be
lief. Instances are noted where single in
dividuals have taken out. in two and a half
months, gold to the value of over $150,000.
Clarence Berry, of Fresno, Cal., went to
the Yukon in 1890 and prospected several
years without success. He returned home
last autumn, was married and took his
bride to the Klondyke last November. He
is now- on the Portland with $135,000, the
result of a winter’s -work. Frank Phisca
ter, of Borado, Mich., is another lucky
miner. He went to the Kionayke last au
tumn and is now returning with $96,027, hav
ing worked two claims with nine men three
months, and he still owns the claims. He
was one of the original discoverers of the
Eldorado district. Although most of the
passengers are returning home with plenty
of gold they all advise and urge people who
contemplate going to the Y’ukon not to
think of taking less than one ton of grub
and plenty of clothing. While it is a poor
man’s country, yet the hardships and pri
vations to be encountered by inexperienced
persons unused to frontier life is certain to
result in much suffering. They should go
prepared with at least a year’s supplies.
COST OF AN OUTFIT.
Here’s a. Pointer for "Tenderfeet” Go
ing; to Alaska.
SAN FRANCISCO, July 17.—San Fran
cisco had a bad attack of gold fever, Fri
day, vffien the reports of the riph discover
ies in the Klondyke district were read.
Hundreds of old miners hunted up the meh
who arrived on the steamer Wednesday,
and obtained facts about the outfit and
money needed for the trip. Mr. J. C. Hest
wood, who has spent three years in Alas
ka, gave the best description of the chances
for the tenderfoot. He brought out SIO,OOO
as the result of two months’ w T ork on his
claim, which is about ten miles from Daw
son City. Mr. Hestwood said:
"To go into the Yukon requires $250 for
an outfit and about the same amount in
cash. To do anything in mining, except as
a day laborer, requires from $5,000 upwards.
The rich pay dirt is only struck near bed
rock, and this generally lies from eighteen
to twenty-five feet below the surface.
“The method of mining is to remove the
surface mass, which is eighteen inches
thick, and then build a fire, wffiich burns
all nig'nt. In the morning the gravel is
thawed down about two feet. This is shov
eled out and another fire is built, and in
this slow and laborious way the ground is
removed to bed rock. This work can be
carried on all winter, except when the mer
cury falls 60 below zero.
“Dawson City is a booming tow nos about
I, inhabitants, and is growing rapidly.
Provisions were scarce and dear last win
ter, and all supplies are costly. An ordi
nary seventy-flve-cent pocket knife sells for
$4. and shoes bring from $6 to SB. Eggs sell
readily at $4 per dozen. Flour sold as high
as $1 a pound.”
Mr. Hestwood showed many small nug
gets from the new Bonanza creek district,
where his mine is situated. The gold is the
color of brass and is worth sl6 to sl7 an
ounce. It is not as pure as is found else
where on the Yukon.
They did not hear of McKinley’s election
until last June, but Mr. Hestwood says
there were few silver men in camp. Some,
however, feared that gold would depreciate
in value because of the prospective enor
mous output of these mines.
The new camp is peculiar for several rea
sons. The prospectors don’t have a dead
man even once a week in Dawson City, the
headquarters of the camp, because Cana
dian provincial police do not allow men to
carry arms. If miners get drunk and fight
they use their fists, and the land laws are
so good that no claim jumping is possible.
Dawson City has now' four thousand people,
and it is expected that two thousand more
will swarm in before snow flies and the
trail from Juneau is closed for the winter.
J. O. Hestwood, one of the miners who
came back Wednesday, said:
“Modern history records nothing so rich
in extent as the placer mines of the Yukon
district. The gold dust which was turned
into the Sebly Smelting Company’s office
Wednesday is only a slight Indication of
what is to follow in the near future. The
climatic conditions of that ice-bound re
gion are such. how*ever, that only the very
courageous should seek fortunes there.
Food is scarce, distances to be traversed
are great and the country is inhospitable.
“A great many men went into the coun
try poverty stricken last year and came out
this spring with thousands of dollars, yet
that does not signify that every chu-chow
ko (newcomer) will be able to do the same.
There is plenty of room there for five thou
sand more able-bodied men. but let no one
undertake the task of getting there until
ho first considers what he must bear and
undergo to reach the El Dorado of the far
north, remembering that wealth from min
ing in that region, as a rule, is more acci
dental than o.herwfse.”
The stories of returned miners vary onty
in details. L B. Rhodes, an old miner,
tells the following history of his good for
tune: “1 am located on Claim 21, above
Discovery, on Bonanza creek. I was among
the fortunate, as I cleared about $400,060,
but brought only $5,000 with me. I was the
first man to get to bedrock gravel and to
discover that it was lined with gold dust
and nuggets. Tne rock was seamed and
had V-shaped streaks, caused, it is sup
posed, by glacial action. In those seams I
found a clay which was exceedingly rich;
in fact, there was a stratum of pay gravel
four feet thick upon the rock, which was
lined with gold, particularly in those chan
nels or streaks. The rock was about six
teen feet from the surface. That discovery
made th’e camp. It was made on Oct.
23, 1896, and as soon as the news spread
everybody rushvd to the diggings from Cir
cle City, Forty Mile and every other camp
in the district. There was a lack of food.
We had nothing but w hat we sledded from
Forty Mile. Flour sold as high as $45 a
suck, and shovels at $lB apffiee. I Invested
my money in another claim, a two-thirds
divided interest in Claim 23. If I had not
bought in 1 would have brought down at
least $25,000, but the investment there is
the best security and pays interest from
15 to 25 per cent, a year.”
Fred Brice said that there were four
miles of good claims on El Dorado creek
and ten miles of claims on Bonanza creek.
He brought down sj*uoo and left $’:0,000 in
vested in the gold flaim. He warned all
prospectors to take full outfits, as there
was no credit at the stores, even if a man
is starving.
♦ .
GOING TO THE KLONDYKE.
Expedition* to the Gold Field Prepar
ing; to Stnrt ut Onee.
SEATTLE, Wash., July 17. —“When are
you going to the Klondyke?” In twelve
hours that question has been asked and
answered a hundred thousand times In Se
attle. On the streets, in the houses, every
where is heard nothing but Klondyke, and
the whole town is ieverish and agitated as
never before over the Alaska gold discover
ies. Men who cannot go are forming pools
to grubstake men wffio will. Ex-Governor
John H. McGraw ■will leave on the next
steamer. Gen. E. M. Carr, of the State mil
itia, who at one time camped within seven
miles of the fabulously rich placer, will go.
Col. Joe Green and A. J. Balliet, Y'ale’s
great oarsman, are packing their effects,
and attorneys, doctors, clerks and laborers
are all scheming to secure a share of the
vast wealth in the north.
Indescribable expectation is directed
toward the steamer Portland, due at any
hour from St. Michael's. She has at least
a million dollars in gold aboard and will
bring news of Seattle men who have risked
their lives for gold. Every one says that
at last the mother lode of the Pacific coast
has been found and that the half has not
been told. The reports have caused intense
excitement here. Policemen are resigning
from the force; every street-car man that
can raise a stake has given notice to his
company. In fact, all classes of society
are represented in the feverish rush to get
north. The men neglect their business and
congregate in groups on the streets in ex
cited discission. People are telegraphing
friends and relatives in the East to come
and join them in the new Eldorado. The
steamer Portland has not yet been reported
at Tattosh and her coming is awaited with
intense anxiety. She will probably arrive
some time to-morrow, and is billed to sail
July 20 on her return voyage. The steamer
offices are rushed with business and out
fitting stores are taxed to their utmost ca
pacity to supply the wants of those who are
getting ready to make the trip. Merchants
are fearful that their help will leave them
and they will be unable to fill their places.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 20 -->
       <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn99063955/1897-07-20/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>ALASKA.
Excitement Greater in Alaska Than
Anywhere.
Port Tqwnsend, Wash , July 20
Tho excursion steamer Queen' ar
rived from Alaska with 170 passen
gers, principally tourists.
If reports be not overdrawn by the
ofliccrs of the Queen, the excitement
at Juneau over the rich gold ilnds In
tho Klondyke country Is much more
Intense than herein tho Pacific states
Merchants and tradesmen in both
Juneau and Sitka arc closing their
stores and shops and hastening to the
new Eldorado.
Fifty business men left Juneau for
Dawson City on the Klondyke July 12,
and 150 would leave on the 10th, two
days after the Queen sailed. The of
liccrs said that by tho time tho Queen
returns to Juneau on her regular trip,
nine days hence, there will not be an
able-bodied man left in town. Many
men aro leaving Juneau for the gold
Holds without provisions or means to
buy them.
The fow Alaskans who came down
on tho Queen were greatly gratified to
learn of the appointment of C. S.
Johnson, of Juneau, to the position of
United States attorney for that dis
trict. Johson was appointed to the
same position -in 1880, going north
from Nebraska. His prosecutions
were so vigorous as to win for him an
envlablo rcputatatfon, henco tho ex
ulting of tho Alaskans at'Wf6 present
appolntmtint.
Reports fro m tho various salmon
fisheries in Alaska arc that fish are
very scarce. Tho fishing season at
Orca has been very poor so far and a
small pack will bo made. Tho Pacific
Steam Whaling company has packed
to dato 15,000 cases of red salmon and
tho Alaska Packers' association about
8000 cases . Tho prospect for tho pack
at Cook inlet Is very good, tish having
commenced to run fairly well. At
Karluk, the salmon have just com
menced to run nnd tho outlook Is not
encouraging for the spring run.
The Pacific Steam Whaling com
pany and numo brothers have built
two largo cannery plants at Karluk
this 6eason. Tho Psciflc Steam Wha
ling company is at tho present time
building a largo cannery nt Kcnal
river, Cook inlet.
Tho manager of tho Oceanic Pack
ing company at Point Roberts in
formed the Associated Press corres
pondent today that from tho com
panys four traps neqr San Juan pass
an average of 20,000 sockoyo salmon
aro being taken daily. Such a heavy
run is unprecedented.
        </text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
