<topics>
  <topic>
    <id>https://guides.loc.gov/chronicling-america-yellowstone/</id>
    <results>
      <!-- 1 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83016555/1871-12-22/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>A Great National Park.
Hon. N. P. Langford, of Slontann, the
leader of the famous Yellowstone expedi
tion of last year, is now in Washington,
and, in eonneetion with Professor Hayden,
who had charge of the government expedi
tion of this year, is engaged in promoting
the project of declaring all that district, in
cluding the canon of the Yellowstone, the
hot springs and the geysers a government
reservation, for the purpose of holding it
forever as a national park. • Copies of the
May and June numbers ot Scribner's Month
ly. containing Langford's graphic story of
"Tnc Wonders ol the Yellowstone," have
been furnished to every member of Con
gress. Professor Hayden lias prepared an
article f«r the February number of Scrib
ner's. in which he confirms Langford's ac
count. describes additional marvels discov
d by himself, aud takes strong ground
in favor of the park project. Such a park
will, in time, attract to it crowds of the
pleasure seekers and scientists of Europe
It is not only remarkable for its scenery,
but in a scientific point of view is said to
be "the most marvelous region on the face
of the earth." The illustrations, which are
to appear in the February number of Scrib
tier, are lroin photographs taken by the re
cent expedition.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 2 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84026355/1896-02-29/ed-1/seq-9/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>YELLOWSTONE
ONE OF NATURE'S WONDERS
Crowning Triumph of America's Won
derland. Yellowstone Park.
WORDS FAIL TO DESCRIBE IT
Ural of Scrlos of Illustrated Letters
Devoted to the Curioui and
Scautlful Sccnee la tlia No
tlonal Reservation.
Written for Tire Trllntne.
Here boglns another chnpter of our
Story. Having crnssed the continent
over the main line of the Northern J'n
elllo railway and witnessed. Its Rrnmli'tir
vt scenery and Hiirnrlws for twenty
ftBht suifesHlve days, we will retrace
our HtepH tor two thousand inlloa to
LlvliiRston and Rather up Home of the
wonderful scenery we lost In linssin";.
We will re-enter for that purpose the
portal of the Yellowstone National
Park, "Tho Wonderland of North
America."
When this Indian reservation was
set aside to be forever the Brand tourist
reHort of the people and their common
property by the peneral Kovernnient,
few had any Idea of the endless variety
and stupendous grandeur of the fea
tures embraced In tills tract of country
Klxty-five by seventy-five miles In ex
tent. This volcanic, region Is located
about midway in our national domain.
It nestles in the heart of the Kooky
mountains covering un nrea of :i.57;i
mpiure miles and Is encircled by ning
liillcent snow peaks from ten to nearly
fourteen thousand feet high. No valley
within its limits has an elevation less
than G.000 feet above sea level, while the
averaK Is about H.UuO feet. This freak
of nature is only a little spot of earth
in the northwest coiner of Wyoming,
coverliiff a few miles of Montana on the
north and overlapping into Idaho and
Montana on the west. It is one
of thu preatPst water-sheds on the
earth. Three of the larRest rivers in
the United States have their source in
Yellowstone park tho Missouri, the
Yellowstone, the Snake. These Htrenins
born within HlRlit of each other, lose
themselves in three mighty rivers that
seek old ocean thousands of miles apart
from each other. Here, too, is the lar
Reat body of water in North America
lit this altitude of nearly 8,000 feet.
Within this wonderful domain are fifty
peysers which uro said to outclass
MAMMOTH HOT
nnythlnjj In the known w orld, throwing
legulurly a column of hot water from
thirty to two hundred and lifty feet
in the air between intervals of from
one minute to fourteen days, besides,
within the boundaries of this wonder
ous geyser land there are known to be
una hundred geysers and 3.600 springs
and pools, together with paint pots,
mud springs, lukes canyons, rivers and
small parks, ad infinitum. Here in the
"Grund Canyon of the Yellowstone,"
ten miles long with, an average depth
of a quarter of a mile which 1 ac
knowledged to be the most brilliantly
colored landscape in existence, and
"Mammoth Hot Springs," the only col
ored terrace-building hot springs know n
that liuve such beauty and magnitude;
also cliffs of volcanic glass, mountains
of petrefactlon, hills or brimstone, un
surpassed waterfalls, interspersed with
thousands of natural curiosities, sur
rounded by perpetual snow clad peaks
which rise Into cloudland. all of which
fittingly characterize this as the won
derland of America and of the world.
' ITS HISTORY AND DISCOVERY.
This weird and enchanted spot Is only
M recent .discovery. Often did the
thought occur to us as w traversed it,
, why was it so long undiscovered. It
was not until 1870 that this remarkable
locality became known, although as far
bark as 1S06 some Inkling of what was
to be found there was Riven bv the
Lewis and Clark exploring expedition.
The stories then told came largely
from frontier guides and mountaineers
and were disbelieved, and more than
Ixty years elapsed before the residents
of Montana attempted to explore it,
althought several expeditions sent out
by the government had crossed the con
tinent In search of the most suitable
route for the Pacific railway; in fact.
the whole western domain was crossed
and re-crossed by these exploring
parties, and still the Yellowstone Park
country remained undiscovered. It was
left to John Colter (the first white ex
plorer) to know and tell of its wonders,
and then to General Washburn, in 1870,
to enter the Inner wilds of this myster
ious land, escorted by Lieutenant
Doaae, of the United States army, and
in 1871-72 for Professor P. T. Hayden,
United States geologist, to make a
thorough discovery under the sanction
of congress and largely through his ln-
V ( iVo wi row tiri
PARK.
6; permission of tho Evangelist.
fluence and efforts it became a national
reservation. It peonis strange that a
region so remarkable as this, was so
long an unknown land to us. That,
this is so. Is undoubtedly mvlng to the
fact that from the east and south the
Park Is almost impossible of approach
on account of the character of the
mountains. Tho region is more than
lifty miles south of the nearest route
traveled by explorers, besides hostile
Indians were in this Immediate vicinity
in very early days. Hut the question
is aptly unsweivtl by Mr. O. 1). Wheel
er, probably the best informed of any
of the Northern l'ucilie olllclals, who
says in substunce, "(lod moves In a
mysterious way, and in Ills inscrutable
wisdom He so concealed this grand her
itage that It would nut be discovered
LIBERTY CAP.
until the American people were suf
ficiently able to appreciate it. as to
preserve it In nil tts Integrity, its nat
ural grandeur and beauty forever. Just
us nature made it." Since the Park
was reserved for Its present purpose,
congress has set aside as a "timber re
serve" nnother tract on the south and
east of about two thousand Bqunre
miles, making the- entire reservation
one-fourth larger than my native state,
Connecticut. This ni t prevents the tim
ber here from being cut down or want
only burdened under severe penalties.
SPRINGS HOTEL.
The completion of the Northern rarlfic
railway across the continent was an
important event for the Park, espe
cially so when their branch line of
fifty-one miles brought them to Cinna
bar at its northern boundary. Thin
road brings the tourist from his far
away home and sets him down amidst
the mountains and confines of this
wonderland. "Thus far und no far
ther," said Mr. Wheeler to t ie, "i
Uncle Sam's edict to railroads, and
none may venture beyond the imagin
ary boundary line."
Connected with the Park are four
Important factors, each Independent of
the other, yet co-ordinate branches.
These are the United States govern
ment, the Northern Pacific railway, the
V - eV- '"TZ- AT'W
Yellowstone Pork association, and tho
Yellowstone National Park Transpor
tation compuny. Like four separate,
yet integral parts of the samo machine,
thry work sympathetically and ,Jhar
ninnioutdy toward tho same end. The
avenue of annrouvh. to the Park Is one
entirely in keeping with its character.
Having given our readers a condensed
outline of this mysterious land of won
ders, we will invite them to follow us
in our dally travels through It. We
leave the main line of the road and
start in to see the park at Livingston,
for it's only through Livingston on the
Northern Pacific road, that we can
reach it. Livingston as described In a
former letter, lies at the base of the
Know and Helt ranges spurs of the
Kocky mountains.
Some people, like ourselves, have an
idea, that we enter the Park on the
same elevation above the sea, ami in
the same manner as itv would enter
Kaliniount Park, of Philadelphia, or
Central Park, New York. This Is a
mistaken idea we commence at Llv
iiiKslon on elevation above sea level
hi 4.4 .0 feet, urn! ascend to Cinnabar,
filfy-uiie miles, on a grade of eighty
feel to the mile overcoming 700 feet.
We do not leave our drawing-mom
car until Ciimaliar is reached. The
ride through this Interesting valley,
hounded by mountains, is mi appro
priate prelude to what follows in the
park Itself. It Is called a park. Your
minds shuliM be disabused of a mis
conception. It has nothing such as an
ordinary park would Indicate. No
gravelled walks no velvety lawns, no
statuary, no (lower beds, etc., but all
this extensive area Is literally crowded
with natural curiosities of the most
wonderful character. The hotels and
the government roads and bridges are
the only artificial things to be found
here, everything else being In Its nat
ural condition, rude, stein and wild.
Three miles from Livingston, . the
railroad passes through the first "can
yon of the Yellowstone," which forms
a natural entrance Into the I'pper Yel
lowstone valley. This canyon Is about
u mile long and Just wide enough to
comfortably admit the read und river,
the mountain walls rising 2,000 feet
perpendicularly on either side. Pass
ing through this first canyon we enter
Paradise valley, which Is from seven
to twelve miles wide and extends some
thirty miles along the Yellowstone river
which tumbles anil pounds continuous
ly, clear as crystal and cold as Ice.
This valley lias been settled by ranch
men. The land Is very fertile nnd Irri
gation has been carried on to a high
state of perfection, making the valley
as productive as the corn belt of Illi
nois, The rich ranches strolohliig-be-
f
yond the level upon the moraines, look
like great Persian rugs with their har
monious blending of colors, put this is
not the district In which one wishes to
specify and particularize. As the train
moves southward, the mountain scen
ery is ever changing and picturesque.
The most prominent peak Is Emigrant,
In the south end of the valley, which
rises proudly a mile anil a quarter
above tho valley to an elevation
of Hi.fi29 feet. Forty miles fronr Liv
ingston we puss through the "second
canyon of the Yellowstone," called
"Y'linkee Jim Canyon," named for an
enterprising Yankee, who, prior to
bulldliifr the railroad, built a wagon
road through the canyon at great ex
pense and enjoyed a lucrative business
In collecting toll from each visitor to
the park. Yankee Jim Is still located
here and has many piscatorial guests
during the tourist season, who tind the
best of trout fishing In these swift wat-
rs. This canyon Is far more pictur
esque than the first, as the mountain
walls rise higher, und Hie gorge within
which the river Is compressed. is scarce
ly loo feet wide. This valley Is the bed
f an ancient lake, with glaciated boul
ders strewn around, affording views of
rocky i iits and spurs
t'lnnnbar mountain is an object of In
terest. Here Is n group of vertical
beds nearly a half mile hlh. Kxtctuling
from the bnsq, to the summit, Is n red
dish band of arenaceous clay about 100
feet wide, called Cinnabar, which gave
the name of the mountain. "The Devil's
Slide" Is found her, formed by two walls
of trap-rock some l.'iO feet apart, which
precipitates 2,tHio feet down a mountain
Hank like a toboggan slide, and Is
strikingly realistic to the tourists. One
says, "It demonstrates how easy His
Satunle Majesty makes it In life for
any one to go down hill."
STAfSR TltAXSPOIlTATIOX.
Arriving nt Clnmib.ir. the transporta
tion company take up the work of st-re
transportation through the park, a dis
tance of one hundred and sixty miles.
Here is a line of six-horse tally-ho
coaches awniting the tourist for a drive
of seven miles to Mammoth Hot Springs
hotel.
Having exchanged our seats In the
comfortable chair car fur others equal
ly inviting In the grat coaches, v.e
commence the ascent of 2.000 feet In
seven miles to the famous hotel. Thin
ride is the first day's pleasure drive in
the park, and it is over an excellent
macadamizi d road; and right here I
wish to emphasize the superiority of
TERRACES AT MAMMOTH SPRINGS.
Yellowstone Park rouds, for to mo
among the pleasant feutures of the
park trip was the strong bridges, grace
ful curves and good roads. We wind
along the Gardiner river, which has Its
source from the snow ravines of "Klcc
trlo Peak," clear as crystal and cold
as ice; this river unites with the Yel
lowstone at Cinnabar. The grade gf
the carriage road . is. very steep, as
nearly ii.OOO feet hus to be overcome be
fore reaching Mammoth Hot Springs,
mainly in the last two miles, -when the
road leaves the river to ascend the
mountain. Klght ut this point 1 toiling
or Hot river empties into the cold, pure
waters of the Gardiner. The former Is
the combined ovei llow of ull the waters
of Mammoth Hot Springs, made' fa
mous from the fact that fish may bo
cuught In the cold stream and cooked
in the but stream without change of
position. After a long climb a sudden
turn is made, and the famous Mam
moth Hot Springs hotel is seen in tie
distance, and presently we pass
through a gateway of ruck and behold
the strangest and most fascinating
sight unlike unything , seoil else
where, it Is a rang. of snow
white terraces, rising like glguutie
steps of marble forming ii.-bus.in
filled with boiling bubbling water, heat
ed by nuture's furnace, und sending
forth clouds of ste;:ui. These ter
races are the . gorgeously arrayed,
exquisitely filigreed, nnd richly col
ored cliffs of "Mammoth Hot
Springs." In front of us Is a level
plateau, where, besides the famous ho
tel, are several other buildings, uinoug
them Camp Sheridan, the headquarters
of the superintendent of the park, and
proudly floating from his oflielal resl-'
dence, was the "stars and stripes'
which gracefully'salutcd us In acknowl
edgement of "three cheers for the old
Hag," alter we set foot on our own
nationul domuin, the wonderland of
America. .
This park is under the exclusive con
trol of the secretary of the Interior,
with Contain George S. Hunter as su
perintendent, and two companies of
cavalry. With United States soldiers
for police, it Is the most law abiding
section in our country today. There
are no saloons, no gambling houses,
thieves, highway robbers, or Indian
massacres. No man, except he be n
federal olllcer, can carry fire-arms of
any description. These two com
panies nntrol the park that no net of
vandalism be committed or the marvel
ous and delicate formations be disturbed.
These soldiers stand guard over all this
domuin according equal rights to ull
and sperj 1 favors to none.
A st a' trout story nnd we close this,
our first day's park experience. As we
reached the "Mulling river" on our
stage ride from t'lnnubar, our attention
was called to two gentlemen who were
fishing in the Ice cold Gardiner river.
One of them had cuught a' trout and
without unhooking It, he swung tlie line
nnd fish over into the boiling river, nnd
It was said the fish was cooked and
ready for the fable In less time thnn it
takes me to tell the story. This is my
first fish story. Tell me if this is not
Wonderland.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 3 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030214/1903-04-05/ed-1/seq-30/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>SNOW .S DEEP .N YELLOWSTONE PARK, AND PRESENT ROOSEVELT MAY HAVE TO USE SK.S WHEN HE GETS f HER E
TRAVELLING ON SKIS.
In Harden Valley, Yellowstone Park.
ROOSEVELT OA 7 SKIS.
President May Have to Use Them
in Yellowstone Park.
Probably no one has ever seen a President of
faese United States Sticking head first ma
Vowl.ank. thrown there by a tricky pair of skis.
Most President* have kept .way from «.o«
banks, and the thought of mixing up with sk.s
never entered their heads.
The soldiers who will guide and [Presi
de Roosevelt through Yellowstone Park when
he reaches that interesting portion of Ins com-
Vg Western trip may witness such a phenome
ii o n The snow in the park is from sixteen to
eighteen feet deep in many places, and the
President will surely have to take to sk.s if he
frets anywhere. He is not exactly a snowshoe
amateur, however, and the chances are very
uoh in favor of some one else taking the
\ aders while the Chief Kxecutive leads the van.
From Mammoth Hot Springs to the Golden
Gate a distance of five miles, there is a broken
trail and the party can ride on horseback. Be
yond that point the park, with its white cover
ing will seem almost as primeval as it did to
John Colter or "Jim" Badger, the first white
men to enter that wonderland of nature. April
is one of the eight or nine months in which the
park Is snowed in and the ordinary tourist
snowed out. In May th- stage roads thaw out,
and for three months there are visitors every
where.
Winter used to be the time of game harvest
for Wyoming hunters until the government de
cided to protect the game by keeping a com
pany of soldiers on the reservation the year
round. It still is the hunting season for the
lawless "bad men" who have taken refuge in
the Jackson's Hole Country, which is on the
edge of the park.
The President is going hunting for game, but
not that ho may add to his large score of centre
Bhots and things killed. Instead of a gun he
will be hunting with the naturalist, John Bur
roughs. There is no better season for seeing
the wild game with which the park abounds.
Larue bands of elk have been driven into the
GIANTESS GEYSER.
A winter eruption in Yellowstone Park,
NEW YORK TRIBUNE ILLUSTRATED SITPLEMENT.
lower basins by the heavy snow, and it is pos
sible that the troopers may have to feed them
hay before the President arrives. Even the
mountain sheep, it is said, can be approached
within forty or fifty feet.
Any one who knows the President must real
ize that he will enjoy every minute of his trip
through the. Yellowstone. In his -The Wilder
ness Hunter" he says tli.u snowshoeing is a
sport that must appeal to -very active sports
man, and he ranks it with mountain climbing.
He learned to use snowshi es in the Maine woods
before he entered politics, and his skill with skis
was acquired while ranching in the Had Lauds.
Here is the story <f his » rst winter hunting
as he has written it in one of his books:
••l enjoyed the trip, for the northland woods
are very beautiful and strange in winter, as
indeed they are at all other times- and it was
my first experience on snowshoes. I used the
ordinary wcaved racquets, and as the snow,
though very deep, was only imperfectly crusted,
I found that for a beginner the exercise was
laborious in the extreme, speedily discovering
that, no matter how cold it was, while walking
SKI RACING BEHIND HORSES. «„«, Into the serricect
This is a comparatively new depart,:. Wltaln.ts* last jy m *»» C l^S^?S» be eorer*d mt •««*■«££
h£&2&3r& sksksss oa «« **. «*• work a <**« *
pleasantly invigorating, and not particularly laborious. __
through the wilderness woods I stood in no need
of warm clothing. But at night, especially ween
lying out, the cold was bitter.
"Our plan was to drive in a sleigh to some
logging camp, where we were always received
with hearty hospitality, and thence make hunt
ing trips, in very light marching order, through
the heart of the surrounding forest. The woods,
wrapped in their heavy white mantle; were still
and lifeless. There were a few chickadees and
woodpeckers; now and then we saw flocks Of
red polls, pine linnets an.l large, rosy gros
beaks; and once or twice I came across a
grouse or white rabbit and killed it for supper;
but this was nearly all. Yet, though bird life
was scarce, and though we saw but few beasts
beyond an occasional porcupine or squirrel,
every morning the snow was dotted with a net
work of trails made during the hours of dark
ness: the fine tracery of the footprints of the
little woodmouse, the marks which showed
the loping progress of the sable, the V and dot
of the rabbit, the round pads of the lucivee, and
many others. The snow reveals, as nothing else
does, the presence in the forest of the many shy
woodland creatures which lead their lives
abroad only after nightfall.
"Once we saw :i "coon out early after its win
ter nap, ami, following, I shot it in ■ hollow
tree. Another time we fame upon a deer, and
the frightened beast left its "yard," a taagsl of
beaten paths or deep furrows. The poor ani
mal made but slow headway through the pow
dery snow. After going thirty or forty rods it
sank exhausted in a deep drift, and '.ay there in
helpless panic as bjc walked .lose by. Wry
different were the aftions of the only caribou
we saw— a fim- beast, that had shfd its antlers.
I merely caught ■ tilimpse of it as it leaped over
a breastwork of down Umbers, ami we nmi
saw it again. Alternately trotting and miking
a succession of lung jumps, it ■peeaYlj left us
far behind; with its great splay hoof* it could
snowshoe better than we could. It si among
deer the true denizen of the regions of heavy
snowfall; far more so than the moose. Only
under exceptional conditions of crust formalin
is it in any danger from a man on snowshoes."
In another chapter of "The Wilderness Hunt
er" President Roosevelt tells how he and ether
hunters "crust" for moose si the very Rocky
Mountain country which he is about to visit:
■• 'Crusting,* or following game on snowshoea,
is, as the name implies, almost always prac
tised after the middle of February, when the
thaw begins and the snow crusts on tip. The
conditions for success in era* ■- moose and
deer are very different. A crust through which
a moose would break at every stride may tarry
a running deer without mishap, while th- former
animal would trot at ease through drifts in
which the latter would be caught as if in a
quicksand.
"If the snow is less deep or the
heavy, the moose may travt-1 for s
before it is overtaken, and this •
the crust be strong enough to bear .4 r:ia\
YELLOWSTONE IWKK BaJDMCXK
Whore President Roosevelt will b« entertained.
ing snowshoes without breaking Tr.e chase
then involves the most exhausting f^tisu-'.
Moreover, it can be carried on only by those » h'>
are very skilful in the use of snows'; These
srowshoes are of two kinds. In the Northeast
and in the most tangled forests of the North
west, the woven snowshoes are used: on the
bare mountain sides and in the open forests oC
the Korkies the long narrow wooden ski?, or
Norwegian snow skates, are preferred, as u;> ■•'■'>■
them men can travel much faster, though they
are less handy in thick timber. Having donm J
his snow shot's and struck the trail of a moosf,
the hunter may have to follow it three days if
the snow is of only ordinary depth, with a mod
erate crust. He shuttles across the snow with
out halt while daylight lasts, and lies
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 4 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn95066012/1911-05-11/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Tie Yellowstone
National
Park in
An Aspect of Nature's Wonderland
That Few Ever See
4
HE polar regions are hardly
less accessible than the Yel
lowtone National park
the greatest playground ol
the American people U in
winter. This Is scarcely
conceivable, for In summer
40,000 visitors now find It
one of the easiest placea to
Teach and to travel through.
Lieut. Frederick Schwatka made an
attempt to explore the park in Jan
uary nearly 25 years ago. He had re
turned not long before from an expe
dition in search of Sir John Frank
lin's party that had perished in the
arctic regions. Before that he had
been on a 3,000-mlle sledge journey In
the frozen north and had suffered ter
rible hardships. On his trip into the
Yellowstone Park Lieutenant Schwat
ka was accompanied by a large, well
organized party. They "traveled" on
Norwegian jkls and Canadian web
' enowBhoes; but the" Snow"" as so light
that it would not support them, and
their toboggans were exceedingly dif
ficult to draw. It took them three
days to cover 20 miles. Lieutenant
Schwatka, inured as he was to such
hardships, fell ill and was unable to
proceed. He and all the rest of the
party but four of the sturdiest men
turned back. The photographer. F.
J. Haynes; Edward Wilson, a govern
ment scout, and two others kept on.
.It took them 29 days to make the cir
cuit of the park, 200 miles. The ther
mometer ranged between 40 and 50
degrees below zero most of the time,
and the adventure nearly cost them
their lives.
Winter Population of the Playground.
The total winter population of the
park is usually between four and five
hundred people. These Include three
troops of cavalry. The cavalry can
use their horses only during the sum
mer months. During the winter they
are stabled at Fort Yellowstone. The
stage horses are driven down to the
lowlands, miles away, when the tour
ist season is over, and graze In the
sheltered valleys there until the
nows melt
In the great hotels that are
thronged during the tourist season
live only the caretakers, generally
two in each place. a man and his
wife. The first blizzard Isolates from
the world outside everybody in this
great national domain that has an
area of 3,312 square miles. No valley
within its limit has an elevation of
less than 6.000 feet, while many of
the mountain peaks within and near'
the park rise from 10,000 to 14,000
feet above sea level. Yellowstone lake
IB by 20 miles in slzo, Is the largest
body of water In America at that alti
tude, 7,741 feet above the sea. On
the summit of the range, a few miles
south of Yellowstone lake, g Two
Ocean pond, a small lake with two
outlets, on Into the Atlantic through
the Yellowstone and Missouri rivers
the other Into the Pacific through the
Snake river, a branch of the Colum
bia, The Grand canyon of the Yel
lowstone, ten miles long, has an aver
ago depth of 1,200 feet, and is the
most brilliantly colored landscape In
existence. But In winter everything
Is blanketed with Bnow eight to ten
feet deep. All is Ice-bound except the
more than half a hundred great gey
sers that throw their columns of boil
ing water hundreds of feet In the air,
almost as little seen by humankind as'
when they began their epoutlngs ages
ago.
From December to March the en
forced dwellers In the park are near
ly as much cut off from the world as
Jw. ll 1
L-J
Winter
3
though they were penned In by the
polar ice. Of course the telephone
and the telegraph bring them scraps
of news from the outer world, but the
only way of getting about is on
snowshoes or skis. Even then the
distances between the places where
the people live are so great and the
ways so dangerous that few venture
forth. Only the government scouts,
whose duty It is to look after the
wild life In the park aftd see that It
is not molested by poachers, get out
at all. The rest of the people there
are like the bearsthey hibernate
until spring. An ample supply of fuel
and provisions is laid in before the
first snowstorms begin to sweep over
the Continental divide, and there is
little to do until the sun swings
northward and the snows melt.
Building a Hotel Amid Arctic Tem-
r.-'i
-r peraturj,
Despite the arctic rigors of this re
gion, however, 2T0 men have boen
fighting the cold there thU winter
completing tho fifth of the big hotels
that are. the halting places of tour
ists In this summer playground that
belonxa to the iople of the United
States. The lirst order prepared on
the kitchen ranges of this new hos
telry which stands on the brink of
the great precipice down which roars
emTlessly the mlghty cataract of the
Yellowstone, was for nails. Nails big
and little, brads and spikes, ten-pen
nies and shingles, had to be heated
on the cookstoves before the carpen
ters could handle them. The reason
for this baste was that the new hotel
had to be finished In time for the
summer season, when the park is In
its brief period of verdant glory.
More people will go to the Yellow
stone National Park this year than
ever before. In 182, when the fed
eral government dedicated It "as a
public park or pleasure ground for
the benefit and enjoyment of the peo
ple," probably not more than a thou
sand persons a year were visiting It
In the next twenty-three years the
number of visitors climbed slowly to
about 6,000 annually. In 1895, the au
thorities began counting the persons
who entered the park, and complete
records have been kept ever since.
There were 5,438 visitors in 1895.
Ten years later the number had risen
to 26,188. In 1904, it dropped to
17,172. The next year it fell off near
ly a thousand. In 1908 the total was
18,748. Then came the most remark
able increase in visitors that the park
has ever known. In 1909 there were
nearly twic as many (32,545) as the
y'ear before This was principally
due to the opening of a new railroad
gateway to the park at Yellowstone,
Mont. which made it much easier of
access.
A Bit of E. H. Harrlman's Wizardry.
This came about through a visit
that the late E. H- Harrlman made to
the park in the summer of 1904. He
was so Impressed by the wonders of
the park that be immediately ordered
the location and construction of a
branch from the Oregon Short Line,
a part of the Union Pacific system, to
the western border of the park. This
road, from Idaho Falls to Yellow
stone, Montana, 20 miles from the
lower 0yser basin, was finished No
vember 12, 1907, and was opned for
traffic the following June. It Is 107
miles long and cost nearly $2,000,000.
Its construction called Into play the
greatest energy and skill In the sci
ence of railroad building.
Owing to the deep snows and severe
winters work could be carried on dur
ing only about four months of the
''4-. ; ;
year, nut In that brief season, a vast
"iny of men and machines tollou
night and day." The giant mountain
barriers with tl.elr dr-p valleys in be
tween had to be conquered. That part
of the earth whero the rails ran had
to be remodeled so as to secure the
safest and easiest grades. Probably
no railway, where so many obstacles
had to be overcome, ever was built
in so short a time. Hut the largely In
creased number of visitors to the
park has proved that the new line is
fully appreciated. Of the more than
40,000 who entered the park last
yeur nearly half went by this new
western gateway that Mr. Harrlman
created.
The government scouts who are
guardians of the wild creatures are
about the only ones who ever see
much of the winter beauties of the
park. Those who have been there
any length of time have learned much
that Is new about the habits of the
animals that abound there, although
they are chiefly concerned In keeping
poachers out of the park. There are
fewer of these now than there used
to be, because heavier penalties have
been laid by the government on those
who are caught.
The few that do venture in the park
mostly come In winter. Then there is
less chance of being detected, but
more risk of losing their lives In the
cold and snow. One thing more than
all others tempts them the buffalo.
Unscrupulous taxidermists will pay
the weight In silver for a buffalo head
nowadays, for these heads are prac
tically unattainable by legitimate
means. The rest of the wild creatures
that make their homes in the park are
seldom molested.
P.oachlng in the Deep Snow.
It has been 17 years since one of
these poachers after buffalo has been
caught, but he did so much damage
before he was arrested that it has
taken a long time to make up for it.
Early in March, 1894, a party was
organized at Fort Yellowstone for
the purpose of visiting the winter
ranges of the game to ascertain the
exact number of buffalo that still ex
isted and to photograph them. The
Oi.P 'ifttiit. UKZa; HA14'
If .V.
.y Kj-v
party traveled on Norwegian snow
shoes, with packs of sleeping bags,
provisions and camera, direc'ly to
Hayden valley via Norris and the
Grand canyon. They found 81 buf
falo in the valley, together with nu
merous small groups of elk aggregat
ing more than 300.
In a secluded spot toward the end of
the second day's march they discov
ered the cache of a poacher. They
were much surprised at this, as they
had had no idea that there was any
one in the park killing game. Ths
cache consisted of a canvas tepee,
sleeping bag, provisions and tobog
gan, and they found six buffalo heads
suspended in a tree nearby. A trace
of fire in thei tepee led the scouts to
believe that the poacher was not far
away. To capture him was the next
move. It had been snowing constant
ly all the morning, and all the snow
shoe tracks leading from camp were
entirely obliterated. The scouts sep
arated and went in different direc
tions. When five miles from camp one of
tbera heard a half dozen rifle shots in
rapid succession. Hastening through
the timber in that direction, he came
upon an opening In the forest and saw
the poacher. He had driven six of the
buffalo Into the deep snow and had
slaughtered the entire band. Ths scout
was alone and armed only with a re
volver. Poachers of this kind are des
perate men. They know that the arm
of the federal government Is long and
Its grip sura ones it seizes them.
Therefore tbey fight to the last No
desperado Is more reckless of his life.
The scout knew this, but did not hes
itate for a moment It was still snow
ing hard, and neither the poacher nor
his dog noticed the scout's approach.
The scout was within 20 feet of the
poacher and had him covered with blB
revolver before he told him to throw
up his hands. A moment more, and
w; . ' tvv ' k )
he was disarmed. Theri he was hand
cuffed and takeu to the guardhouse
at Fort Yellowstone. He had killed
about onc-elhth of all (tie buffalo In
the park.
Elks and Dears Very Comfortable In
the "Big Cold."
There are about 250 buffalo in tho
park now. To protect them more ef
fectually against poachers about 20U
are kept In an liuiosure and have be
come partly domesticated. The re
mainder run wild in the country to
th; cast of the Yellowstone lake.
Fully 5,(100 elk winter In the foot
hills of Mount Washburn, on Speci
men ridge, along the east folk of the
Yellowstone and along the main
stnam of that river dear to the base
. , , ?- . , . I n in 1
the k vo n "vnrrU"--rlace8 50U 10 i
f t t ,-. Tv..: Ikn U- ntCr '
1,000 feet in diameter, where they
keep the Bnow trodden down. The
bull elks patrol these "yards" at night
so as to keep away the mountain
lloriB and other animals that prey
upon them.
The elks shed their horns about the
flrBt of March, and until they grow out
again lead a quiet life so that their
sprouting horns will not be Injured.
At the time when they shed their"
horns they are still herded together,
and now and then a Bcout will run
across some secluded spot in the pri
meval wilderness where the ground is
covered with two or three score of
these great antlers, some of them six
or seven feet long. They are allowed
to remain where they are, for it is not
permitted to take them from the park
or even to use them for decorative
purposes there. Hut before the end
of the next winter they disappear. The
field mice and other small rodents eat
them.
The bears that are seen around the
hotels In the summer time, stealing
garbage or fighting the searchlight
when it is turned on them at night, go
into winter quarters in November or
December snd sleep until spring.
There are hundreds, of them, black,
brown and grizzly. They go into
caves or hollow logs or under the
roots of trees that the snow will
v V 1 "i J
eovt?-. There are many natural cavei
in the park. Sometimes four or five
bears will snuggle up to each other ir
the same cave and sleep the winter
away. It Is In winter, too, that the
cubs are born. When the baby bear
comes into the world he Is not much
bigger than a rat, but be grows and
grows In his cave, kept warm by his
mother until spring. When he emerges
into the light he is a full grown cub,
quite able to take care of himself and
fight anything of his size.
A Paradise for Wild Things.
Millions of trout come up into the
smaller streams to spawn In the
spring. Hears live mostly on berries
and fish, when they can get them.
Since there are no berries in the
spring the bears break their fast on
fish. They wade into the creeks and
scoop them out with their paws. When
the little bears get tired of catching
fish In the shallow pools they go hunt
ing for moles and work as industrious
ly as puppy dogs digging them out of
tho earth. Springtime, when the
bears are lean and hungry, is their
busiest time
Three-fourths of the park Is a dense
forest, a primeval wilderness. Away
from the few hotels, the roads and
the trails the park today is what It
was before even a Pharaoh reigned In
Egypt It is such a paradise for the
wild things' that roam at will there
that they have lees to fear, even from
each other and from the elements,
than anywhere else in the wilderness.
When the fury of the winter storms
drives the tlk, deer, mountain sheep
and antelope Into the sheltered val
leys and canyons they have nothing
to be afraid of except the pelting,
driven steel-dust of ths mountain bliz
zards. Nature is kind even to the
birds. On the great terraces where
the stupendous aprlngs of hot water
V. 'AW
T.tti-,4
4 ,
flow Incessantly gather great flocks
of wild ducks and other fowl.
In this region, nearly 8,000 feet
above the Bea, where tho mercury
sinks away below zero from Hecem
ber to March, there is far more won
der and mystery in midwinter than
the summer tourist ever nets a hint
of. Civilization is miles away across j
a wilderness of shining, snowclad
mountains. The gale-driven snow
dances over this waste and is piled
into fantastic drifts. Sometimes It is
swept with a roar through the miAin
tain gorges faster than the swiftest
railway train ever traveled. It covers
to the eaves some of the big hotels.
In summer times these places are buz
zing with life, but In winter they are
pictures of desolation, almost Indlstln-
- -
8('UP tenemh the enshrouding snow
, . . . . .,
If the caretakers wish to get out they
have to obtain exit from a window on
one of the upper floors. Tall trees
burled In the snow appear like bushes.
The general aspect of the country is
entirely changed.
Masses of Purest White In Place of
Brilliant Hued Rocks.
The Incomparable wonder of the
Grand canyon of the Yellowstone, that
huge gash in Uie earth whose walls
glow with every tint of Jewels and
flowers, la a mass of purest white save
where here and there the winds have
swept away the snow and left the bill-llant-hued
rocks exposed. Their reds
and yellows and purples and crtmsons
glow the brighter in contrast with the
surrounding whiteness. The black fo
liage of the pines stands out sharply.
Where the water slides over the preci
pice and forms the Great Falls of the
; Yellowstone, it roars down as white as
carded wool. Down at the bottom of
the gorge, where the waters are swift
and deep, they are black. There are
; immense Icicles 200 feet long. An ice
i bridge a hundred feet high Is formed
at the base of the falls.
The great geysers play endlessly,
each at Its appointed period, although
no one Is there to see them. Every sev
enty minutes Old Faithful sends lt9
columns of water and steam 300, 500,
sometimes 1,000 feet Into the air and
holds It there for three minutes. Some
times the winds unfold from Its top
an iridescent banner of spray; at oth-
J er times the fountain form Is a perfect
con". In winter Its boiling hot water
gives off a vast cloud of drifting
steam. At nightfall of a January
j evening, this Immutable water clock
of the Yellowstone becomes a specter
of ghostly white, a sight so strange
and startling that even those who
neighbor with it never lose their awe
of its maiestv. All about the tevsers
j the foliage of the trees la heavily
j laden with ice, giving the trees a thou -
i sand fantastic shapes. A cloud of va-
Dor. line me steam from some exeat
manufacturing citj, hangs and drifts
over the geyser basins the workshop
of nature.
The "Sisterhood" of the Geysers.
There are more than fifty In this
giant sisterhood of geysers. Not even
in Iceland or New Zealand, or any-1
where else where the earth Is still be- '
ing made is there such a convent of
their order as in the Yellowstone. No
one has ever been able to describe
them adequately in words any more
than it has been possible to tell on tho
printed page the extent of the won-
ders in this "workshop of the Al-
mighty." It is a place where almost
every form of creative eccentricity In
nature is found. I
liut the geysers play unseen, and
the agents that are molding the earth i He told of too many wonders. St.
keep at their tasks in solitude all win- l.ouisans marveled, then laughed,
ter long. The great streams and wa- then for many a long year spoke of
terfalls never rest in their toil of tear- "Colter's Hell." They thought he had
ing down the heights and building up imagined It all.
the valleys. Only during three months But Colter, trapper, pioneer and
of the year Is It possible for many peo- ' discoverer, proved exactly right. It
pie to see this Titanic work of Nature was not unlil thirty-four years later
in progress. If those w'ho travel for that he w-as found to have told the.
pleasure every summer knew how cu- truth. Uridger, the noted guide, con
rlous and beautiful a place the park firmed his romantic story.
mm mm mimM &
.VW.
wwm's wvrr at
,,01 ,?
s It
i
- V
:m r ... .
4 f ni ' i
u r
is, there would be as great an influx of
visitors between the 15th of June,
when the season beginH, and the 15tl
of September, when It end.s, us now
nail away to Europe for rest and play.
To get to the new gateway to this
wonderland by the most direct route
the traveler branches off from the
"'-ln Uno of the Union Pacific at Og-
den, Utah. A night's ride In a Pull
man lands him at Yellowstone station,
the western entrance of tho park,
ready for the 158 mile tour in the
Monlda and Yellowstone stages that
are awaiting him. The trip through
the park may be made In five days,
or it may be cut down to two by vis
iting the region of tho geysers alone.
Many, Many Wonderful Things.
There are many wonderful things
on the road before one gets to the
Yellowstone park, however. Going
west from Ogden on the Union Pa
cific is one of the most stupendous
pieces of railway engineering In 'the
world, the great Salt Lal;o cut-off that
was constructed at a cost of $6,000.
000 to save forty-three miles of the
distance between Ogden and 8an
Francisco. It crosses the Great Salt
lake at its deepest portion and is
102 miles long. Soms of the best
engineers in the world pronounced
this cut-off Impossible, but it was
built and is one of the unique fea
tures of American railroading.
Another thing that attracts trav
elers is Salt Lake City itself, which
has been constantly in the public eye
ever since it was a little huddle of
wagons in the wilderness more than
three generations ago. In many ways
it Is one of the most remarkable
cities in the world, and as the seat
l of power of the religious empire of
the Mormons It Is unique. The Taber
nacle, with Its great organ, the big
gest in the world, and the other nota
ble buildings have been described
over and over again, but no words or
photographs can picture them ade
quately any more than they can a
bath in the lake Itself In water In
which one cannot sink.
To get to the Yellowstone National
park or to Salt Lake City Is now one
of the easiest things imaginable. The
directions are simple: You go to Cg
den by the Union Pacific, the new
and direct route, turn to tho north
for the park and to the south for the
"City of the Saints."
The "First Man on the Ground."
It is just a hundred and four years
since the Yellowstone territory was
discovered. A trapper and hunter
found it. He was one John Colter, a
private of the famous Lewis and Clark
' expedition. When, in 1806, this dis-
' tlnguiehed band of pioneers retraced
1 tnir K,ePs and 6taftel back to St.
j Ixula over thf'lr route that eventually
"v f'1"1 ......
broke aw-ay. All by himself, he set
out for tho headwaters of the Mis
souri. He w-as practically forgotten
when, four years later, he came into
St. Louis, tattered, torn, Indian-like
in bis ways, but bubbling over with.
i enthusiasm.
He had seen the most wonderful
place in the world, ho said, where
steam came out of the earth and
scalding water leaped miles high,
whero there were diabolical furnaces
under ground. It would have been
the "abode of the damned," he said,
but for the fact that there was no-
sign, for hundreds of miles, of human
beings. Surrounded by tho curious,
John Colter talked for days of the
wonders he had seen. And he met
with the fate of many; no one be
lieved him.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 5 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83030272/1915-10-31/ed-1/seq-57/</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>Thomas Moran, Dean of American Painters, Now Seventy-Eight</text>
      </result>
      <!-- 6 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85058396/1918-12-07/ed-1/seq-12/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Yellowstone Park Is a Veritable Garden of Edenfor
Our Four-Footed Friends of the ForeSt Thou
sands of Them Find Safety Here.
Copyright. 101S, 'l'be Ictcrnatlocal Syndicate.
IHE FAME of Yellowstone Park
m has been so Indelibly associated
wllh Its wonderful geysers that
few persons know that It Is the
only spot in tho United States where
tho public can see in largo numbers
tho animals of the forests and wilds In
their natural state. In reality It Is
tho most successful wild animal pre
serve In the world.
Only those who personally know
tho West appreciate tho changes that
havo taken place. In Its animal life In
the past forty years. Thirty years
ago elk and antelope existed In la'rgo
numbers in tho Rockies from Mexico
to Canada, but these .animals were
killed with no thought that they might
ultimately bo extinguished. It was
fortunate that when tho Yollowstono
National Park was established, In
1S72, It occurred to somo public mind.
2d Individuals that Its 54 by C3 square?
miles would mako a wonderful game
preserve. As a result there are enough
animals now In this park, to bo of
rreat Interest and In ycara to come It
may form an epltomo of conditions In
tho wilderness that once existed In
many places In tho West.
Thousands Or Animals
There aro six hundred antelope, a
thousand- or more of deer, more than
five hundred moose, four hundred buf
faloes, two hundred mountain sheep,
any number of black and grizzly bears,
and more than thirty thousand elk.
that mako Yellowstone Park their
homo under Government protection.
Those animal herds uro now being
used ns nucleus herds for other parks
national. State and city and for
zoological gardens, when Government
permits. In recent years many of the
animals particularly the elk. bears and
bison have been quietly taken captive
and shipped away to various parts of
the country.
In early days buffaloes existed in
large numbers In tho AY est and ranged
from the Middle West to the Rockies.
Now the only place whero thoy arc
found In their original habitat Is the
Yellowstone Park. The pronged horn
antelope apd a large variety of moose
found near Yellowstone Lako are oth
er Interesting park animals.
Animals Fed In Winter
Though most persons see the ani
mals of the Ycll6wstone In summer
thero arc certain enthusiastic nulmal
lovers who go to this remarkable Park
In winter that they may sec them as
they como to Gardiner, the entrance
to tho Park to get tho alfalfa hay
which the Government harvests each
yoar for winter food for tho Park
animals. Though In summer all kinds
of animals roam In the higher parts
, of tho Park, tho winters are so scvero
that they arc glad to como down to
get food. So nt Gardiner, one can seo
tho graceful deer, hundreds of striped
antelopes, dozens of big horn sheep
and thousands of elks who ramblo
about, feed, and do not seem timid at
all. Early in the morning tho big
hay wagon starts out from Mammoth
Hot Springs, near Fort Yellowstone,
and carries alfalfa to Gardiner, and
as soon as It approaches tho elk and
antelope begin to appear. Sometimes
they como In stately tile, with every
appearance of a stylish dinner party,
and at other times they mess together
in groups of hundreds. Or thoy stand
In line ar.d wait patiently until the
wagon starts on its rounds of scatter
ing feed They never puch each other,
never quarrel, and pay no attention lo
sightseers or photographers, though
when thoy finish eating they stand and
look at tho onlookers reflectively' and
perhaps tho deer kick up their -heola
and run In sheer playfulness. As tho
Park lsrsurrounded.by four national
forests the question of whether part
of their area could bo used for graz
ing has been discussed, but the diffi
culty of adequate protection has been
thq main trouble.
Bears Arc Very Tamo
In summer tho wild aplmals vlo In
Interest with the geysers and most
tourists revurn, with Interesting benr
stories. At meal tlmo bears venturo
near tho hotels to get the garbage and
they aro sometimes soen in other
places. Back In the woods, dwell Mr.
and Mrs. Bruin, and their progeny,
but they havo learned whero garbage
titbits can bo found and on their dally
excursions to get this food thoy arc
a source of enjoyment to lookers-on.
Seats aro oroctcd a short dlstanco
from tho hotels at tho edgo of the
woctl3, and here ono may sit and
watch Bruin cat his supper. As he
comes down from his forest home, ac
companied by various members of his
family, Mr, Bear, whether ho bo cln- j
napion, black or silver tipped pays
no attention to his audience- He is
out for a good meal and ho gets it
undisturbed by such harrowing prob
lems as conservation, Hooverlzatlon
and the like. A soldier stands guard
for fear of somo accident for though
It is said the henry of Yellowstone
Park arc harmlces and a few have
learned to cat out of some Intrepid
persons hands, they nre" wild bears
still. Tourists always enjoy taking
their pictures and around Old Faith
ful, and tho Canyon they seem quite
domesticated. It took years for these
bears to learn that the people In the
Park were their friends, but they bear
evidonco of good treatment in their
sleek coats and fat bodies.
Every year tho beautiful deer are
soen along the roadways and near tho
hotels. During tho fall, winter and
I spring they arc a familiar fcaturo or.
tho parade ground at Fort Yellow
stone and they seem loss timid than
the elk, which aro apt to seclude them
selves In the valleys and timber. But
a short ride from tho hotels will
usually bring a herd in view especial
ly in the vicinity of Shoshomc Lake
and Haydcn Valley. By some marvel
the animals Deem to adapt themselves
to tho automobiles that now take the
place of tho Park coaches. As one
skims along In theso cars thero are
certain retired portions of tho Pak
where one can seo the beavers at work.
They seem to be rapidly multiplying
though many have been shipped to
city parks or approved preserves. At
Yancey's thero aro many colonics of
these beavers Inthe brooks and they
can be seen cutting down trees, swim
ming, laying in their winter food and
doing all sorts of chores as they frisk
about their dams, .houses and slides.
Fishing Paradise
Of course, the fisherman gets his fill
In this Park, whore tho waters have
been "planted" annually over since
1S91. It Is great fun to go fishing
In tho lako or streams and catch the
Loch Levin, rainbow or brook trout.
There are few restrictions and if one JS
stream shows depletion thore la al- 1 51
ways another to turn to. Tho guards 1 &
enjov winter fishing for come of the A
streams near iho entrance are too f
rapid to freeze over completely Three
watersheds find their beginnings w ith- 51
in tho borders of this Park, and al to
.rout streams are of a high degree of M . ftb
excellence. Hawks, eagles, swans. g
pelicans, crows, blackbirds and robins
love this tract in summer am : for- 1
tunately reptiles arc so rare s tJ a t U
summer visitor can experience lltue 4 ma
Sang in Plucking the many gorgeou 1
wild flowers that make tbe roadside 1
'iris worth a trip -re- e Sf. g
tinent to see the animals In this Parfc f N
nnd one can always be sure of a feV
trevser thrown In for good measure &
fvnd ye.. h.s wonderful spot mor. i
wonderful than similar areas In Nej jg
Zealand and Iceland. lay hidden for j
long rears, while a tide of trapper J
explorers and hunters surged by and
beyond it. John Colter of Iho Lej i jg
and Clark Expedition was t he .nr- , g
white man to record a visit This wa
in 1S0.1-6 and along In 1840 Jai ;
' Bridges saw somo of the Geysers. . Wi . .
It remained for the Washbrun-Doane ,
Expedition In 1S70 to give the nrs
authentic account of this wondcrfu" jfl
place. It took many years for people JT
to bellevo that such wonders exlstea
on this continent though a member oi .4,
tho American Fur Company trleo -i
give an idea of the marvel In a stn
paper published in Buffalo In 184" ijj t
Though there are over thirty we t u
known geysers In the Park the anlmfl. gjj
appear totally unaware of their exW Kgere,
enco unless it be that they are Pfu" , hg.M
enough not to get close to the hot
waters. Hero, In this Tellowston
Park, which Is located at the head
ters of the Missouri and Ycllowston- ,;S
rivers, wo have not alone some of tn ilTS
most marvelous of known geysers, do h-. -tho
largest game preserve. It vJ( (
valuable to all of the American pe ,:V
pic. for It is tho home of anl?a;; jjiTOfc
which otherwise would become 1-Jtyk ,
and be known to future generation
only by name and picture. 
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 7 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn88056159/1919-06-25/ed-1/seq-6/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>he oldest and blg
• gest of our national
parks, the first national
park to he established In
the world, the largest and
finest geyser basin on
earth and the most famous of big
game preserves, will probably receive
b largo addition of territory to the
A°uth from the Sixty-sixth congress.
A bill for this addition was Introduced
In the lust congress, was passed by
the house and was shelved In the sen
Bte tn the confusion of the lust days of
the Inst session.
Yellowstone has n most romantic his
tory. It was discovered In 1807 by
lohn Colter. We bought the Louisi
ana territory—the land between the
Mississippi and the Rockies—of Nu
poleon In 1802, without knowing any
thing about this garden spot of the
world. The Lewis and Clark expedi
tion of 1804-8, whlèh made the round
trip from St. Louis to the tuouth of the
Columbia river to find out what we
bad bought, passed within n few miles
of the north end of the park without
•vcn suspecting Its existence. Colter
was one of the party and secured his
discharge before reaching St. Louis to
turn back and trap beaver. Colter re
turned to St. Louis in 1810. The pub
lic laughed nt his story and derisively
dubbed this geyser land "Colter's
Hell." Only one man believed him—
his old commander, Capt. William
Clark, who put .Ills 1807 route on the
•fflclat mnp, of the expedition.
In the '20s James Bridger, the fa
mous plainsman, rediscovered "Col
ter's Hell" and told of Its wonders.
But Bridger was a genius in telling
"tall yarns"—his obsidian cliff, and
hot spring stories ure classics In the
West to this day. "Just another of
Jim Brldger's yarns" was the popular
verdict. Prospectors who flocked to
the region during various gold excite
ments dlscnvcrjgd the Yellowstone the
third time. But It was not until 1870
that the country believed In "Colter's j
Hell." Then there was popular enthu- !
slasm and In 1872 the Yellowstone was
aet a-dde by act of congress ns a na- !
tlonnl park—a nubile playground for
the people of the United Stutes for
ever.
Millions In Improvements.
Paring the first 14 years of its ex
totenee as a national park Yellowstone
was administered by civilian superin- !
tendent* good, bad and Indifferent, j
Congress sometimes appropriated
funds for the park and often did not.
By 1880 conditions were so bad In the
park and poachers were killing off the
big game so fast that the management
was turned over to the army. The |
army record was excellent. With the
creation of the national park service,
two yenrs ago, exclusive control Is now
In this new bureau of the Interior de
partment, which Is charged with ad
ministration of all nationnl parks.
On the whole, congress has been fair
ly liberal In appropriations. These to
tal $3,980,523.84 to July 1. 1910. There
are 278 miles of main and 25 miles of
secondary road and nearly 400 miles
of fairly well-marked trails. Fifteen
ranger stations nre maintained; these
are connected with headquarters near
the north entrance by 270 miles of tel
ephone.ITEMS OF INTERE9T
The best meat to eat In cold weuth
er is mutton, owing to Its high heating
value.
An official estimate of the forest
lands destroyed by the enemy In
France places ihe total at 1,200.000
acres.
During the war nearly 14,000,000
publications, representing a monetary
value of something like $1,500,000,
were sent by the British public to
the troops.
ÔTEPJYE/Y TSfAr/tfK t
d/aeceoj? /y.y?s
The park lies principally In the
northwest corner of Wyoming, hut laps
over a little Into Idaho and Montana.
Us area is about 3,343 squares miles
or 2,142,720 acres. Its altitude Is 0,
000 to 11,000 feet. There nre four
entrances : Gardiner on the north ;
Cody on the east ; Moran on the south,
and Yellowstone on the west. All ex
cept Moran are railroad points. In
1018 the travel by entrance wns:
North, 7,504 ; east, 4,401 ; south. 542 ;
west, 8,702.
Tourist travel goes over n belt road
which forms two large loops, resembles
a- figure 8 and covers the scenic fea
tures of the north two-thirds of the
park. Three-flftlis of the tourist travel
is by private automobile and the pro
portion Is growing larger each yenr.
Yellowstone Lacke Scenery.
This, then Is the lay of the land.
Yellowstone Is'by far the biggest of
the 18 national parks and Is the best
developed. Its geysers nre us unique
ns the big trees of Sequoia, the lake
of Crater Lnke and the canon of Grand
Canon. Why. then should It he en
larged by the addition of territory to
the south approximately equal to one
third of Its present area?
The comprehensive answer Is: The
Yellowstone Is too small. The natural
question, then, Is, Why Is the Yellow
stone too small ? There are several an
swers, Including these three:
Becnuse It lacks scenery.
Because the region to the south Is a
natural part of the park.
Because the elk to the south are tn
danger of extinction.
Yellowstone does lack scenery of the
majestic kind. Its peaks nre not lofty
and rise from a high plateau. Its gey
sers, hot springs, paint pots, etc., are
freak scenery. In short, the Yellow
stone does not hold the tourist. In the
days of the stage coach It took the
tourist about live days to see the Yel
lowstone ; then he was ready to leave.
Now the automobile has cut his stay
in half. And he Is not likely to re
turn. In strong contrast nre such
parks ns Rocky Mountain and Yosemlte.
There the average stay Is at least two
weeks, while many thousands go regu
larly every season, stay a month or
more and look upon the park ns their
summer home.
The offlclui attendance flgures tell
the story: Yellowstone, last four sea
sons, 51,895; 35,849 ; 35,400 ; 21,275;
Rocky Mountain, 31,000 ; 51,000; 117,
188; 101,497. The 1918 decrease In
both parks was due to war-time condi
tions; Increase In railroad fares and
government discouragement of pleas
ure travel. The travel by private au
tomobile held Its own. The hotels in
Yellowstone were not open.
The nationnl park service would
change the Yellowstone conditions and
would begin by enlarging the park.
In addition It has extensive plans for
making the Yellowstone attractive.
These Include golf, tennis, improved
fishing, model automobile camps, new
(
I Lightness nnd durability are claimed
for a new life belt for novice swlm
I mers that consists of a broad strip of
j canvas with sealed inetui floats at the
I Iront and back.
I Featured by a spirit level, n Chicago
Inventor has patented a device for
tailors to enuble them to get the ex
act width of the eollnr nnd slope of
the shoulders of a customer.
It Is estimated that the Maine sar
dine pack for the present season will
be 2.500,000 enses of 100 cans each, a
normal catch.
rFLLOWJTÖ«*//
TO CODY—^
OfOijp
L r s
Y /
\
•x,
\
•//tC«oyiSKfj|V
* MT. u , JöJkt
mor.sOM®'
v f*
— r
crmd i'-.Cj
If if
TETON "• T >
fe
- PEE JE, 7/r BOUrtOEYlJNE
—— /ŸEtY BOMOAYL/ftE
— BEIT ROAD
..... AEk>/?OAP
trails and plenty of mountain climbing.
The territory to be added contains
approximately a thousand square miles
end is known to big game hunters as
the Jackson Hole country. It contains
the sort of scenery that Yellowstone
lacks. The Absaroka Itnnge along the
east boundary contains several lofty
peaks and Younts Peak runs up to 12,
185 feet. The west slope of this range
contains the headwaters of the Yel
lowstone river. The south boundary
runs along Buffalo fork to the Snake
river at Jackson lake. The west line
runs nlong the Teton range. Included
In the addition are Jackson lake.
Grand Teton (13,741) and Mount Mo
ran (12,100). Grand Teton has been
a famous landmark since the early
days of the fur trade and Jackson
Hole was the last refuge of organized
bad men, cattle rustlers and horse
' ' ~ '
thieves. It wns unknown land when
Yellowstone was established In 1872.
The Jnckson Hole elk herd Is an en
tirely different herd from that of Yel
lowstone. It Is supposed to number
about 15,000 head. As nntlonnl parks
upon establishment automatically be
come wild animal life sanctuaries, en
largement of Yellowstone would save
the herd.
The uddition of the Jackson Hole
country will work many changes In
Yellowstone. A planned feature Is an
automobile liighwuy from Moran to the
Cody road, around the east side of
Yellowstone lake, thus making a third
loop. A hotel will be established on
this loop north of Jnckson lnke. The
south entrance will be developed. The
automobile litghwnys to Victor nnd
Lander, both rnllrond points, will he
Improved. Improved hlgliwny connec
tion with the Lincoln Highway will
be made to accommodate private au
tomobile travel. These Improvements
to the south entrance will give It at
lenst Its full share of travel. The
south entrance route Is the shortest
between Rocky Mountain nnd Yellow
stone. Presumably automobile camp
ers will And the addition the most de
sirable part of the park.
The fame of Yellowstone National
park has spread over all the enrth and
its Influence 1ms been world wide. The
world saw In It a new thing In civili
zation—the establishment of a public
playground In perpetuity for the peo
ple of n nation. The world found It
good nnd the example has heen fol
lowed by many nations, with others
now making ready. The United States
has now eighteen nationnl parks, with
five or more In prospect.
by
Plans are being made to establish a
pictorial record of the work women
are doing, and the women In Industry
service of the United States depart
ment of labor is asking the co-opera
tlon of employers of the country In
assembling these pictures.
Thousnuds of huts discarded
English women are exported every
yenr to Brazil, where they are eagerly
bought by the Indians. The feathers
and other ornaments on the lints are
taken by the inen, and the bare straw
shapes given tô their w i.neii folk.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 8 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn84023416/1920-09-02/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>OIXG to "Colter's Hell" this sum-,
nier? If so, be sure to take with
you Uncle Sam's 1020 bulletin, just
off the government press. It tells
you all about "Colter's Hell"
which is to say, the Yellowstone,
oldest and most famous of our 19
national parks.
Why "Colter's Hell"? Well, It's
an interesting story and not every
one knows it. The story of John Colter and "Col
ter's llell" properly begins away back In 180o,
when Thomas Jefferson, our third president,
bought the Louisiana territory from Napoleon
Bonavmrte.
The western boundary of the United States
was then the Mississippi, as fixed by the treaty
with Great Britain after the Involution. Jeffer
son sent James Monroe to France to co-oirerate
with Minister Robert It. Livingston in the pur
chase of the Mississippi's mouth for $2,000,XH).'
Napoleon laughed at them, lie had just made
Spain cede him the Louisiana Territory, Intend
ing to establish there an empire to replace that
lost to the British In Canada. Then Napoleon saw
be must fight the British. He could not fight and
colonize, too. So, to spite the British, he told the
two Americans they could have all the country
between the Mississippi and the Itockies (Texas
not included) for $15,(XK),000. And he made Mon
roe and Livingston agree. Jefferson was scared
stiff at the act of his agents. There was a nation
wide rumpus over the purchase, but congress rati
fied it and the people finally approved it.
Jefferson had not the slightest idea what the
United States had bought and in the spring of 1S04
ho started the Lewis and Clark expedition from St.
Louis to find out Tills famous expedition went to
the mouth of the Columbia river and returned to
St. Louis in lSOG, after having been given, up for
lost. It passed a few miles to the north of the
Yellowstone, without even suspecting its existence.
John Colter was one of the private soldiers of
the exiedltioii. Before it reached St. Louis he got
his discharge and returned with two trappers to
the headwaters of the Missouri for beaver. In the
firing of 1S07 at the mouth of the Platte be met
Manuel Lisa and . again turned back. Lisa built
Fort Lisa at the confluence of tlfe Yellowstone and
the Big Horn. Colter, going alone to summon the
Crows lo (lie fort for trade, passed to the south of
tlie Yellowstone tltrough Jackson's Hole to Tierre's
Hole at the west of the Yellowstone. Returning
thence to Fort Lisa, he passed diagonally through
the Yellowstone, the first white man to see its won
ders. Colter, after adventures and travels that give
him a front rank among explorers of the west, re
turned to St. Louis in 1S10. lie recounted his ad
ventures and lie told of the marvels of the Yellow
stone. St. Louis believed some of his tales of ad
venture, but would have none of the geysers, boil
ing springs and paint-pots of the Yellowstone.
They derisively dubbed it "Colter's Hell," laughed
over it for a time and then forgot it. Gen. Wil
liam Clark, his commander, was the only one to
believe him. On the oflicial map of the Lewis and
Clark expedition Is a dotted line from Fort Lisa
to the Yellowstone and return, with the legend,
"Colter's route in 1807."
The Yellowstone v'as discovered the second
time about 1S27 this time by Jim Bridger, one of
(Jen. William 11. Ashley's lieutenants In the Rocky
Mountain Fur company. Bridger was the discov
erer of Great Salt Lake, a map-maker without an
equal, a mountaineer, plainsman and guide with
no superior. But he had a hobby big yarns. It
is he who made up those classic "whoppers" of
the west the obsidian cliff, boiling spring, echo
and alum creek stories. So, when he told about
the wonders of the Yellowstone, u scoffing frontier
said, with laughter: "Oh, just another of Jim
Bridgor's yarns."
Warren Angus Fenis described the Upper Gey
ser basin of the Yellowstone in 1S-12 and was not
believed. Prospectors in the Montana gold excite
ment of 1802 again described the Yellowstone; they
were set down as liars. Newspapers and maga
zines would not publish the stories; lecturers were
stoned. Iu 1809 the semi-official Montana Wash-burn-Langford
expedition did succeed in getting a
hearing. In 1870 the federal government sent an
official exjied It ion which official ly put Mie Yellow
stone on the map.
Cornelius Hedges, September 18, 1S70, by a
campflre In the Yellowstone, proposed that the
wonderland be niado a national park a pluy-
ground set aside for the people's use forever. The
idea took. Congress established the Yellowstone
National park, March 1, 1872.
The establishment of the Yellowstone as a na
tional park after 05 years of "discoveries" was
the first time such a thing had been done In all
history. It was the first national park in all the
world. The United States set the example which
practically all the civilized world has followed.
Uncle Sam's 1920 Yellowstone Bulletin is a
fascinating booklet of 103 pages of text, maps
and illustrations. It contains everything that the
tourist needs to know, from how to get there to 0
time table of the geysers and from the different
kinds of trout to the automobile regulations. The
following items are taken from the introductory
pages :
The Yellowstone National park was created by
the act of March 1, 1872. It is approximately G2
miles long and 54 miles wide, giving an area of
3.348 square miles, or 2,142,720 acres. It Is under
the control and supervision of the national park
service of the Interior department.
The Yellowstone is probably the best known of
our national parks. Its geysers are celebrated the
world over because, for size, power, and variety
of action, as well as number, the region has no
competitor.
The Yellowstone National park is located in
northwestern Wyoming, encroaching slightly upon
Montana and Idaho. It is our largest national
park. The central portion Is essentially a broad,
elevated, volcanic plateau, between 7,000 and 8,500
feet above st-a level and with an average elevation
of about 8,000 feet. Surrounding ft on the south,
east, north, and northwest are mountain ranges
with culminating peaks and ridges rising from
2,000 to 4,000 feet above the general level of the
inclosed tableland.
The entire region is volcanic. Not only the sur
rounding mountains but the great interior plain
is made of material once ejected, as ash and lava,
from depths far below the surface. Geological
speculation points to a crater which doubtless once
opened just west of Mount Washburn.
There are five active geyser basins, the Norris,
the Lower, the Upper, the Heart lake, and Sho
shone basins, all lying In the wesMind south cen
tral parts of the park. The geysers exhibit a large
variety of character and action. Some, like Old
Faithful, spout at quite regular Intervals, longer
or shorter. Others are irregular. Some burst up
ward with immense power. Others shoot streams
at angles or bubble anil foam In action.
Geysers arc. roughly speaking, water volca
noes. They occur only at places where the Inter
nal heat of the earth approaches close to the sur
face. Their action, for so many years unex
plained, and even now regarded with wonder by
so many. Is simple. Water from the surface trick
ling through crack In the rocks, or water from
subterranean springs collecting in the bottom of
the geyser's crater, down among the strata of in
tense heat, becomes Itself Intensely heated and
gives off steam, which expands and forces upward
the cooler water that lies above It.
At last the water in the bottom reaches so
great an expansion under continued heat that the
less: heated water above can no longer weigh It
down, so it hursts upward with great violence,
rising many feet in the air and continuing to play
until practically all the water In the crater has
been expelled.
Nearly the entire Yellowstone region Is remark
able for its hot water phenomena. The more
prominent geysers are confined to three basins
lying near each other In the middle west side of
the park, but other hot water manifestations oc
cur nt more widely separated points. Marvelous
ly colored hot springs, mud volcanoes, and other
strange phenomena are frequent. At Mammoth,
at Norris, and at Thumb the hot water lias
lrought to the surface quantities of white min
eral deposits which build terraces of beautifully
incrusted basins high up into the air, often en
gulfing trees of considerable size. Over the edges'
of these carved basins pours the hot water. Mi
croscopic plants called algae grow on the edges
and sides of these basins, painting them hues of
red and pink and bluish gray, which glow bril
liantly. At many other points lesser hot spring
occur, introducing strange, almost uncanny, ele
ments into wooded and otherwise quite normal
landscapes.
The Grand Canyon of the Yellowstone affords
a spectacle worthy of a national park were there
no geysers. Standing upon Inspiration Point,
which pushes out almost to the center of tle can
yon, one seems to look almost vertically down
upon the foaming Yellowstone river. To the south
a waterfall twice the height of Niagara rustics
seemingly out of the pine-clad hills and pours
downward to be lost again in green. From that
point two .or three miles to where you stand and
beneath you widens out the most glorious kaleido.
scope of color you will ever see in nature. The
steep slopes, dropping on either side 1,000 feet and
more from the pine-topped levels above, are incon
ceivably carved and fretted by the frost and the
erosion of the ages.
The fossil forests of the YellowstoneNatlon.il
park cover an extensive area in the northern por
tion of the park, being especially abundant along
the west side of Lamar river for about 20 miles
above its junction with the Yellowstone. One
traversing the valley of the Lamar river may see
at many places numerous upright fossil trunks in
the faces of nearly vertical walls. These trunks
are not all at a particular level hut occur at Irreg
ular heights; in fact a section cut down through
these 2,000 feet of beds would disclose a succes
sion of fossil forests. That is to say, after the
first forest grew and was entombed, there was a
time without volcanic outburst a period long
enougli to permit a second forest to grow above
the first. Tliis In turn was covered by volcanic
material and preserved, to.be followed again by a
period of quiet, and these more or less regular al
ternations of volcanlsm and forest growth contin
ued throughout the time the beds were iu process
of formation.
The Yellowstone National park Is . the largest
and most succesNful wild animal refuge In the
world. It Is also, for this reason, the best and
most accessible field for nature study. Its. 3.300
square miles of mountains and valleys remain
nearly as nature made them, for the 2HJ miles of
roads and the four hotels and many camps are as
nothing in this immense wilderness. No tree has
been cut except when absolutely necessary for
road or trail or camp. No herds Invade Its val
leys. Visitors for the most part keep to the beat
en road, and the wild animals have learned in the
years that they mean them no barm. To be sure
they are not always seen by the ioople In the
automobile stages which whirl from point to point
dally during the season; but the quiet watcher on
the trails may see deer and bear and elk and an
telope to his heart's content, and he may even see
mountain sheep, moose, and bison by journeying
on foot or by horseback into their distant retreats.
It is an excellent bird preserve also; 20U spe
cies live natural, undisturbed lives. Eagles aro
found among the crags.
Trout fishing in Yellowstone waters Is unex
celled. All three of the great watersheds abound
in trout, which often attain large size. Yellow
stone lake is. t lie home of large trout, which are
taken freely from boats, and the Yellowstone riv
er and Its tributaries yield excellent catches to the
skillful angler.
The criticism often made by persons who have
visited granite countries that the Yellowstone re
gion lacks the supreme grandeur of some others
of our national parks will cease to have weight
when the magnificent Teton mountains just south
of the soiflhern boundary are added to the park.
These mountains begin at the foot of the Pitch
stone plateau a mile or two below the southern
gateway and extend south and west. They bor
der Jackson lake on its west side, rising rapidly
in a series of remarkably toothed and Jagged peaks
until they reach a sublime climax, 30 miles south
of the park, in the Grand Teton, which rises cathedral-like
to nn altitude of 13,747 feet. ,
These amazing mountains are, from their na
ture, a component part of the Yellowstone Na
tional park, whose gamut of majestic scenery they
complete, and no doubt would have been Included
within its original boundaries had their supremo
magnificence been then appreciated. Already Yel
lowstone visitors have claimed It, and nutomohllo
stages run to Moran and back on regular schedule.
In time, no doubt, part of it will be added forumlly
to the park territory.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 9 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86091197/1922-06-29/ed-1/seq-4/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Jim Bridger, discoverer of Yellowstone Park, whose stories no one
would believe when he first reported his miraculous "find" is shown in the
upper right. Jim died years ago, but the bear here shown lives on, and
will help golden anniversary year tourists in their vindication of the old
trapper's wondrous yarns at the gala fiftieth year. Below is one of the
big park busses, being loaded at Old Faithful camp.
VERSARY OF YEL
LOWSTONE PARK
Jim Bridger's Biggest
Lie Was the
Truth
Tears ago old. Jim Bridger was
one of the earliest travelers of the
Yellowstone.
But when he tried to tell of the
gigantic geysers, rivers that ran
cold on top and hot on the bottom
and
country laughed at him, and he be
came known as the grtatest liar of
his time.
waterfalls, the
monstrous
A rough deal,, indeed.
But 1922 marks the golden anni
versary of the Yellowstone National
Park. And this year every traveler
who goes to the wonderland to help
ceelbrate the gala year, every deluxe
train that runs from Salt Lakt City
to the park entrance at West Yel
lowstone, will be a vindication for
poor old Bridger.
His biggest "lie" was the truth.
• There have been many changes to
the Yellowstone since Bridger's day
as travelers who come this year will
find. Where he went in overland
with pack horses, they roll in over
a steel highway in de luxe trains,
whose service this year will be
doubled. In addition to the famous
"Yellowstone Special" which nightly
flashes over the rails from Salt Lake
to the park entrance, there will be
a daylight train, which will enable
the visitor to see the scenic moun
tain wonders of the Targhee forest,
en route to the park itself.
Arriving at West Yellowstone,
more changes are evident. Where
Bridger went thru the brush, and
used river beds as trails, this sum
mer's traveler will find a matchless
system of highways, with automo
bile transportation awaiting him.
He can select any one of half a
dozen trips thru the wonderland.
Instead of mountain trails there is a
system of matchless highways.
Hotels with every modern comfort
and convenience await him in the
heart of the wilderness. Permanent
camps offer equal comfort and at
traction. But both hotels and
camps have been so skillfully con
structed that their rustic log archi
tecture adds to the natural wild
beauty of the whole.
Thru all this is a wonderful sys
tem of co-operation between gov
ernment, railroads, hotels, camps,
and transportatoin that enables
100,000 people to se the whole park
annually. And yet with all these
changes, so have they been kept to
the spirit of the place, the park is
the same old Yellowstone.
Only one change is the reverse of
what it seems it should be. The
animals, wild in Bridger's day, are
tame now.
hand.
lordly heads to watch the bus cara
vans roll by. Deer pause by the
roadside and eye them speculatively.
Mighty rainbow trout leap from the
river to tempt the anglers.
Clear and deep, the Yellowstone
river flows on, unchanged. The
voice of the falls booms forth in the
key it used when the moon was
young, the geysers spout at the
regular intervals as they did before
Columbus made his historic first im
migration to American shores. Deep
carpets of pine needles, the accumu
lation of centuries invite rest in the
shadows of pines that started grow
ing when the ground first grew cool.
Unusual activity is promised for
the geysers this year. The snow
fall was adbnormally heavy last
winter, and the moisture which will
make the falls and cascades of un
usual beauty will add to the sensa
tional performances of boiling
springs, geysers and mud pots.
Even nature has assisted, this
year, in the vindication of Jim
Bridger's suspected tongue, and the
stage is set for a wonderful opening
of the park's fiftieth anniversary.
Bears eat from your
Grazing elk herds raise
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 10 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn94060041/1937-12-18/ed-1/seq-15/</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>Science in Virginia</text>
      </result>
      <!-- 11 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85053308/1911-06-30/ed-1/seq-2/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NEW YELLOWSTONE GEYSER
Spouter Named the Harvard in Honor
of College Visitors in Park.
A large new geyser erupted in the
Norris Geyser basin in Yellowstone
National park. The new geyser has
been named the Harvard in honor of
the delegation of Harvard alumni,
who arrived in Yellowstone park on
the same day the geyser was discov
ered, from the Twin City. The gey
ser plays to a height of more than
100 feet and is said to be very beauti
ful.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 12 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86075229/1934-08-24/ed-1/seq-8/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Showing Eruptions
Shortly after the long-awaited erup
tions of the Giant and Beehive geysers
recently in Yellowstone national park,
another geyser, the Whistle, returned to
action at 8 a. m. Aug. 4. This was the
first recorded eruption since July 18,
1931.
The Whistle is unique because of the
great noise that accompanies the. rush'
of steam and water. Workmen heard;
the shrill whistling nearly a mile away,'
they reported. So violent was the erup- 1
tion that a crust of vari-colored algae
was blown off the formation.
The two Ruwenzori peaks in Africa,
both over 16,000 feet high, were scaled
in the summer of 1932 by a Belgian
Congo expedition.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 13 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn96076839/1920-08-20/ed-1/seq-3/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>GEYSERS ARE AT
BEST THIS YEAR
Activity of Old Faithful and the
Rest Mew Wonder of Yellow
stone National Park.
Great Depth of Snow Last Winter Be.
, lleved Responsible for Unusual
Brilliance of Natural Phenom
ena Deer Often Seen.
1 Yellowstone National Park, Wyo.
Interesting changes have developed
thl year In the natural - wonders of
Yellowstone National park. Led by
Old Faithful geyser, which has short
ened the Intervals of his perform
ance by almost a quarter of an hour,
and Is now playing every 64 minutes,
the geysers and hot springs are on
their best behavior, promising a sea
son of unsurpassed beauty, as If mind
ful that the number of visitors Is ex
pected to exceed 100,000 for the
first -time In the history of the park.
Unusual depth of snow during the
wlntei, followed by a rainy spring, Is
believed to be responsible for the
brilliance of the natural phenomena.
Abundant moisture has been stored In
the underground passages feeding the
geysers and springs to enable them
to excel their previous exhibitions.
The Grand has become the park's
most powerful geyser. It Is playing
once or twice each day, and for ten to
thirty minutes affords a magnificent
spectacle of a fountain of steaming
water 200 feet In height, which Is suc
ceeded by five to "twelve distinct erup
tions. Giant and Giantess have been
giving great exhibitions.
Constant has discontinued opera
tions, its activity apparently trans
ferred to the Whirligig, directly across
the foot-path.
Terraces Gorgeous In Color.
Mud Boiler has changed its tactics
and is discharging water that is al
most clear. Scores of small geysers
are constantly In action and of course
Old Faithful, which attains a height
of 125 to 170 feet, is observed hour
ly by pei rons from all parts of the
world, as In previous years.
At Mammoth Hot Springs, the head
quarters of the park administration,
the terraces are a marvel of gorgeous
coloring, whore the hot water ripples
over the unique formations. With the
single exception of Minerva Terrace,
which Is less splendid than In past
years, all of the terraces are perfornw
Ing with great volume. Cleopatra ap
parently lr trying to make up for Min
erva's deficiency by starting a new
channel where the cplorlng changes
daily.
Jupiter, for many years the finest
of all the terraces, has lost its leader
ship, being surpassed by the prosaic
ally named Pulpit Terrace, which
is sending more water than ever
from Its sapphire pool over a series
of beautifully curved basins, fretted
and colored like some old Gothic
carving, until more than 200 feet be
low a conduit is reached, which' takes
the warm waters from all the springs
into the open-air bathing pool.
Doer Appear Occasionally.
Hymen Terrace is attracting great
attention because of the abundance
and exquisite shape of the algae, or
microscopic plants, which give the,
lerraces their color. Nowhere else
in the r ark are to be found such grace
ful formations, floating in the water
like ostrich plumes of delicate green.
Angel Terrace has developed a rich
pink coloring, much like a birthday
cake, a resemblance enhanced by the
trees, which the growing terrace
reached out and killed, and which
now stick out through the crust like
white candles. Occasionally a deer
can be seen and photographed, nib
bling 'the salty encrustations from the
trees.
Orange Spring' Terrace, which -has
grown to a great mound 15 feet high,
has a tiny assistant, an "off-spring,"
to quote the pun of a visitor, which
bubblts merrily at the original level
of the parent spring, affording a com
prehensive view of how the terraces
have been built
MIneial springs In the park, includ
ing the apolllnarls and Iron springs,
which are eagerly sought by visitors
desiring to drink the waters, are pro
ducing great quantities.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 14 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86072239/1920-07-30/ed-1/seq-7/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>NATURE WORKS
GREAT CHANGE PARK WONDERS
YELLOWSTONE PARK, Wyo.,
July 30).—Interesting changes have
developed this year in the natural
wonders of Yellowstone national park.
Led by Old Faithful geyser, which has
shortened the interval of its perform
ances by almost a quarter of an hour,
and is now playing every 64 minutes,
the geysers and hot springs are on
their best behavior, promising a sea
son of unsurpassed beauty, as if
mindful that the number of visitors
is expected to exceed 100,0000 for the
first time in the history of the park.
Unusual depth of snow during the
winter, followed by a rainy spring, is
believed responsible for the bril
liance of the natural phenomena.
Abundant moisture has been stored in
the underground passages feeding
■Jbe geysers and springs to enable
them to excel all their previous ex
hibitions.
The Grand has become the park’s
most powerful geyser. It is playing
once or twice each day for 10 to 30
minutes, affording a magnificent spec
«•
tacle of a fountain of steaming water
200 feet in height, which is succeeded
by five to twrelve distinct eruptions.
j£»iant and Giantess have been giv
ing fine exhibitions. Constant has
discontinued operation, its activity
apparently transferred to the Whirl
igig directly across the footpath.
Mud Broiler has changed its tactics
and is discharging water that is al
most clear. Scores of smaller gey
^ sers are constantly in action and of
course Old Faithful, which attains a
height of 125 to 170 feet, is observed
hourly by persons from all parts of
the world as in former years.
At Mammoth Hot Springs, the head
quarters of the park administration,
the terraces are a marvel of gorgeous
coloring where the hot water ripples
over the unique formations. With the
single exception of Minerva Terrace,
which is less splendid than in past
years, all of the terraces are per
forming in great volume. Cleopatra
apparently is trying to make up for
Minerva’s deficiency by starting a
new channel where the coloring
changes daily.
Jupiter, for many years the finest
of all the terraces, has lost his lead
ership, being surpassed by the pro
saically named Pulpit Terrace, which
is^ sending more water than ever from
its sapphire pool over a series of
beautifully curved basins, fretted and
colored like some old gothic carving,
until more than 200 feet below a con
duit is reached which takes the warm
waters from all the springs into the
open air bathing pool.
Hymen Terrace is ^attracting great
attention because of the abundance
and exquisite shape of the algae, or
microscopic plants, wrhich give the
terraces their color. Nowhere else in
the park are to be found such grace
j* n f_j • £1 1* • i.T ...» 4-^%,
mi luimauuiio, uuaung in me natvi
like ostrich plumes of delicate green.
Angel Terrace has developed a rich
pirfk coloring, much like a birthday
^cake, a resemblance enhanced by
the trees which the growing terrace
reached out and killed, and which
now stick out through the crust
like white candles.
Occassionally a deer can be seen
and photographed nibbling the salty
encrustations from the trees.
Orange Spring Terrace, which has
grown to a great mound 15 feet high,
has a tiny assistant, an “offspring”
to quote the pun of a visitor, which
bubbles merrily at the original level
of the parent spring, affording a com
prehensive view of how the terraces
have been built.
Mineral springs in the park, includ
ing the appollinaries and iron springs
and the hot soda springs, are produc
ing in great quantities.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 15 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn82015313/1928-08-08/ed-1/seq-7/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>HUGE GEYSER
DISCOVERED IN
YELLOWSTONE
Largest Known in History
of Park Since 1888 '
Is Found. *
lh/ Science Service
YELLOWSTONE PARK, Wyo.,
Aug. B.—A new geyser of great
magnitude, whose volume of water
discharge is greater than any other
known in Yellowstone National
Park since Excelsior geyser stopped
playing in 1888, has broken out in
the Fairy Creek section of the lower
geyser basin here.
Although the existence of this
geyser has been known for several
days, until today no data has been
given out pending the investigation:
of Ur. Arthur L. Day, director of
the geophysical laboratory of the
Carnegie Institution of Washington,
and Dr. Eugene T. Allen, who has
been filed representative of the
geophysical department of the Car
negie Institution here for the last
two years.
This huge geyser has a crater
of roughly circular form, with
diameters of 100 and 120 feet. It
erupts twice in twenty-four hours,
and each eruption last three hours
or longer. The geyser continues
to spurt at intervals of from
fifteen to twenty seconds during its
period of eruption, bursting forth
from a quiet surface with a loud
explosion and throwing a column
WSjSssz? .willSbl
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 16 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn86075250/1941-04-11/ed-1/seq-1/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>Yellowstone Roads Opening
Park Expecting
Heavy Travel
Yellowstone National Park’s snow
plows are busily engaged in clearing
the roads of snow, making ready for
what is expected to be the largest
travel year in the history of the park,
superintendent Edmund B. Rogers an
nounced. Last year more than a half
million people visited the nation’s
largest ami oldest playground but indi
cations are that an even larger number
will enter at the park’s five gateways
before the official travel year closes
on September 39. Excellent weather
last fall and an unusually mild winter,
with sixty miles of the park’s highway’
along tho north side from Glacier to
Uooke open throughout, the winter, has
resulted in the travel already being
considerably ahead of last year.
The snowplows are opening first the
road from Mammoth to Old Faithful
and West Yellowstone. The highways
cn the east side of the park will be
opened next and April 25 is the ten
tative date set for the opening of the
east entrance road from Cody, Wyom
ing. The south entrance ro -1 from
the Jackson Hole is expected to be
opened by May 1 and the entire grand
loop road should be traversable by
that date. The northeast entrance
from Red Lodge to Cooke should be
open by May 15.
As soon as the park roads are open
to travel, accommodations will be
available for early visitors. Meals and
lodgings will be obtainable at the
general store at Old Faithful by April
1 and when travel is permitted to
Yellow’stone Lake the store at that
location will be ready to accommodate
visitors. Tho general store and gas
oline filling station at Mammoth have
been open throughout the winter and
similar service will be available at
Old Faithful by April 1.
The . fishing season this year opens
on May 30, the same as last year,
and visitors to the park over the
Decoration Day holiday period will be
able to share in the first catches
from the various park waters. Yellow
stone Lake will be open to fishing
starting May 30 but tho Yellowstone
River from a point 150 yards above
Fishing Bridge to the Upper Falls at
Canyon will remain closed until July
1.
        </text>
      </result>
      <!-- 17 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn85042588/1895-05-24/ed-1/seq-8/</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>City and County</text>
      </result>
      <result>
      <!-- 18 -->
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045217/1921-11-26/ed-1/seq-5/</id>
        <rel>0</rel>
        <text>-</text>
      </result>
      <!-- 19 -->
      <result>
        <id>https://chroniclingamerica.loc.gov/lccn/sn83045217/1922-03-12/ed-1/seq-51/</id>
        <rel>1</rel>
        <text>ontana Offers Tourists a Paradise
now Tipped Mountain
n
o o
aune
BY CHESTER C. DAVIS,
State Commissioner of Agriculture.
Delightful Montana , a land of distances and of
alpine heights, a paradise of lake and forest, snow tip
ped mountains and broad vistas of rolling valley and
plain, invites weary city folks and dwellers of the flat places
to come and learn the real meaning of the word "recreation."
It invites them to come when all the east is sweltering and
sleep there is impossible. It promises them refreshing sleep,
glorious scenery, splendid trout fishing, big game hunting in
season and the varied matchless attractions that are contain
ed within Montana's 147.187 square miles of territory.
The national parks—Glacier in the,*,
northwestern and Yellowstone in the
south central part of the state—the
oil fields of eastern Montana, the lted
!>Jdns on the Indian reservations, the
old time stock ranches in the badlands
sind the grazing districts where the
cowboy is making his last stand, the
mine« and smelters, the Custer, the
Big Ilole and other Indian battlefields,
the gigantic power plants, the numerous
hot springs, the irrigated valleys that
fleck the silent prairies of the eastern
part of the state and the primeval
forests that flauk the bold mountain
ranges of western Montana—these are
some of the attractions from which
the visitor may make his own choice.
Roads and Accommodations
Montana has good roads. Most of
the towns maintain tourist camps. Ac
commodations range from the palatial
hotels of the national parks and the
larger cities to the primitive log cab
ins set in forest wildernesses. Neither
Montana's scenery nor its other at
t rgctions have been commercialized,
(rood highways .have made accessible
good fishing streams, attractive big
pi nie districts and remarkable scenery.
Luxuriously appointed hostelries have
been built, but this is not all. The
forests aud the wild life of the moun
tains. streams and lakes are there to
day as they were in the days when the
• 'row, the Blackfeet :i uni the Flathead
Indians roamed the laud.
The visitor who wants to rough it.
!>ml have a taste of pioneer life, has
the opportunity so to do in Montana.
Hundreds of square miles are to be
found in the mountainous portions of
rhi* state that are uninhabited. Pros
pectors looking for golden treasures,
ihtrepid big game hunters, and forest
rangers are almost the only visitors.
There are no roads and, in many in
stances, not even trails, through these
remote districts. The prospectors
travel afoot, and the hunters, and for
est rangers on horseback, with pack
horses to carry their duffle.
Temperatures Never Oppressive
When the muggv, stifling heat of
other parts of the'country is scarcely
endurable, is the time to come to Mon
tuna. There are very few nights in
u year when the blankets are not de
sirablc. "The summer temperatures
are l ever oppressive," states Bulletin
*{ of the I'nited States weather bu
roan in considering the Montana cli
mate. "During the middle of the long
summer days of this high altitude the
temperature often rises higher than in
the southern suites, but it cools rap
i'llv i:i the evening bv radiation and
HOT NIGHTS ARE NEVER EXPE
RIENCED." The average daily tem
perature for May in Montana is 50.7
degrees. .lune, 00.2 degrees; July, 05.8
<]psr'*ei's; August. O.'Ï.T degrees; Sep
tember. 54.1 degrees, and October, 43.5
degrees.
Another delightful feature of Mon
Auto Purchases Are Financed
Corporation in Great Falls Furnishes Funds to
Complete Sale Between Buyer and Seller.
An important part of the automobile.
industry in Great Falls is the Montana
Auto Finance corporation, organized inj
April. 1020, for the purpose of assist-I
ing iu the financing of the sale of auto
mobiles between the purchasers and
I he dealers,
potation arf
The
»fficers of this cor
Leonard G. Diehl. presi-l
dent; Judjre W. B. Rhoades, vice presi-j
dent : Samuel M. Weekes. secretary.
and Scott Leavitt, treasurer, and has
for a year and lO months conducted
an increas'ng business in auto financing.!
The field for such a financing com-|
pany in Montana was recognized and
a stud\ of the situation revealed that
(iie business for which this corporation;
was intended, was going out of Moil
tana in a large amount. For the
I'nited States as a whole, the service
of financing companies is required in
75 per cent of all purchases of automo
biles, with a result that that there are
many strong financial concerns con
Officers of the Montana Auto Finance Corporation
SCOTT LEAVITT
Treasurer, Montana Auto Finance
Corporation, Great Falls _
. a
LEONARD G. DIEHL
President, Montana Auto Finance
Corporation, Great Falls
« SAMUEL M. WEEKES
Sécretaèy, Montana Auto Finance
Corporation, Great Falls
—
tana's summer climate are the long
sunny days. In this latitude it is pos
sible to read out of doors until almost j
10 o'clock of evenings aud dawn breaks j
around 4 o'clock of summer mornings, j
Wild Animal Life Abundant
There are few places in the north
ern hemisphere that have the wild ani
mal life to be found in Montana. There
are several reasons for this. The Yel
lowstone National park, in the south
ern part of the state, is the largest and
most successful wild animal refuge in
the world. It contains more than 30,
000 elk. several hundred moose, numer
ous bear, innumerable deer, many ante
lope and a large and increasing herd
of buffalo is maintained in its natural
state. In Glacier National park, in the
northern part of the state, is another
big game refuge. In western Montana
is the National Bison range, where a
herd of buffalo is maintained in its
natural state. Elk aud other big game
are also to be found on the range. In
addition to these game preserves there
are 851.000 acres, exclusive of the Sun
River Game preserve, set aside on na
tional forests where hunting is pro
hibited. The last census made by the
supervisors of game on national for
ests in Montana, considered by no
means complet , revealed a count of
13,918 elk. 43.423 deer. 3.453 mountain
goats, 1.S78 moose, 175 antelopes and
30 caribou. It is a common experience
for tourists drivin» through the moun
tains to run across elk, deer or bear j
by the roadside. Grouse and fool hens '
abound in the mountainous districts,
prairie chickens in the grain growing
districts of eastern Montana and sage
hens in the grazing areas. In the fall
hunters find Montana a wild fowl para
dise.
Glories of the Yellowstone
It was the Yellowstone National park
which gave the first big impetus to
tourist travel in the United States and
directed attention to Montana. This
was augmented when the (»lacier Na
tional park was created. While there
•? « wealth of scenery and other attrac
tion» throughout the state, it is oni j
natural that the two paiks lein.nn the
attractions.
The Yellowstone National park, con- |
taining 3,348 square miles and located j
in Montana. Wyoming and Idaho, was
created in 1872. The main entrance,
which was dedicated by President
Roosevelt, is at Gardiner, in Mon- i
tana, along the north boundary. There j
is a western entrance at Yellowstone, j
Mont., and an eastern entrance at Cody, j
Wyo. The Yellowstone is the best j
known of the national parks. Its gey- j
sers are celebrated the world over be
cause for size, power and variety of 1
action, as well as number, the region ,
has no competitor. New Zealand, i
which ranks second, and Iceland, where |
the word "geyser" originated, possess i
the only other geyser bas-.ns of prom- j
fining their activities to this
lass of!
j
j
!
business, located in the principal cities
of the country from const to coast,
Montana has for the last two years
liad a registration of automobiles of|
a little more than 00,<MM>. which indi
eates the large scope of this class of!
! business carried on in the state.
The convenience of doing business at.
home, or within the state, where the
! automobile dealers can quickly get
j touch with a finance company, has been
' a determining factor in nfaking the
local concern a success. >îs capital
is being continually increased and the
j demands for its service have been con-j
; tinually in advance of its capital, which
brings about a healthy situation in any
business. Thus, the Montana Auto
J Finance corporation has been able to.
! play an important part in the general
advance and success of the automobile
business in Great Falls and is con
side red by the automobile men an im
portant adjunct to their own business, i
mt
m
■' J:
AUTOMOBILE ROAD IN GLACIER NATIONAL PARK
j
I
!
!
inence, but both together do not offer
the visitor what he may see in two or
three days in Yellowstone. Looking
downward from Inspiration Point the
Grand Canyon of the Yellowstone of
fers, according to the National park
service, "the most glorious kaledio
scope of color you will ever see in na
ture." Then there are the fossil for
ests along the Lamar river, a succes
sion of them, rising to a height of ap
proximately 2,000 feet above the valley
floor. Each forest grew, only to be
inundated and preserved by a flow of
volcanic
m
.b V ;
m
CHESTER C. DAVIS
Comissioner of Agriculture
lava. These alterations of
voleanism and forest growth continued
throughout the time the beds were in
progress.
„ ..
Noble Mountains of Glacier
The Glacier National park, in north
western Montana, incloses 1,534 square
miles of "the noblest mountain coun
try in America," according to the Na
tional Park service. It was established
in 1910 and its name is derived from
its 00 glaciers. In ruggedness and
sheer grandeur it probably surpasses
the Alps, in the opinion of the park
service, though geologically it is mark
edly différé - ^. It resembles the Cana
dian Rockies more closely than any
other scenic country. The latter have
the advantage of more imposing masses
of snow and ice in summer, but, for
that very reason, Glacier is much more
I
I
j
j
'
easily and comfortably traveled.
"To define Glacier National park,"
says the National Park service, "pic
ture to yourself two approaching
chains of vast tumbled mountains,
which pass the continental divide back
and forth between them in wormlike
twistings, which bear living glaciers, in
every hollow of their loftiest convolu
initions, and which break precipitately
thuosands of feet to iower mountain
masses, which, in their turn, bear in
numerable lakes of unbelievable charm,
offspring of the glaciers above; these
lakes, iii their turn, giving birth to
roaring rivers of icy water, leaping
turbenily from level to level, carving
innumerable sculptured gorges of
grandeur and indescribable beauty." It
is on the east that the scenic quality
of these parallel mountain masses be
come titanic.
Tourists in quest of knowledge and
pleasure are urged by the National
Park service to spend a month or
more camping out in the Glacier park.
Once off the excellent trails in the
developed part of the park, wild ani
mals are more frequent and tamer,
fishing is finer, and" the federal park
officials assert many of the valleys
have not been thoroughly explored, and
some of them never have been entered
unless possibly by Indians • from the
Blackfeet reservation adjoining the
park on the east.
Visit Both Parks
Tourists visiting one of the parks
in Montana will make a mistake if they
do not visit tlie other while in the
northwest. The railroads this year are
offering combination tickets from east
ern points permitting the tourist to
come west by the wa.T of the Glacier
National park, thence to the Yellow
stone and eastward and vice versa.
The only thing the two parks have in
common is that they are national parks.
Scenery, topography, everything is
different. The parks are approximately
400 miles apart. The big motor busses
of the transportation companies make
the trip in two days with <i night stop
over at Helena. It is an easy and de
lightful three day trip for the private
automobile with much to see on the
way. Four alternative routes are
offered, each of which holds specia'
attractions for the visitor. In connec
tion with this phase of the matter,
the director of the National Park ser
vice in his 1020 report says: "All of
the states offer exceptional smaller
circle tours within the limits of their
respective boundaries, which will con
siderably distribute the interpark travel
through their different communiHes as
it passes from one park to the other.
Particularly is this true of Montana,
whose cross-state roads are being ex
tensively developed."
Highways Into Montana
There are three main east and west
transcontinental highways traversing
Montana, three main north and south
direct interpark highways, and a fourth
north and south highway that swings
northwesterly from Billings through
the best developed oil field of the
state to Glacier park and is part of
the Custer Battlefield Hiway.
The visitor from the east, if he
comes from Duluth, Superior or other
northern Minnesota or northern Wis
consin points, can follow the Roose
velt highway which enters Montana at
Highway Covers 6,000 Miles
Y-G Bee Line, Link of National Park to Park
Highway, Goes Through Great Falls.
The National Park to Park highway
is In many ways unique among the na
tionally important highways of the
United States. This is the only such
highway to which the National govern
ment.. acting through the officers of
the National Park service, has given
official recognition, and it did this be
cause the movement was intended to
link together the national parks of the
west, there making theni more access
ible and, therefore, more attractive.
The national parks arc the best ad
vertised and most - universally known
places in the western United States, if
not in the United States as a whole.
The advertising has been carried on in
magazine articles, school test books,
government publications, railroad pub
licity matter, publications of cities,
towns aijd stales, and in fact through
almost every known medium of pub
licity over a period of many years. The
length of this advertising varies from
a few years in the case of some of the
new national parks. Kuchvffi\the Gla
cier. over a period of nearly a half
a century in the case of the Yellow
stone. The result is that there is
a great desire rn the minds of many
millions of people, not only in the
United States, but also in Europe, to
sec the American national parks.
Highway 6,000 Milos in Length
Taking advantage of this situation,
a highway was worked out to make
these parks accessible and to connect
them with each other, resulting in the
stimulating of the desire to see not
only one but all of the national parks.
This highway, known as the National
Bark to Park highway, leads from one
to another in a great circle approxi
mately 0,000 miles in length. The
travelers following this great master
highway are ultimately taken into and
through so much of the west, drawn
on by the lure of the national parks,
that all portions of the west are profit
ing. not only from the rich harvest
of the tour'^'t travel, but from the fact
that a very large percent of such
travelers are attracted to different
locations and become pemanent settlers i
and residents.
Within the great circle of the Na
tional Park to Park highway itself,
other highways lead across like the
spokes of a wheel, with Salt Lake as
the hub, and the National Park to
Park highway is also intersected by
every great trans-continental highway
leading in from the east.
The National Park to Park highway
leads through 11 of the western states
and links together Glacier National
Park in Montana. Mt. ltanier National
park in Washington, Crater Lake Na
tional park in Oregon. Mt. Lassen,
Yoscmite, and Sequoia (Big Trees) Nu
Bainville, follows the Great Northern
westward through the Milk River val
ley touching Glasgow. Malta, Dodson,
Chinook and Havre, then on to Shelby
and Cut Bank, through the Blackfeet
Indian reservation to Glacier National
park. The automobile must be
shipped by rail from Glacier Park sta
tion over the continental divide to
Belton. the western entrance to
j Glacier. The Roosevelt highway
I then goes through one of the most
! beautiful parts of the state, touch
ing Kalispell, Marion. Libby and Troy
! into Idaho by way of Bonner's Ferry
and thence westward to Spokane and
the coast.
Tourists from St. Paul, Minneapolis,
Milwaukee, Chicago and points east
ward have their choice of two routes,
the National Parks highway or the
Yellowstone trail. The National
Parks highway goes from Chicago by
way of Milwaukee, through LaCrosse
to the Twin Cities, and thence through
St. Cloud and Fargo into Montana by
way of Yates. Wibaux and Glen
<live. The Yellowstone trail ctomes
westward from Chicago by way of
Milwaukee through Oshkosh and Eau
Claire to the Twin Cities and thence
through Montevideo, Milbank and
Aberdeen into Montana by way of
Baker. Ismay and Fallon. From
Fallon these two trails follow the
same highway through Montana, wind
ing westward up the fertile Yellow
stone to Livingston, where the road
branches southward to Gardiner, the
main entrance to the Yellowstone
National park. Snow-capped moun
tains rim the rich and irrigated val
ley of the Gallatin as the main road
continues west from Livingston
through Boreman. Belgrade and Man
hattan to the Wiree forks of the Mis
souri, discovered and named Three
Forks by Lewis and Clark on the
memorable expedition that opened to
the I'nited Stales the northwestern
countrv. Here the road forks, the
southern fork going by way of White
hall. Butte, Anaconda and Deer Lodge,
over the main range to Garrison, and
the northern fork going by way of
either Townsend or Boulder through
Helena to Garrison. It was a short
distance west of Garrison that gold
was first discovered in 1852 in what
is now Montana. The highway darts
westward Missoula through the
cam-on of the Hellgate river and a
short distance beyond Missoula again
forks, tha southern fork following the
St Regis river through Superior and
St Regis to Wallace, Ida., and thence
to Spokane and points west. I he
northern fork follows the Cark s fork
of the Columbia through Ravalli and
Thompson Falls to Sand Point, Ida.,
and thence to Spokane.
From Omaha and Sioux Falls
Another highway from the east of
increasing importance is the Custer
Battlefield highway which, starting at
Omaha, runs north Sioux ï alls,
thence due west across South Dakota,
northwesterlv through the picturesque
Black Hills,'and across Wyoming into
Montana *t Wyola. It traverses the
Crow Indian reservation, passes the
Custer Battlefeild where Custer and
his entire command were wiped out by
the Indians in *1870, and intersects
the Yellowstone .and National Parks
highway at Billings. From Billings it
goes northward to Roundup, the scene
of the first oil activity in Montana,
and then to Grass Range, where a
road runs east a few miles to the Cat
Creek oil field. I.ewistown. the cen
ter of the prosperous Judith Basin
country, is 'he largest town on the
route between Billings and Great
Falls. The road continues northwes
terly out of Lewistown through the
tional parks in «California, Grand Can
yon National park in Arizona. Mesa
Verde (Cliff Dwellings) and Rocky
Mountain National parks in Colorado,}
Zion National park in Utah, and Yel-j
Iowstone National park iu Wyoming
and Montana. In addition it links to
gether 20 national forests and runs
through 12 of the largest industrial
cities and travel centers of the west.
besides approximately 150 towns and
villages of lesser importance.
Headquarters al Denver
The headquarters of this highway
association are at Denver, where Gus
Ilolms. formerly of Cody. Y\ yo„ has
an office as secretary anil general man
ager. The other officers are Scott
Leavitt of Great Falls, president; Syl
vester L. Weaver, who is president
of the Los Angeles Chamber of Com
merce and president of the Weaver
Roof Manufacturing company of that
city, and Father C. Yabre. of Flagstaff.
Arizona, who is one of the leading good
roads advocates in the southwest, vice
presidents ; and F. J. Chamberlain,
Denver, Colorado, businessman, treas
urer. Chairman of the board of di
rectors is Charles Tyng, of Salt Lake
City. Utah. Mr. Tyng is a very prom
inent business man and is well known
to the Rotarians of the entire country.
L. L. Newton, of Cody. Wyo., the secre
tary of the board of directors, is a
prominent merchant and newspaperman
and is president of the Wyoming Good
Roads association. The remainder of
the board of directors is as follows:
Dr. S. F. Way, of Livingston, Mont..;
Dr. J. E. McDermond, of Poeatello,
Ida.; Robert >1. Dyer, of Seattle,
Wash.; Sydney B. Vincent, of Port
land. Ore.; W. M. Welsh, of Ivennett,
Calif.; W. II. Goodin, of Lovelock,
Nev. ; Judge L. V. Root, of Winslow,
Ariz.; Col. D. lv. B. Sellers. Albu
qjerque, N. M.; and G. V. llodgin, of
Canon City, Colo.
This highway, therefore, gives Great
Falls a community of interest with the
highway movement of the entire west.
It joins in a co-operative endeavor
with such cities as Spokane, Seattle,
Portland, San Francisco, Los Angeles,
and Denver, in the promotion of a
movement to develop the resources of
the western states, building on the
attractiveness of the national parks as
the foundation to bring many people
into these states. In the annual report
to the secretary of the interior, cover
ing the 1021 travel season, Hon.
Stephen T. Mather, director of the Na
tional Park service, of -Washington.
D. C., said, "The designation ill 1920
of the National Park to Park highway,
which touche* in one fcteat circle the
major national parks of -the, west, has
undoubtedly stimulated motor travel." 4
HH
m
MT. WASHBURN IN YELLOWSTONE NATIONAL PARK
,
j
Judith Basin by way of Raynesford,
Armington and Belt into Great Falls,
and by Fairfield, Choteau. Dupuyer
and Browning to the eastern entrance
of the Glacier National park.
Park to Park Routes
The most easterly Glacier-Yellow
stone Park highway is that called the
Y-G-Bee Line, running northerly from
Gardiner through Livingston, Clyde,
Park, White Sulphur Springs, Raynes- j
ford. Great Falls, Choteau and Brown- I
ing to the western entrance of Glacier j
park. I
The central route between these
two parks connects with the western j
or Yellowstone entrance, as well as j
the northern or Gardiner entrance to j
the wonderland. From the Yellow- i
stone entrance the route runs nor- I
therlv through the Madison national |
forest, Virginia City—rich in historical j
lore of the vigilante days—Twin
Bridges. Whitehall. Butte, Helena and
Wolf Creek. Here the rciad forks, the
western fork passing through Augusta.
Gilman. Choteau and Browning to the
western entrance of the Glacier park
and the eastern fork to Cascade and
Great Falls, and from there to Cho
teau and the Glacier park. From the
northern entrance the road runs north
to Livingston, and thence follows the
east and west highway to either
Butte or Helena.
While not. a main road, one of the
most beautiful approaches to the Yel- !
iowstone park is from Bozeman
southerly up the Gallatin river to
Yellowstone station.
The most westerly interpark high
way begins at Yellowstone and skirts
More Miles
From Old Tires
We can make your old tires give you
more miles—enough miles to more than
pay for the necessary repair.
Your worn tires will receive the un
varyingly careful attention of skilled re
pairmen in our vulcanizing shop.
We use the highest quality repair ma
terial and all our work is done in an
expert way.
That means that you will be com
pletely satisfied.
Bring us your worn casings, 'we can
put more miles into them.
Ever Ready
Vulcanizing Co.
Dealers in
705 Central Ave.
u.
S. Tires and Tubes
Phone 6161.
v..
westerly along the base of the conti
nental divide to Monida and then
swings northerly to Dillon, north
westerly from there, through the Big
Hole basin, past the Big Hole Battle
field where the ' Nez Perces were de
feated in 1876, and into the Bitter
Root valley, one of the most at
tractive scenically and highly de
veloped places agriculturally in the
state. The road follows the Bitter
Root river past farm and orchard
through Hamilton and Stevensville
into Missoula, and thence goes almost
due north across the Flathead Indian
reservation where the glistening peaks
of the stately Mission range stand
sentinel over the tourist every mile of
the way until Flathead lake is reached,
This is one of the largest fresh water
lakes west of the Mississippi, and the
traveler has the option of following
either the western or eastern shore
boulevard road into Kalispell, from
there to Columbia Falls and thence to
Belton. the western entrance to the
Glacier park.
.Every Mile Interesting
Every mile of the way is something
worth seeing on any of these highways.
Each of them abounds in good fishing
streams, impressive mountain ranges
and scenes and incidents inseparably
connected with the early history of
the west. Equally true is this .of the
Custer battlefield highway through
Montana, which- is the route x>ersons
especially interested m the developed
oil fields of the state should take
There are many worth while side j
trips- South of Billings, in Carbon i
county, for instance, is the Beartooth j
plateau in the Beartooth National
forest. It is accessible only to pack
horses, which may be procured at Red
Lodge. Two days' steady climbing up
the mountains brings one to the pla
teau, a waste of granite, lakes and
small glaciers that is literally "the roof
of the world." One glacier, called the
Grasshopper, derives its name from the
fact that millions of these insects are
embedded in the crystal clear ice. 4
The great rolling prairies of eastern
Montana, formerly the greatest "cow
country," are a never ending place of
fascination to the "visitor. There are
also many spots of beauty and excel
lent camping grounds in the badlands
and along the rivers.
The western part of the state has
much fascination for the tourist be
cause of its mountains and lakes.
Flathead lake, one of the largest fresh
water lakes in the country, aside from
tlie Great Lakes, is becoming famous
lake has a short line of 300 miles
as a heme for summer colonies. The
and steamers operate on its waters.
The Kootenai country through Lin
coln county is unexcelled for beauti
ful, peaceful valleys and towering pic
turesque mountains, covered with dense
pine forests. The Blackfoot valley,
which follows the canyon'of the Big
Blackfoot river in Missoula county,
between towering wooded mountains of
great beauty, is attractive as a vaca
tion spot.
Of equal beauty and fascination la
the Missouri river canyon in Lewis ;
and Clark county from Canyon Ferry !
dam to the Holter power dam and the
"Gates of the Mountains." For scenic ,
splendor this is unexcelled. The fam- !
ous Gallatin valley is rich in natural
scenery. The "Gallatin Way," lead
ing to Yellowstone park, is one of the
most beautiful of drives.
Sanders county is noted for its
trout fishing streams, great areas of
virgin forests and its wealth of wild
life. Camp sites are available at beau
tiful mountain lakes- The Belt and
Highwood canyons in Cascade county,
the beauties of Madison county, the
Lewis and Clark Cavern, the mountain
drives of Jefferson county, the Bitter
Root and Hell Gate valleys, the mines
at Butte, the state fish hatcheries, the
big smelters, the gigantic power dams,
the lumber mills, offer diversification
that delights the traveler.
NEWSPAPERS AND MUD HOLES
It is not an unusual thing to become
stuck in a mudhole, especially at this
time of the year. Carry a few old
newspapers in one of the pockets or
under the seats. They afford good
traction for the wheels and will as
sist greatly when pulling out of the
mud. Never speed up the engine and
"jump" the clutch. This will only
cause the wheels to spin and dig deeper
into the mud.
An American-made passenger auto
m obile recently won first place in a
430-mile reliability contest, conducted
under the auspices of the Royal Au
toinobile club of Norway. There were
80 cars iu the field, representing two
continents.
        </text>
      </result>
    </results>
  </topic>
</topics>
